SPK_1: песочный интерес
SPK_0: Паш, привет, но пока мы еще, видать, на брудершафт не выпили
SPK_2: Ну, давайте, да, собственно, перейдем к новостям
SPK_0: Павел, а тебя кто-нибудь называет вообще Пашей?
SPK_0: Вот так, знаешь, по-небратски кто-нибудь
SPK_0: Паш, ну хватит
SPK_0: Есть такие, да?
SPK_2: Супруга, я так думаю
SPK_1: Да, конечно
SPK_0: Я говорю так, прям вот в СМИ
SPK_2: Не, в СМИ, вот ни разу не слышала
SPK_1: И не только супруга, а в СМИ нет
SPK_2: Ну и мы не будем, отец Павел
SPK_0: Лучше меня в СМИ не называть, так как меня супруга называет
SPK_2: Наверное, да
SPK_2: На самом деле, тема-то серьезная
SPK_2: И чего мы смеемся, отец Павел, почему вы смеетесь?
SPK_0: Потому что мы христиане
SPK_2: И нам все равно?
SPK_0: Нет, нам не все равно
SPK_0: У нас просто, помимо плохих новостей, всегда есть очень много хороших
SPK_0: Мы стоим на фундаменте очень хорошей новости
SPK_0: Радостной новости, да?
SPK_0: То, что называется Евангелие
SPK_0: Ну, Полин, просто благая весть, радостная весть, понимаете?
SPK_2: Я понимаю
SPK_2: И надо сказать, что в тот момент, когда наши слушатели и зрители это все увидят
SPK_2: Уже закончится третья неделя
SPK_0: Закончится все
SPK_2: Нет, нет, ну я надеюсь, что нет
SPK_2: Но третья неделя Великого Поста
SPK_2: Закончится точно
SPK_2: И станет еще ближе Пасха
SPK_2: Но начнем с новостей, которые, на самом деле, последнюю неделю
SPK_2: Будоражат умы, сердца тех, кто смотрит новости, наверное
SPK_2: С Ирана
SPK_2: И я начну не с вопроса, а с утверждения
SPK_2: И потом можете его прокомментировать
SPK_2: Если можно, можно я так сделаю
SPK_2: Потому что я долго думала, что спросить
SPK_2: Но я вот наблюдаю последнюю неделю за всем происходящим
SPK_2: И вам, Павел, наверное, очевиднее, как это все в США выглядит
SPK_2: И об этом я тоже хотела вас потом спросить
SPK_2: Но вот есть Трамп, который вот сегодня, в день записи этого эфира
SPK_2: Сказал, что он всех победил вообще
SPK_2: И выиграл все, что можно выиграть
SPK_2: Но при этом из Ирана не уйдет, потому что надо бы довести до конца
SPK_0: Как пара Олимпиады, получается
SPK_2: Ну, возможно, не знаю
SPK_2: И при этом есть Иран, который выбрал Пару Олимпиаду
SPK_2: Новую Айталу
SPK_2: И кажется, вот просто на уровне ощущений
SPK_2: Вы уж простите, я перейду вот в такую плоскость
SPK_2: На уровне ощущений мне кажется, что он проигрывает
SPK_2: Несмотря на превосходство США в воздухе
SPK_2: Несмотря на то, что вроде бы там какие-то невероятные бомбежки
SPK_2: Каждый день анонсируются все больше и больше и больше
SPK_2: И у меня в связи с этим возникла гипотеза о том, что так происходит
SPK_2: Из-за того, что...
SPK_2: За Ираном, вот на каком-то таком тонком уровне
SPK_2: Стоит что-то большее, чем за США
SPK_2: Потому что в США мы видим, как выкладываются ролики
SPK_2: Про бомбежку Ирана под музыку из Макарены
SPK_2: А все-таки Айталу выбирает Совет Старейшин
SPK_2: Все-таки это как будто бы разный немножко калинкор
SPK_2: Вот так ли это?
SPK_2: Верно ли это ощущение?
SPK_2: Верна ли это гипотеза моя?
SPK_2: Я думаю, что в принципе...
SPK_2: Иран, возможно, даже может быть и победит в этом конфликте
SPK_1: Ух, ну про тонкий мир у нас священник пусть лучше скажет
SPK_1: Я просто прокомментирую, что происходит
SPK_1: На самом деле, христианину довольно...
SPK_1: Если мы внимательно читаем Писание
SPK_1: Нам очень легко распознать некоторые закономерности политической реальности
SPK_1: И вот сегодня на примере вот этой войны
SPK_1: Мы видим очередное проявление истины из Богородичной песни
SPK_1: Где это...
SPK_1: Благословен Господь, который...
SPK_1: Рассеял надменных помышлениями их сердец
SPK_1: Вот вся та вот эта странная, скажем так, позиция
SPK_1: Которую вы наблюдаете вокруг Пресетского залива
SPK_1: Ее корни лежат в очень простой страсти
SPK_1: В которой отец Павел постоянно исповедует всех к нему приходящих, наверное
SPK_1: Гордыня надменная
SPK_1: Потому что биполярочка это не очень хорошее состояние
SPK_1: Для принятия политических решений
SPK_1: А американская политическая стратегия строилась на примерно...
SPK_1: В следующих взаимопротиворечащих утверждениях
SPK_1: С одной стороны, Иран это абсолютное исчадие зла
SPK_1: Там вот это все 40 лет Death to America
SPK_1: Мулы, зло и прочее
SPK_1: А с другой стороны, да как они посмели бить по нашим базам в окружающих странах
SPK_1: Понимаете, что это два утверждения, которые являются полностью противоречивы относительно друг друга
SPK_1: Но они прекрасно удерживаются в одной голове
SPK_1: И вот на этом разрыве, соответственно, и происходит вот этот акт рассеивания
SPK_1: Что твои планы приводят к последствиям, которые, мягко говоря, ты не ожидал
SPK_1: Обратится болезнь его на главу его, наверх его неправда его снедит
SPK_1: Ну то есть у тебя неадекватное представление о реальности
SPK_1: Ты неправильно оценил противника, мягко говоря
SPK_1: Ну, условно говоря, план мы сейчас всех переубиваем, как было в первый день
SPK_1: И вы тут выйдете свергать свой собственный режим
SPK_1: И становиться нашей колонией
SPK_1: Внезапно что-то пошло не по плану
SPK_1: И проблема-то в том, что плана Б нет, да?
SPK_1: То есть почему вот это все выглядит сейчас смешно?
SPK_1: Заявление о победах, потому что, очевидно, это как в русском, знаете, такой присказке
SPK_1: Я медведя поймал, так иди, он меня не пускает
SPK_1: То есть можно, конечно, очень долго заявлять о том, что я победил Иран
SPK_1: Проблема в том, что нужно, чтобы еще Иран хотя бы перестал делать те действия
SPK_1: Которые не позволяют тебе заявить о своей победе
SPK_1: То есть заявить-то, конечно, можно, но сложно заявлять о своей победе с перегрытым армузским проливом
SPK_1: А вот здесь наступает фундаментальная проблема
SPK_1: Что заставить Иран снять плакаду армузского пролива военным путем сейчас невозможно
SPK_1: Это можно сделать политическим путем, но для этого надо заплатить очень много
SPK_1: Ну, то есть, а это и есть поражение
SPK_1: То есть критерий победы и поражения, он же определяется относительно целей войны
SPK_1: Для США цель была простая
SPK_1: Смена режима в Иране на дружественной и взятие под контроль иранской нефти
SPK_1: Ну, то есть, чтобы это США определяло, сколько, куда, когда иранской нефти пойдет на рынок
SPK_1: Ну, такая Бенесуэла 2.0
SPK_1: Очевидно, что эти цели, они не будут в Иране
SPK_1: Цели не достигнуты
SPK_1: Проблема в том, как отползти с минимальными потерями
SPK_1: Но вот сейчас сделать это, мягко говоря, будет крайне сложно
SPK_1: Потому что, ну, как вы понимаете, человек, у которого убили всю семью, не очень склонен договариваться
SPK_2: Это правда
SPK_1: У него вот есть маленький, скажем так, зуб на вот эту историю, да
SPK_1: И, как минимум, то, что ходит в слух
SPK_1: Даже вот сегодняшнее сейчас было выступление
SPK_1: По сути, он ставит вопрос радикально о выводе американских баз с территории региона
SPK_1: О выплате репараций
SPK_1: Ирану со стороны США и Израиля
SPK_1: И тут, как в анекдоте, вы когда последний раз видели, чтобы Америка кому-то что-то платила, да?
SPK_1: То есть все эти условия становятся практически политически невозможными
SPK_1: Но цена продолжения конфликта в длинную для США выше
SPK_1: В этом вот такая загогуля
SPK_1: На все началось с того, что у вас в голове было два неправильных утверждения
SPK_1: Ну, это вот российским зрителям это знакомо
SPK_1: Это как очень популярное такое размышление
SPK_1: То, что Владимир Путин одновременно является дедом России
SPK_1: Который прячется в бункере со страха
SPK_1: Но при этом же он управляет всем миром
SPK_1: Вот как эти две, скажем так, тезисы
SPK_1: Соответственно, существуют в одной и той же оппозиционной или аналитической голове
SPK_1: Понять сложно, но прекрасно вот существуют
SPK_1: То есть вся европейская дипломатия на этом строится
SPK_1: Россия крайне слаба, поэтому нам надо вооружиться и ее деколонизировать
SPK_1: Но при этом Россия очень страшная и опасная
SPK_1: И если мы не объединимся, она нас съест
SPK_1: Вот вам краткое содержание этих биполярчик
SPK_0: Я думаю, что, ну, как бы это дисклеймер сразу
SPK_0: Что я, как бы, конечно, очень могу ошибаться
SPK_0: Ну, такой своей мысли вслух
SPK_0: Что мы просто еще, в целом, мир еще до конца не дошел
SPK_0: До стадии полного отрицания международного права
SPK_0: Еще где-то что-то сохраняется, какие-то последние иллюзии
SPK_0: Поэтому мир не перешел еще к тем войнам, которые были в старые добрые времена
SPK_0: Когда вырезалось просто все
SPK_0: Население, женщины, французы
SPK_0: he is a woman in captivity, men kill everyone, preferably boys, yes, that is, full submission and
SPK_0: destruction is a victory, but if they surrendered to slavery, yes, well, okay, maybe someone
SPK_0: will be spared, but at some point it happened that it seems as if they began to pity the world for the population,
SPK_0: but weapons of mass destruction are considered evil and so on, so it seems to me that we are moving
SPK_0: in that direction when, well, the last stoppers will finally be removed and people will already start
SPK_0: fighting like in the good old days when you just dig up just the population, and everyone will
SPK_0: already care about it, and in the same time, it seems to me that the Americans may end up in such a situation
SPK_0: that they will pay for the repair, it will be a shame to disgrace the base, this is also a defeat, well,
SPK_0: as it were, why not repeat it with the first
SPK_0: time you canới первое скрыть вы знаете отсюда на счет власть местных
SPK_1: capitalist table и тогда все эти базы очень workspace то есть ну можете конечно все это
SPK_1: посбрасывать но проблема это не решит потому что бы тем самым только гарантируете стирание
SPK_1: государства израиль уже с этой скажем так территории нет там сейчас хороших вариантов
SPK_1: нет это вот проблема то что вся стратегия
SPK_1: was hanging on about absolutely this, you know, very such a protestant idea of ​​election, yes, that we are
SPK_1: elected, we can and we can't get it, I'm not a fool, I can do it, why look at point 1,
SPK_1: that's about it, well, the boss is always right and what to do if the boss is wrong, look at point 1, America
SPK_1: always wins what to do if America loses, look at point 1, here you have, according to this logic, it
SPK_1: all kind of goes around, but here there is a nuance and its comments that this is what
SPK_1: they are old good times here, in fact, we do not agree here 20th century was much less humane than
SPK_1: for example century 19 if you look at this especially less humane than by 2018 at the
SPK_1: beginning of total capitulation, it is the consequence of n idea of ​​exception of the war if you look at
SPK_1: the medieval wars it was absolutely normal to fight for ten years then conclude
SPK_1: status in turn, but the idea of ​​extinction right after the end of the century the idea of ​​extinction the idea of ​​extinction the idea of ​​extinction the idea of ​​extinction war if you look at the medieval war it was absolutely normal可以 воевать 10 лет потом заключить перелаживать в hugely неожиданный мир
SPK_1: world for 10 years after which the war is automatically prolonged the state of the war today we live in the
SPK_1: world when there is no war, you will notice that because of him no one can declare a war to anyone,
SPK_1: that is, the United States cannot declare a war to Iran, Russia cannot declare a war to Ukraine, Ukraine cannot even
SPK_1: declare a war to Russia, and even Iran did not declare a war to the United States, that is, no one is with whom, as it were,
SPK_1: does not fight this war, but this creates this impossibility, in fact, the conclusion of a normal
SPK_1: agreement, because if there is no war, there is no agreement for a double line to Grandma mah vogiesheva, here, too,
SPK_1: here is the reverse such some kind of dependence as a result we actually do everything through a little
SPK_1: such an infinite no war and no world the whole world becomes 1 1 ha a global wild field of
SPK_1: the world a global gray zone of war space space of the world is notThat is, it is really important
SPK_1: what is happening now, a triumph ma rimose triumph of Trotskyism, but now I have a question about the괙
SPK_2: fate of the exit from this, you probably wanted to 춘DE it to start
SPK_2: but it didn't work out, because it seems to be initially...
SPK_2: Well, there are different hypotheses about the origin of power,
SPK_2: but one of them says that a person who took power
SPK_2: took responsibility for the people he represents in front of the Lord.
SPK_2: Obviously, looking at the USA,
SPK_2: although despite the fact that it's really a Protestant idea and so on,
SPK_2: it doesn't seem like it's like that there.
SPK_2: In the case of Iran, there's a little bit more of an impression that it's like that.
SPK_2: Well, maybe. It's, again, maybe, it seems to me.
SPK_2: And I'll just ask the second question right away.
SPK_2: Is there anything here that just in the end,
SPK_2: in the current transition of the world that is happening now,
SPK_2: will those countries win, where the power will take on this sacred function?
SPK_1: There will be. There will be a short answer,
SPK_1: but the question is whether we will survive.
SPK_1: I think we will survive with you until this time,
SPK_1: because now you need... How do I explain it to you?
SPK_1: Well, generations of grown-ups, rulers,
SPK_1: who, to put it mildly, were overthrown by the tsars all over the world for this.
SPK_1: That is, in general, the idea of ​​dividing power and responsibility
SPK_1: is the main idea of ​​all Masonic revolutions, starting with the Great French Revolution.
SPK_1: Well, including the October Revolution and all these stories.
SPK_1: What was the point?
SPK_1: The monarch has a very clear responsibility before God.
SPK_1: The aristocracy doesn't really want to serve.
SPK_1: That is...
SPK_1: They are oligarchs, they are aristocrats, they are high officials, and so on, and so on.
SPK_1: Therefore, historically, they have always been very tempted by this task.
SPK_1: And let's save the power and shift the responsibility, including the people.
SPK_1: If anything, the people will be to blame for everything.
SPK_1: He didn't choose those.
SPK_1: Well, you chose them yourself, he wanted to.
SPK_1: And this was the system, it was formulated for centuries, as it were.
SPK_1: And now, for it to change at some point, voluntarily, no.
SPK_1: Unfortunately, I'm afraid,
SPK_1: there are only pain, bloodshed, and grumbling.
SPK_1: Well, that is, you are right, of course.
SPK_1: The question is whether we will survive to this time.
SPK_1: I fully agree that at the end of this entire period of the Thirty Years' War,
SPK_1: or however long God has measured it, only those will survive,
SPK_1: where the authorities will take, including themselves,
SPK_1: sacred responsibility for those over whom they rule.
SPK_1: It's very optimistic, you could say.
SPK_1: Well, how optimistic he is.
SPK_1: On the subject of optimism, you know, we even have an apocalypse.
SPK_1: We are destined to meet with optimism.
SPK_1: Oh, my God, Hagrid.
SPK_1: Oh, my God, Jesus, Varanath.
SPK_1: Although there are events happening, to put it mildly,
SPK_1: just like you are watching the news right now.
SPK_1: That is, this is such a subtlety of the state.
SPK_1: But from a political point of view, it should be understood that the entire system of democracy
SPK_1: exists only in order to divide power and responsibility for power.
SPK_1: That is, your thesis is extremely anti-democratic.
SPK_1: Well, if anything.
SPK_1: And this, after 1945, we all signed into the Constitution.
SPK_1: That is, to put it mildly, it is difficult to refuse this.
SPK_1: It is difficult to refuse this.
SPK_1: Although there will be no other way out.
SPK_1: But first they will try everything they can.
SPK_1: Artificial intelligence, censorship, control over the population, and so on, and so on, and so on.
SPK_1: As long as you don't take responsibility.
SPK_1: But in the end, only those who will take responsibility will survive.
SPK_1: Yes.
SPK_0: I look more apocalyptic, but not in the sense of some wars and so on,
SPK_0: but in the sense of what the Holy Patriarch said when he said that artificial intelligence
SPK_0: will be an apocalyptic challenge to human freedom.
SPK_0: After all, there is a famous fairy tale, and the king is naked.
SPK_0: That is, thanks to mass media, in general, the population in the world,
SPK_0: in civilized countries, has seen what power is in reality.
SPK_0: And what people are in reality.
SPK_0: And this is not even a matter of Heppstein's list, but in general, just how smart, wise, competent the power is.
SPK_0: Especially considering that people have recently started giving a lot of interviews, making remarks
SPK_0: in social networks, comments.
SPK_0: This also applies to Russia.
SPK_0: That is, the discreditation of the State Duma is just incredible.
SPK_0: That is, there are, of course, smart deputies who do a lot of good, useful things.
SPK_0: But those comments of various officials, they just put everything down to zero.
SPK_0: And it seems to me that at some point people will be disappointed in the human rule over themselves.
SPK_0: And it will simply be proposed.
SPK_0: Well, first of all, such attempts have already been made.
SPK_0: But it will simply be proposed, that is, some kind of management of the artificial intelligence,
SPK_0: which will still be behind a person, it is clear.
SPK_0: We will not see these kings anymore.
SPK_0: That is, the artificial intelligence, for example, will be called to put on the king.
SPK_0: So that no one could undress him.
SPK_0: And the power will be covered with artificial intelligence.
SPK_0: But people will be calm, because it will be ...
SPK_0: Well, in short, in simple words, if the radio listener does not quite understand,
SPK_0: it is like a camera on the street.
SPK_0: That is, once there were HBDD employees, with whom you can always negotiate.
SPK_0: And people, in principle, drove as they wanted.
SPK_0: I remember the 90s perfectly well.
SPK_0: Then cameras appeared.
SPK_0: And the movement became normal.
SPK_1: But over the long run, I will say right away, it will not work with the authorities.
SPK_1: For one simple reason.
SPK_1: Because they will not negotiate with each other.
SPK_1: That is, the problem is that such a system kills trust.
SPK_1: That is, this algorithm, it actually exists for that.
SPK_1: So that you don't have to trust.
SPK_1: And when trust is killed, there is no ability to cope with an emergency situation.
SPK_1: And emergency situations, the main one of which is war,
SPK_1: will not happen anywhere in human nature.
SPK_1: Because each of the authorities will not consider others as people anyway.
SPK_1: Okay, that they, conditionally, do not consider those who rule as people.
SPK_1: But conditionally speaking, conditionally Biden, conditionally Trump,
SPK_1: will never consider Mulu as a person.
SPK_1: And Putin will not consider him as a person or a collective either.
SPK_1: Therefore, they will not negotiate.
SPK_1: And this is why this process of natural selection will take place.
SPK_1: At the same time, what my father-in-law wrote with artificial intelligence,
SPK_1: is that now they think that this is such a sword and hammer,
SPK_1: which will allow them to avoid solving the problem that I talked about at the beginning.
SPK_1: It won't work, but this will take a few, maybe decades,
SPK_1: but I don't think it will take that long, in fact.
SPK_1: They think it will be much faster.
SPK_2: And how does it all look from the inside?
SPK_2: Here in the USA, in general, I understand that the average statistician
SPK_2: in the USA is not so much interested in what is happening outside his headquarters.
SPK_2: That is, there is no such thing that they bombed a school for girls,
SPK_2: everyone was outraged, because I, for example,
SPK_2: I can only listen to Tucker Carlson, who still speaks on this topic,
SPK_2: but I don't know how much...
SPK_1: But he is the only one, you know, he was specially marginalized for this.
SPK_1: Tucker Carlson is a person with a large, so to speak, of course, number of subscribers,
SPK_1: but on a large political level, he is an exception.
SPK_1: And the Americans, in general, well, there is irritation, they don't like the fact that gasoline is growing on gas stations.
SPK_1: This is important, this is unpleasant.
SPK_1: And this kind of Russian type of compassion for the outside world is not at all typical for the Americans.
SPK_1: The other thing is that this does not matter.
SPK_1: Accordingly, decisions are made based on other logics.
SPK_1: How decisions are made, for example, the logic of this group of pastors, dispensationalists,
SPK_1: who want to speed up the apocalypse by building the Third Temple, this is important.
SPK_1: They have a business in this region.
SPK_1: But in general, the Americans have nothing to do with it.
SPK_1: And since they have nothing to do with it, their opinion, let's say, is the secret of Polichinelli,
SPK_1: who do not tell them that, in principle, yes, the opinion...
SPK_1: It always turns out that they are all against the war.
SPK_1: That is, every president says, I will end the voids, but all the voids continue for some reason.
SPK_1: Well, that's exactly what continues, because real clans are a real group of interests,
SPK_1: and there is a business for the region, but the Americans don't. That's all.
SPK_0: Well, I'll go back a little bit about the fact that they don't agree.
SPK_0: It seems to me that...
SPK_0: When people agree, that's when motivation appears.
SPK_0: The threat of loss in general, in general, of power,
SPK_0: taking into account the fact that it is clear that both the wars that are taking place
SPK_0: and the tension in the whole world that is growing,
SPK_0: it can lead to the fact that the highest circles, which, for example, I don't know at all,
SPK_0: but they are in any case those people who do not listen to us now, I think,
SPK_0: they will not listen to us at all.
SPK_0: It's a temptation, it's a temptation that people can be controlled in this way.
SPK_0: I will give a simple example, which, well, it's not that it surprises me,
SPK_0: but it is unpleasantly surprising, that now on measured YouTube a lot of channels have appeared,
SPK_0: which are called Father Dmitry or Father Anatoly or something else,
SPK_0: which exist for literally two or three months.
SPK_0: They have somewhere tens of thousands of subscribers,
SPK_0: somewhere already hundreds of thousands of subscribers.
SPK_0: This is from the beginning to the end of artificial intelligence, from the beginning to the end.
SPK_0: The priests preach, well, it's not priests, it's IEA, they preach perfectly, everything is beautifully shot.
SPK_0: To be honest, even in some kind of preaching of such a pastoral, theological character,
SPK_0: it is impossible to dig up, because, you see, the numbers clearly calculate which texts to take for the voice-over,
SPK_0: which will not be discredited or anything else.
SPK_0: But what is surprising is that when you open the comments, and there are a lot of comments,
SPK_0: there are a lot of grateful people.
SPK_0: And right here, Father Dmitry, thank you, Father Anatoly, and so on, and even when...
SPK_2: You don't think they are also bots?
SPK_0: No, no, no, no.
SPK_0: They are the same.
SPK_0: Well, because you can look at the channel, who you are subscribed to, and so on.
SPK_0: You can check, in fact, the real subscriber.
SPK_0: And even when people write, this is artificial intelligence, and so on,
SPK_0: then no one even notices it.
SPK_0: And in this sense...
SPK_1: Dear Father Pavel...
SPK_0: Yes, let's go, Pavel.
SPK_1: Sorry for interrupting.
SPK_1: It's just important.
SPK_1: It's not that the problem is at the bottom.
SPK_1: Everything you say is true.
SPK_1: One nuance.
SPK_1: People will not die for artificial intelligence.
SPK_1: Who will protect this power when it is kept on artificial intelligence?
SPK_1: I'm talking about this.
SPK_1: Are you sure?
SPK_1: The challenge will be that.
SPK_2: I think they won't, really.
SPK_0: Well, you know, it's interesting.
SPK_0: I'm talking to the guys, it's cool, probably, it turns out,
SPK_0: because now I'm constantly going, 9th, 8th, 8th, 9th grade.
SPK_0: Well, about a third of the classes are constantly communicating with artificial intelligence.
SPK_0: Constantly, right?
SPK_0: Right.
SPK_0: Right, constantly.
SPK_0: And for them it's...
SPK_0: It seems to me that some of them will be ready, if they are removed, they have artificial intelligence,
SPK_0: which is already friendlier with them, right?
SPK_0: Some may even want to go out the window.
SPK_0: That is, they will want to die.
SPK_1: Go out the window, please.
SPK_1: No, they may want to die, but they will not want to sacrifice themselves.
SPK_1: A huge difference.
SPK_1: Do you understand?
SPK_1: I can't explain this difference between self-sacrifice and, in fact, the reaction of a teenager
SPK_1: to attract attention and inability to cope with their own pain.
SPK_1: That's what I'm talking about.
SPK_1: And in relation to the government, you know, the government that does not take responsibility for the people
SPK_1: over whom it rules, no one will defend it.
SPK_1: And that's why this whole structure hangs on this, in fact, this Kantian project.
SPK_1: Let's kick the canto again.
SPK_1: And here we are at the top.
SPK_1: At the top of the elite we will agree.
SPK_1: And in order to better manage this scum, we will not fight each other.
SPK_1: But it doesn't work, because you at the top level cannot count on each other for people.
SPK_1: You can't, it's proven, you can't.
SPK_1: And if there will be a winner?
SPK_1: Because, in simple terms, time is moving.
SPK_1: The winner, the passion does not go anywhere.
SPK_1: The city, the greed, the excess.
SPK_1: That is, rationally, if a person were rational, Father Pavel, then yes.
SPK_1: But we are not rational, we are moving passions.
SPK_1: But rationally, it should have been in the 90s.
SPK_1: If what?
SPK_1: Well, for three years, yes.
SPK_1: Well, for three years, okay, let's bear with it.
SPK_1: Yes, that is, not for long.
SPK_1: Yes, that is, I understand.
SPK_2: For listeners who have not read the Apocalypse, it should be explained that after the Antichrist comes,
SPK_2: well, before the coming of Christ the Lord in power, only three years should pass.
SPK_2: Yes, I'll just explain it just in case.
SPK_0: And you don't have, Pavel, a strange apocalyptic story?
SPK_0: You don't have a taste for it when you look at it all.
SPK_0: Or do you think that, well, or do you honestly understand that Solomon is right?
SPK_0: Everything that happened now has already been there for centuries.
SPK_1: And both, yes, that is, in fact, well, Solomon is right, definitely.
SPK_1: That is, it is not special.
SPK_1: On the other hand, as we should always be ready.
SPK_1: That is, it is more difficult to explain in Russian than in English.
SPK_1: You know, there is a certain article, an indefinite article.
SPK_1: Here I definitely have a feeling of an indefinite article, like this apocalyptic feeling with an indefinite article.
SPK_1: And about a certain article, the Church teaches us not to think,
SPK_1: otherwise it is our favorite entertainment in every generation to look for the fact that the Apocalypse is right here and now.
SPK_1: It is told to us, given to us.
SPK_1: In general, no one knows this more often than the Father of our Heaven.
SPK_1: Therefore, even if you want, you cannot be too much into it.
SPK_1: There are many bad consequences from this.
SPK_1: But with indefinite, that is, if we understand the whole symbolism of the Apocalypse as purification, revelation, the secret becomes clear,
SPK_1: then, like the likeness of this fractal, yes, of course, there is a war.
SPK_1: And the war is always in this sense of purification.
SPK_1: War, disease, crisis, attack.
SPK_1: This is not for nothing that in the Russian language such events are always, as we said, the Lord has blessed.
SPK_1: That is, the Lord has blessed.
SPK_1: This is not always about what we perceive as a happy, such a blissful moment.
SPK_1: This is often about such a great tragedy.
SPK_1: And therefore, yes, there is in this case.
SPK_2: The last thing I ask about this topic, we have only one and a half minutes left until the end.
SPK_2: How true is the hypothesis, just our viewer and listener asked us about this.
SPK_2: How true is the hypothesis that Trump can be driven by some really messianic ideas,
SPK_2: and that is, really the construction of the Third Temple and so on.
SPK_2: That's what I wanted to ask.
SPK_1: Look, a short answer.
SPK_1: Not as much as Trump himself, a bunch of people around Trump.
SPK_1: Trump himself is driven by a very simple idea, and Trump is great.
SPK_1: He personally speaks only with one, God himself.
SPK_1: He literally said it.
SPK_1: No one limits him to his own blood.
SPK_1: Therefore, he is great.
SPK_1: He is the ruler of the planet from one particular palace.
SPK_1: And he has no problems with this question.
SPK_1: And around him, these people with messianic things are serious.
SPK_0: Before we go to the end, I just want to say that I already have two temples on the territory.
SPK_0: So if anyone wants to build a third one, come to the Harbin Temple.
SPK_0: Friends, do not miss it.
SPK_2: Do not miss it.
SPK_1: Sand Interest
SPK_2: Good evening, dear friends.
SPK_2: Sand Interest is on air.
SPK_2: I am the priest Pavel Ostrovsky and I am Polina Uvarova.
SPK_2: And our guest today is political philosopher Pavel Shchelin.
SPK_2: Hello again, Pavel.
SPK_2: We greet you again.
SPK_0: Friends, I wanted to talk about the family for a second and a half hour.
SPK_0: Because sooner or later we need to give birth here.
SPK_2: More.
SPK_0: More.
SPK_0: When I watch all these stories about what needs to be given birth and so on,
SPK_0: I feel sorry for the young guys who have to do all this.
SPK_0: Because I communicate with them the most.
SPK_0: And while they are Christians, while we are having Christian conversations,
SPK_0: they have some kind of light in front of them.
SPK_0: But when the speech comes in, we are already talking in a secular way.
SPK_0: Probably, for this reason, it is better not to talk to young people in a secular way.
SPK_0: They have some kind of absolute...
SPK_0: Stupor.
SPK_0: ...sadness.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_2: Their tone.
SPK_0: For one reason.
SPK_0: Because we are, in fact, the first place in the world in Russia in divorce.
SPK_0: It is clear that no one wants to get into a mortgage.
SPK_2: Yes, a mortgage is okay.
SPK_2: As a person living in a marriage, I can say that just despite the fact
SPK_2: that I love my husband and, I hope, he loves me too.
SPK_2: Despite what?
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_2: But despite this, I can't get rid of, reading the news,
SPK_2: just from some kind of constant, as if a wet sword.
SPK_2: As if this marriage institute, which is present in our country,
SPK_2: as if nothing at all, except God's help and our personal will,
SPK_2: which sometimes, as I understand it, can be experienced by some spirits of evil,
SPK_2: just can't stand it.
SPK_2: And from this, in fact, to the cold, it's terrible.
SPK_2: Here.
SPK_0: I will add, before we give the word to our wonderful Pavel,
SPK_0: that those people who actually speak for real family values,
SPK_0: because the word traditional family values has already discredited itself,
SPK_0: it's just not beautiful.
SPK_0: But those who really speak for family values,
SPK_0: offer anything, they don't even get into any discussions,
SPK_0: not even in any working groups, and often just openly marginalize themselves.
SPK_0: And those people who are called upon, even appointed by the authorities,
SPK_0: to decide all this, well, it seems to me, even if they want to,
SPK_0: if they want to, it can't work out.
SPK_1: Pavel, what do you think?
SPK_1: Well, short answer.
SPK_1: You are both completely right, in fact.
SPK_1: This topic is very sad, but it is deservedly sad,
SPK_1: because I absolutely completely agree with Pavel
SPK_1: that these magical spells of traditional values in the 21st century will not work.
SPK_1: We can just say in advance why.
SPK_1: And there is one fundamental reason for this.
SPK_1: Today, under marriage,
SPK_1: there really is no rational basis.
SPK_1: There is only a super-rational basis.
SPK_1: And everything that is super-rational, it is faith.
SPK_1: We can clearly see from Pavel's father where it is located.
SPK_1: That is, you absolutely, Pavel, you yourself said everything.
SPK_1: Marriage is held in good faith today.
SPK_1: And, probably, in this, if you look for optimism, this is good.
SPK_1: He is only held by faith, he is called to this,
SPK_1: that only by faith he should be held.
SPK_1: But historically, we just had such very large crutches.
SPK_1: The main crutch was survival.
SPK_1: You are not in marriage, you will die.
SPK_1: Well, physically.
SPK_1: You can ask a woman in the 18th century how she will live without her husband in winter.
SPK_1: Bad. Short answer. Bad.
SPK_1: She will probably die.
SPK_1: She will probably die with her husband, too.
SPK_1: But without a husband, yes.
SPK_1: Without a husband, she will probably die from cold with a child.
SPK_1: Well, that is, it is necessary to understand that this Institute of Traditional Values,
SPK_1: I will never say a better phrase,
SPK_1: but you can really give even this, remove this rational hat
SPK_1: in front of all sorts of feminists and marxists.
SPK_1: There is really a lot of such applied, economic, class and all sorts of things in it.
SPK_1: Today there is no such thing.
SPK_1: Today a person alone, alone with this scum of the state,
SPK_1: nevertheless, survives.
SPK_1: He has a delivery man, delivers food, a drone flies by,
SPK_1: artificial intelligence satisfies emotional needs.
SPK_1: That is, there is no rational reason to get married.
SPK_1: Property, it does not really matter.
SPK_1: Moreover, for example, for men,
SPK_1: entering into marriage is almost a guaranteed way to lose property.
SPK_1: In statistics with divorces.
SPK_1: Well, yes, yes.
SPK_1: That is, all these rational arguments for marriage, they really do not exist.
SPK_1: And it seems to me that the first step to a real honest conversation
SPK_1: about all this demographic problem,
SPK_1: about the problem of tradition,
SPK_1: is the recognition of the fact that
SPK_1: no one will really give birth for money.
SPK_1: This has failed in South Korea, in China, in Scandinavia.
SPK_1: That is, there is a small effect, but there is no real one.
SPK_1: That is, he does not make a problem.
SPK_1: And while we are at the level of the public, public thinkers,
SPK_1: and even more so at the level of the authorities,
SPK_1: do not recognize that we cannot solve this problem
SPK_1: with any rational actions,
SPK_1: it is useless to touch on it at all.
SPK_1: The only solution to the problem of marriage today
SPK_1: is a super-rational solution.
SPK_1: Look, and all over the world.
SPK_1: The only groups that have passed the temptation of this rationality,
SPK_1: well, that is, this is called the second demographic transition,
SPK_1: but in a good way, just a certain level of wealth and education,
SPK_1: so to put it simply.
SPK_1: The only groups that have passed this and continue to give birth
SPK_1: are deeply religious people.
SPK_1: These are traditional Orthodox, deeply churched.
SPK_1: These are traditional Catholics.
SPK_1: Not Catholics at all, but those who still
SPK_1: go to the Latin place.
SPK_1: That is, if you look at the statistics of these arrivals,
SPK_1: then there are 7-8 children there.
SPK_1: Some traditional Muslims.
SPK_1: Also, note, not Muslims in general.
SPK_1: Muslims who ended up in Europe, for example,
SPK_1: are exactly the same, as well as the same,
SPK_1: on the same robes as Catholics, Protestants, Orthodox.
SPK_1: In general, a single challenge.
SPK_1: That is, only a serious attitude to religion.
SPK_1: Well, the third is traditional Judaism.
SPK_1: The state of Israel as a state
SPK_1: is the only state that has passed the second demographic transition
SPK_1: and has a birth rate of more than two children per woman.
SPK_1: But you can look at the role of religion in the life of Israel
SPK_1: with all the pros and cons, right?
SPK_1: That is, no matter how I treated Judaism,
SPK_1: just the fact itself.
SPK_1: A short answer to the beginning, whether he likes it or not.
SPK_1: In the 21st century, robots will either give birth
SPK_1: or people with a living faith.
SPK_1: That's it.
SPK_1: Well, robots cannot give birth.
SPK_1: This is such a sarcasm, if anything, right?
SPK_1: But a short answer is that only people...
SPK_0: Yes, there is actually a reasonable question.
SPK_0: So, if at the top they did not understand the obvious
SPK_0: that it is the believers who give birth.
SPK_0: Well, I say believers.
SPK_2: In the broadest sense of the word.
SPK_0: In the broadest sense of the word, believers.
SPK_0: In the broadest sense of the word, all believers.
SPK_2: Not only Orthodox, but also all others.
SPK_0: Well, that it is the real believers that give birth.
SPK_0: Regardless of what.
SPK_0: Regardless of their finances.
SPK_0: With a living faith.
SPK_0: Yes, yes.
SPK_0: Well, I say believers in the broadest sense of the word.
SPK_0: Those who have faith with deeds.
SPK_0: Confirmed with deeds.
SPK_0: If the authorities do not notice it,
SPK_0: then how can they not notice it?
SPK_0: Because it lies on the surface.
SPK_0: But if she notices it and understands it,
SPK_0: then, it turns out, she resists it.
SPK_0: For the reason that,
SPK_0: despite the fact that in our country,
SPK_0: on the one hand, we have no, thank God,
SPK_0: persecution of the Orthodox Church.
SPK_0: There is no persecution.
SPK_0: But to say that we have at least,
SPK_0: well, at least a little bit of some religious propaganda,
SPK_0: in the good sense of the word,
SPK_0: that is, this is a movie,
SPK_0: and so on,
SPK_0: we do not see it.
SPK_0: We do not see it.
SPK_1: Where do they come from?
SPK_0: The question.
SPK_1: Well, in a good way.
SPK_1: After all, people are elderly.
SPK_1: It is necessary to understand.
SPK_1: That is, it seems to me, after all,
SPK_1: I tend to the first option, sincerely.
SPK_1: Because, do not forget,
SPK_1: in the mass of their people, this generation,
SPK_1: when we have in our bosses,
SPK_1: who gave birth, people, well, people always give birth.
SPK_1: That is, they are from the generation,
SPK_1: when the birth, it just happens.
SPK_1: Well, you know, it's like, well,
SPK_1: well, this is, well, we are here,
SPK_1: probably, we underestimate the speed
SPK_1: of this transition.
SPK_1: But it is necessary to understand that
SPK_1: when they were formed,
SPK_1: this is what I was talking about,
SPK_1: rationality and super-rationality,
SPK_1: this is an sincerely incomprehensible fact.
SPK_1: Well, really.
SPK_1: They think that this is a problem of money,
SPK_1: well, money, maybe a little shy
SPK_1: life circumstances.
SPK_1: But in general, the fact that the very installation
SPK_1: for birth is natural for them
SPK_1: is the most obvious fact
SPK_1: and, in addition, as it were,
SPK_1: the understanding of the needless.
SPK_1: But it's amazing, here it's industrial,
SPK_1: in fact, it's good.
SPK_1: In a sense, we ourselves drive ourselves to the point
SPK_1: when we have to admit that birth
SPK_1: is not just, forgive me,
SPK_1: to have some kind of
SPK_1: and this is exactly a spiritual, divine,
SPK_1: supernatural fact.
SPK_1: But it will certainly not be obvious to them,
SPK_1: and it is difficult to demand this from people
SPK_1: at their age, formed in the late 70s,
SPK_1: early 80s, with all the ongoing events.
SPK_1: At the same time, if you talk about,
SPK_1: I repeat, subconscious fear,
SPK_1: then, of course, there is a subconscious fear.
SPK_1: And this is, returning to the first part
SPK_1: of our program, of course,
SPK_1: this is a fear of responsibility.
SPK_1: It will have to be imitated by themselves.
SPK_1: They also don't really know how to imitate.
SPK_1: They are also children of all these.
SPK_1: You will notice that the collective symbol
SPK_1: of the power of modernity is Pontius Pilate.
SPK_1: They are all brought up in this kind of fatigue.
SPK_1: They carry it here,
SPK_1: it is necessary to deal with all this,
SPK_1: that's all.
SPK_1: And just like Pontius Pilate,
SPK_1: they all can say, in fact,
SPK_1: from my experience of communication,
SPK_1: where is the truth here?
SPK_1: From this Pilate fatigue.
SPK_1: Pilate's questions are very powerful.
SPK_0: Well, well, well.
SPK_1: Is there any human way
SPK_2: to cope with this at all, I think?
SPK_2: I understand that our only chance
SPK_2: is to live to the moment
SPK_2: when the generation will change
SPK_2: and, accordingly, something will change
SPK_2: in the structure, or what?
SPK_0: No, no, I don't agree with you
SPK_0: to say the generation will change,
SPK_0: because when today,
SPK_0: even in the Orthodox environment,
SPK_0: we are talking about marriage
SPK_0: and everything else,
SPK_0: it is necessary to say that the Orthodox Church
SPK_0: in Russia, I don't take it now,
SPK_0: I don't know how in Greece, in Serbia,
SPK_0: or in America,
SPK_0: but if we take Russia,
SPK_0: the same people enter the Orthodox Church,
SPK_0: who go to the elections,
SPK_0: to the store, to the five, and so on, right?
SPK_1: Yes, absolutely.
SPK_1: And all the problems,
SPK_0: including demographic,
SPK_0: psychological, any,
SPK_0: they concern the Russian Orthodox Church.
SPK_0: That is, we have a gigantic problem
SPK_0: with the clergy.
SPK_0: Our families are being destroyed
SPK_0: by the clergy.
SPK_0: by the simple Orthodox Christians.
SPK_0: And in general, when you start talking,
SPK_0: whether with priests
SPK_0: or with laymen
SPK_0: who have some influence
SPK_0: or even education,
SPK_0: I do not generalize now,
SPK_0: but very often,
SPK_0: if not in most cases,
SPK_0: you see that people say
SPK_0: that in order to give birth to children,
SPK_0: of course, it is important that there are money,
SPK_0: that it is important to have a living space,
SPK_0: and so on.
SPK_0: Although, by and large,
SPK_0: what Pavel says is the only goal.
SPK_0: That is, the birth of children
SPK_0: is very useful for spiritual life.
SPK_0: Just because you will be forced
SPK_0: to love these thugs
SPK_0: who yell at you and everything else,
SPK_0: but the confession of God to us,
SPK_0: yes, love each other.
SPK_0: And in this sense,
SPK_0: the birth of a child
SPK_0: and in general a complete family,
SPK_0: and so on, for spiritual life,
SPK_0: for spiritual growth,
SPK_0: it is very useful.
SPK_0: It is not by chance that it is said
SPK_0: that a woman is saved by a prodigal child,
SPK_0: not only by a prodigal child.
SPK_0: Polina is just six months old
SPK_0: and enjoys it.
SPK_0: Congratulations.
SPK_2: Thank you.
SPK_2: Do you understand that everything
SPK_2: that we are saying now is clear to the three of us?
SPK_2: There is hope.
SPK_2: But it seems to me that what we are saying
SPK_1: is also very simple.
SPK_1: Only these will survive, Polina.
SPK_1: It's a empty sound, but, unfortunately,
SPK_1: this divine selection works here.
SPK_1: Do you remember the prophet Isaiah?
SPK_1: May God bless us.
SPK_1: How is it?
SPK_1: Did I stay alone? No.
SPK_1: I left 5,000 people to myself
SPK_1: from a million city.
SPK_1: But the rest survives.
SPK_1: The short answer is that
SPK_1: you are completely right.
SPK_1: It is necessary to tell the truth.
SPK_1: No one guarantees survival
SPK_1: and no one forces it.
SPK_1: If you do not want to survive,
SPK_1: you will not.
SPK_1: Whoever acquires faith will survive.
SPK_1: This is the short answer.
SPK_1: If you are interested in a rational explanation,
SPK_1: then it is like this.
SPK_1: In this sense, survival
SPK_1: should be understood not in the narrow sense
SPK_1: as we had historically,
SPK_1: physically, from hunger and cold,
SPK_1: but in such a long, big,
SPK_1: with some...
SPK_2: It turns out like this.
SPK_1: Yes, it turns out like this.
SPK_1: And I agree with you that the speech,
SPK_1: of course, is not so much
SPK_1: about the death of generations,
SPK_1: again, our Orthodox lexicography
SPK_1: is more useful here.
SPK_1: The speech is about repentance and metanoia.
SPK_1: The speech is about the change of mind.
SPK_1: In this sense, in our generation,
SPK_1: in some sense,
SPK_1: the feat of a consciously giving birth to a woman today,
SPK_1: let my father correct me now,
SPK_1: if I am wrong,
SPK_1: it is comparable to the feat of a saint
SPK_1: of the first centuries.
SPK_1: Simply because today
SPK_1: the same super-natural motivation is required.
SPK_1: This is also an act of faith.
SPK_1: Do you understand? This is the whole story.
SPK_1: And all the problems inside the Orthodox families,
SPK_1: what are they?
SPK_1: Today we are entering an era
SPK_1: when it will not be possible
SPK_1: to rely on any form.
SPK_1: That is, neither formal faith,
SPK_1: nor a formal institute,
SPK_1: nor even formal biology,
SPK_1: nothing formal will save us.
SPK_1: Only the connection of your choice of the heart,
SPK_1: your will,
SPK_1: with those abilities and potentials
SPK_1: that are embedded in us,
SPK_1: today can give
SPK_1: some kind of living good fruit.
SPK_1: This is really to emphasize
SPK_1: the uniqueness of our moment.
SPK_1: Even our parents did not require this.
SPK_1: Such a level of awareness
SPK_1: and spiritual feat
SPK_1: in the simplest things
SPK_1: was not required earlier.
SPK_1: A person could simply go to one church all his life
SPK_1: simply because his parents go there,
SPK_1: give birth to children because
SPK_1: everyone does it this way,
SPK_1: and how else, and so on.
SPK_1: He did not need anything consciously.
SPK_1: To observe faithfulness simply because
SPK_1: how not to observe?
SPK_1: Today only freedom of will.
SPK_1: Only freedom of will
SPK_1: and a super-rational choice.
SPK_0: I want to note that today,
SPK_0: when I talk to young Christians,
SPK_0: I tell them directly that
SPK_0: it is necessary to teach yourself,
SPK_0: to teach directly,
SPK_0: not to look around,
SPK_0: including those around you,
SPK_0: in the church and so on,
SPK_0: to look for the best examples for yourself,
SPK_0: preferably among those who have already died.
SPK_0: That is, as the Apostle Paul said,
SPK_0: remember your mentors
SPK_0: and following the end of their lives,
SPK_0: imitate their faith.
SPK_0: That is, the end of their lives,
SPK_0: that is, those who are to the end.
SPK_0: To take the best examples,
SPK_0: to follow them.
SPK_0: And yes, this is the most real
SPK_0: feat of faith, because,
SPK_0: for example, a girl is getting married,
SPK_0: she even has an Orthodox husband,
SPK_0: and everything is fine and so on.
SPK_0: Here she gives birth to him,
SPK_0: the first, the second, the third,
SPK_0: and she really believes in God,
SPK_0: believes in her husband,
SPK_0: in the hope that her husband will not die,
SPK_0: that her husband will not change,
SPK_0: then the fourth child, the fifth child.
SPK_0: In the hope that her husband will not look to the sides,
SPK_0: to look for a non-priest,
SPK_0: wolves, sheep, sheep,
SPK_0: who will tell him, if anything,
SPK_0: go to the psychologist, your wife is toxic.
SPK_2: Or throw her away.
SPK_0: Throw her away and so on.
SPK_0: Because there is also such a thing,
SPK_0: that her husband will take an example from Christ.
SPK_0: This is, however, a feat of faith.
SPK_0: What is interesting is that when you talk to the guys about this topic,
SPK_0: you say directly how it is,
SPK_0: that it is impossible to be a Christian
SPK_0: if you do not dream of becoming a great saint.
SPK_0: That is, not just a saint.
SPK_0: You just have to take it to the maximum.
SPK_0: Even if you do not succeed in becoming a great saint,
SPK_0: God forbid, you will simply be a saint.
SPK_0: But the church is a gathering of holy people.
SPK_0: These words of Christ,
SPK_0: the one who takes the plow and looks back,
SPK_0: unreliable for the Kingdom of Heaven,
SPK_0: this is today, right now,
SPK_0: about our time in full measure.
SPK_0: And it can be seen that the guys like it.
SPK_0: As John the Baptist said,
SPK_0: young men, you are brave, you have defeated the wicked.
SPK_0: That is, the confrontation
SPK_0: with God in all spheres of life,
SPK_0: including within the church,
SPK_0: there are also many antichrists and so on.
SPK_0: Yes, I agree with Pavel
SPK_0: that this is a unique time.
SPK_0: Today we either speak the truth
SPK_0: or we are just out of context.
SPK_0: Immediately, instantly.
SPK_2: Well, I hope that we will at least reach someone,
SPK_2: because I certainly understand
SPK_2: that what you say makes sense to me.
SPK_2: But if a person just connects
SPK_2: who lives in the usual secular context,
SPK_2: then, of course, for him this is most likely ...
SPK_2: If he is not in the state of a burning crisis,
SPK_2: then most likely for him
SPK_2: this will not be some kind of way out.
SPK_2: That is, it is not yet a pre-prep.
SPK_1: Well, about the crisis ...
SPK_1: Well, about the pre-prep, yes,
SPK_1: here it is, without pre-prep,
SPK_1: this is, unfortunately, a prediction,
SPK_1: you know, we are one of those rough predictions
SPK_1: which, unfortunately, are true
SPK_1: both in the church and in personal geopolitical life,
SPK_1: do not reach through the head,
SPK_1: you knock through the liver.
SPK_1: That's about it.
SPK_1: Yes, that's about it, unfortunately,
SPK_1: that's how it works.
SPK_1: In the biblical language, we have prophets
SPK_1: who write a lot about this,
SPK_1: how the process of knocking through the liver
SPK_1: occurs at the collective level.
SPK_1: And I just want to fully support Father Paul.
SPK_1: That is, here is this duality,
SPK_1: precisely optimistic,
SPK_1: that the first thing is that when we tell the truth,
SPK_1: we can actually avoid this Phariseeism,
SPK_1: in which the discussion of traditional values
SPK_1: has stopped, turned into much,
SPK_1: and which does not give good fruits,
SPK_1: but gives fruits exclusively evil.
SPK_1: That is, according to the secular person,
SPK_1: the first thing to say is that
SPK_1: if you stay with a secular person,
SPK_1: yes, you really do not need marriage today
SPK_1: and you do not need to torture yourself.
SPK_1: That is, you can live as you live.
SPK_1: That is, all these formal dances
SPK_1: are not needed, they are really for you.
SPK_1: That is, this is actually the first very important step.
SPK_1: You can tell him this whole formal story
SPK_1: and this is without any condemnation,
SPK_1: so it is.
SPK_1: That is, if you are in such a system of values,
SPK_1: well, do not torture yourself,
SPK_1: do not try to force yourself to be faithful
SPK_1: without this great supernatural context,
SPK_1: because you will not be able to,
SPK_1: and you will only spend money on a psychologist.
SPK_1: In fact, it is very therapeutic,
SPK_1: but if you make a choice,
SPK_1: then you understand
SPK_1: which battlefield you are going to.
SPK_1: And this honesty on it,
SPK_1: even in my work,
SPK_1: I have fewer young people,
SPK_1: I have more people of 30-40 years old
SPK_1: who come to study with me,
SPK_1: but this honesty catches them too,
SPK_1: because this honesty
SPK_1: of the real system of coordinates,
SPK_1: of the real value of one choice or another,
SPK_1: it is now important for itself.
SPK_1: We cannot choose for a person,
SPK_1: but there is a duty
SPK_1: to honestly mark between what and what they choose.
SPK_1: Because, for example,
SPK_1: this spoon, which is that there is a choice,
SPK_1: you can get all the fruits of faith without faith,
SPK_1: the good ones, such as faithfulness, love, humility
SPK_1: and patience,
SPK_1: you can just say no, not today.
SPK_1: Maybe a hundred years ago it was still possible,
SPK_1: but today it will not work,
SPK_1: because that's it.
SPK_0: Well, Apostle Paul, in general,
SPK_0: has wonderful words,
SPK_0: this is when he ends his life,
SPK_0: he says, the course has been completed, faith has been preserved.
SPK_0: Just, guys, I suggest a choice,
SPK_0: you tell them that life will end anyway,
SPK_0: you will look back,
SPK_0: and if you really fought,
SPK_0: fought,
SPK_0: and you walked on the path of a hero,
SPK_0: you will understand that,
SPK_0: yes, the course of life has passed,
SPK_0: faith has been preserved.
SPK_0: It is not shameful to look back,
SPK_0: despite numerous mistakes and so on.
SPK_0: But if you did not start fighting in the end,
SPK_0: then this feeling
SPK_0: that I am actually an empty place,
SPK_0: it will appear to you long before death,
SPK_0: which is the most interesting thing.
SPK_0: That is, it is not so that you will die,
SPK_0: you think that I burned my life in vain,
SPK_0: and so on.
SPK_0: No, you will not even be 40 years old,
SPK_0: and you will understand that I lived half my life,
SPK_0: and I did not live.
SPK_0: And in this state, of course,
SPK_0: young guys, in principle, they feel it.
SPK_2: That's what I wanted to ask,
SPK_2: I thought I would ask Paul, but thank you.
SPK_2: Yes, I'm learning better and better,
SPK_2: though, Paul.
SPK_2: In general, I just wanted to ask
SPK_2: what those who choose the secular path pay,
SPK_2: and thank you for this answer,
SPK_2: because, by and large, then it turns out
SPK_2: that this is a choice between life and death,
SPK_2: in general, by and large, absolute.
SPK_2: And this must be understood,
SPK_2: because what we said before
SPK_2: sounded like the fact that this secular path
SPK_2: is so very sweet,
SPK_2: and the maximum when you start to regret it
SPK_2: is only before death.
SPK_1: Well, like a drug.
SPK_1: Much earlier.
SPK_2: Well, yes, yes, yes.
SPK_2: It's just important to talk about it.
SPK_1: Yes, a new dose is needed.
SPK_1: Well, it usually leads to Osterfein-Epstein
SPK_1: in all kinds of him,
SPK_1: further into the world of strength,
SPK_1: abilities and financial resources.
SPK_1: But on a practical level,
SPK_1: well, this is a crisis of senselessness,
SPK_1: this is a crisis of senseless life,
SPK_1: and he, of course, devours it.
SPK_1: But just what needs to be said,
SPK_1: just the first step to this is the recognition
SPK_1: that it is not formally resolved.
SPK_1: Today, this crisis of senselessness,
SPK_1: it is through the form,
SPK_1: that is, what Father Paul says,
SPK_1: just to come and go to church
SPK_1: and correct the ritual is not enough.
SPK_1: If you think that at least some form will save you,
SPK_1: even the church form
SPK_1: from the crisis of senselessness will not save you,
SPK_1: only through this conscious,
SPK_1: well, through the path of changing yourself.
SPK_1: That is, it sounds very banal, yes,
SPK_1: but you are absolutely right, Polina,
SPK_1: but this is our second law, yes.
SPK_1: I offered you life and death,
SPK_1: blessings and curses.
SPK_1: Choose life so that you live
SPK_1: and then something else.
SPK_1: But choose.
SPK_1: This is very important.
SPK_1: Culture is just a short comment.
SPK_0: You should be amazed now that
SPK_0: both I and Pavel know the text of the Holy Sepulchre.
SPK_2: I am amazed.
SPK_2: Let Pavel finish what he said.
SPK_2: Sorry, Pavel, please.
SPK_1: No, just a short moment.
SPK_1: We often forget this, especially,
SPK_1: that is, a short comment.
SPK_1: We should not be conservators.
SPK_1: It is very important to understand that a conservator
SPK_1: is a tradition, a tradition is something
SPK_1: that a person must constantly choose
SPK_1: in each generation himself and again.
SPK_1: Here, culture, it gives the temptation
SPK_1: that it is enough to just do
SPK_1: such a conservative reconstruction,
SPK_1: yes, that is, just perform these things.
SPK_1: Here, you need to get married,
SPK_1: so you went to the registry office,
SPK_1: put a signature, it itself,
SPK_1: this signature will save you.
SPK_1: It will not save you, only through choice.
SPK_1: And choice is precisely the metanoia,
SPK_1: the transformation of repentance.
SPK_1: And that's what young people,
SPK_1: even at any age,
SPK_1: it is our power and subject,
SPK_1: which, regardless of the news,
SPK_1: that we are able to make this choice.
SPK_1: This is the power that no one
SPK_1: can take away from a person,
SPK_1: even artificial intelligence.
SPK_1: We can, in the end, choose to use,
SPK_1: not to use and so on.
SPK_1: This is all our choice.
SPK_1: This is the centrality of choice.
SPK_1: Well, I don't know, someone fell asleep
SPK_1: in the days of what the modern sermon is about.
SPK_1: It seems to me that maybe today
SPK_1: it will sound louder or, well,
SPK_1: the groundwork for this,
SPK_1: for the conversation about the centrality
SPK_1: of the choice of a person,
SPK_1: it is now very important.
SPK_0: Well, I notice this in young people,
SPK_0: those who are encircling,
SPK_0: it seems to me that this is some kind
SPK_0: of evolutionary process,
SPK_0: that they, well, survival,
SPK_0: in this sense, evolutionary,
SPK_0: that they, having looked at the previous generation,
SPK_0: having listened to all these coaches,
SPK_0: psychologists, info gypsies and the like,
SPK_0: having looked at what is happening around,
SPK_0: they understand, well, not everyone,
SPK_0: it is clear that, well, some of the guys
SPK_0: understand that this is not possible,
SPK_0: and they address then, well,
SPK_0: first of all, to those people
SPK_0: who, well, first of all,
SPK_0: offer some kind of certain
SPK_0: clear practice, not a form,
SPK_0: but a practical, yes,
SPK_0: some kind of moment, yes,
SPK_0: which is proven in different
SPK_0: generations, in different times,
SPK_0: in different eras, in different circumstances,
SPK_0: yes, and in general, well,
SPK_0: I can say that, well,
SPK_0: I can say that those young guys
SPK_0: with whom I have to communicate,
SPK_0: and it pleases me very much,
SPK_0: these are the guys who are not just
SPK_0: formally you confess and confess,
SPK_0: yes, that is, once a week
SPK_0: at the service, but these are the guys
SPK_0: who read the Scripture, who together,
SPK_0: they use, by the way, modern technology,
SPK_0: they start, well, all seven of them
SPK_0: are non-believers, yes, but they,
SPK_0: well, I found out yesterday,
SPK_0: just these guys, they, well,
SPK_0: in collective communication, together
SPK_0: read the evening prayers. Oh, class.
SPK_0: It's a little boring, but, as it were,
SPK_0: I want to, as it were, together,
SPK_0: so they, you know, there they call,
SPK_0: they have their chats, yes,
SPK_0: and together they read the morning prayers,
SPK_0: the evening prayers, there, together
SPK_0: something goes somewhere, this, in my opinion,
SPK_2: this is a church, where two or three,
SPK_2: yes, gathered together, there I am among them.
SPK_2: Unfortunately, we don't have time
SPK_2: for another topic, which was very important,
SPK_2: maybe we will leave it for the next time,
SPK_2: but I really wanted to say
SPK_2: thank you very much for this broadcast,
SPK_2: because during the last week
SPK_2: I was very bored with the news,
SPK_2: and I somehow, somewhere,
SPK_2: despite the fact that I seem to be a Christian,
SPK_2: a deified one, somewhere, for some reason,
SPK_2: some internal meaning was lost,
SPK_2: and now I understand ...
SPK_2: Do you read the morning prayers?
SPK_0: I read, I read. With earthly compliments?
SPK_2: With earthly.
SPK_0: Well, okay, okay.
SPK_2: But, yes.
SPK_0: I now, as a typical,
SPK_0: a typical, a typical,
SPK_0: a typical, a semi-esthetic pop,
SPK_0: you know, such a thing.
SPK_2: In general, I just think that
SPK_2: I understand what, in fact, the meaning is,
SPK_2: the meaning is just to repeat even,
SPK_2: it would seem, banal things
SPK_2: until they are heard by the maximum
SPK_2: number of people. I think so.
SPK_0: So? Pavel, it doesn't matter what Polina says,
SPK_0: I'm always glad to see you,
SPK_0: just remember about it.
SPK_2: I'm talking to each other, I too,
SPK_0: Give your wife your greetings
SPK_0: and condolences, this is traditional.
SPK_1: Thank you.
SPK_2: Yes, thank you very much for the broadcast,
SPK_2: and our listeners, thank you very much,
SPK_2: for listening. I hope you listened
SPK_2: to the end. Bye everyone.
SPK_2: Stay with us.
SPK_0: Goodbye.