SPK_1: Welcome everyone. We are at the end of this journey. We are looking at a thing which comes, at least we think comes at the end.
SPK_1: We stopped before in a place where we discovered that to live in an agnostic world, we have to live as if we are immortal.
SPK_1: But there is a real tricky element to it, like accidents happen, like wars and crime and stuff.
SPK_1: And other people, generally speaking, there is this weird problem that other people actually are kind of cause of our death.
SPK_1: So how do we square this? Well, there is an easy solution you might have heard.
SPK_1: Peace to strengths. And that's the topic of the final episode.
SPK_1: So that's effectively the summary and the introduction.
SPK_1: And it might cause the most desire to burn me and the steak that usually comes when I express the paradox
SPK_1: hidden behind what seems the most basic and human.
SPK_1: The most humanist and irrevocable claim of modernity is that peace is good and we all must strive for global peace.
SPK_1: And that global peace is something even desirable and that we can achieve it.
SPK_1: And in fact, there is no such thing as big enough sacrifice to achieve such a world peace.
SPK_1: Well, to me, it represents, at least on the level of political philosophy, an ultimate lie of Gnosticism,
SPK_1: which unfortunately is very appealing to us.
SPK_1: Precisely because of all of the reasons we discussed before, like, ultimately, are you pro-war?
SPK_1: Like, that's the most easy natural response. Or are you pro-death?
SPK_1: This kind of responses can come into play.
SPK_1: Which just says again that we live in a pretty deeply Gnostic civilization and pretty deeply Gnostic world.
SPK_1: So the short answer is no, but.
SPK_1: And this but is important.
SPK_1: The but lies in the following way.
SPK_1: The peace Gnostic offers is not peace.
SPK_1: Is a simulation.
SPK_1: Is a simulation of peace.
SPK_1: That's why it's not peace, it's peace through strengths.
SPK_1: Because true peace does not come through strengths.
SPK_1: It comes through love.
SPK_1: But we cannot do love because love requires trust.
SPK_1: And love is not exactly about reason and knowledge.
SPK_1: And to love somebody in a broken world, ooh, that's tough.
SPK_1: Like, because also people are pretty broken too.
SPK_1: Like, pretty much, how can you love anything which is not perfect?
SPK_1: How, even bigger, how anything not perfect
SPK_1: can be loved?
SPK_1: Ooh.
SPK_1: But again, death is bad.
SPK_1: Death is a destruction.
SPK_1: Death and war and violence and murder.
SPK_1: In a Gnostic paradigm, they are enemy for a very particular reason.
SPK_1: Because this destroys the illusion.
SPK_1: And this destroys the illusion not on a schedule which is set up.
SPK_1: So it's uncontrollable destruction of illusion.
SPK_1: And this is a destruction of illusion which makes a very important thing to the people.
SPK_1: Kind of difficult, honestly.
SPK_1: That's the most difficult part to manage.
SPK_1: Because there is a famous saying in Russian that there are no atheists in trenches.
SPK_1: So the closed experience of life and death, willingly or unwillingly,
SPK_1: moves a man close to the transcendent.
SPK_1: The border between visible and invisible, spiritual and bodily,
SPK_1: really becomes sin in this moment.
SPK_1: Really.
SPK_1: Yes, there are still Gnostic ways of doing it, but honestly,
SPK_1: really hard.
SPK_1: Even Drew Berserk is not Gnostic, just in case.
SPK_1: So it can go really down, but it won't even be that Gnostic.
SPK_1: It's a fantasy.
SPK_1: Apocalypse is now a movie.
SPK_1: Basically, this is an example of going deep down in a spiritual world.
SPK_1: But that's exactly way more closer to the honest pagan,
SPK_1: which is also not what Gnostic wants of a man.
SPK_1: And often it can actually make you rethink your suffering and move you higher.
SPK_1: Well, uncontrollable.
SPK_1: Again, it's one thing if I move you to the death on my schedule,
SPK_1: on my term.
SPK_1: But there is always this uncontrollable element,
SPK_1: the one you pointed out before, and I hope you will talk again
SPK_1: what is this uncontrollable element of the deepest point of darkness is.
SPK_1: So ideally, you would prevent it.
SPK_1: Ideally, you would need to do it.
SPK_1: You would take this variable from the equation altogether.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: I feel like I want to go all the way back to the beginning,
SPK_0: which is to say a story.
SPK_0: A lie, but a story.
SPK_0: That the world was created,
SPK_0: and the world is broken.
SPK_0: And what we're saying,
SPK_0: and I agree completely,
SPK_0: and this is experiential,
SPK_0: that it's at the moments where you encounter reality,
SPK_0: in spite of anything you may prefer,
SPK_0: and almost always on the basis of something that is suffering,
SPK_0: that produces suffering,
SPK_0: or grief specifically.
SPK_0: The as if fabric cannot be pulled that far.
SPK_1: Yes.
SPK_0: And so you are outside the field of the as if fabric.
SPK_0: You sometimes will even look around confused,
SPK_0: because you are suddenly simply in reality.
SPK_0: And you notice that you are,
SPK_0: and something qualitatively has happened.
SPK_0: Feels weird.
SPK_0: Yes, something has changed.
SPK_0: You're suddenly in the world.
SPK_0: You're in reality.
SPK_0: And the image of the matrix,
SPK_0: the move of the matrix,
SPK_0: where everybody is ultimately perfectly not alive,
SPK_0: but is always able to pretend that they are in a simulation of life.
SPK_0: I think that's what the image was descending upon them
SPK_0: before the Gnostic syndicate got a hold of those two.
SPK_0: So the phrase that I've been using of trading life for mere survival,
SPK_0: and as you say, trading life for mere simulated peace.
SPK_0: And I get it.
SPK_0: Nobody wants to have grief.
SPK_0: Nobody wants to experience the death of the people that they love.
SPK_0: And in fact, this goes all the way back to this notion of cleaning your room.
SPK_0: It is in fact the case that we should put real effort into keeping our children from dying.
SPK_1: Yes.
SPK_0: It is in fact the case that we have to.
SPK_0: If we don't, they will.
SPK_0: They will put themselves in hazard,
SPK_0: and that will be the end of that.
SPK_0: And so that leveraging of the reality of capacity and responsibility
SPK_0: to avoid highly undesirable events
SPK_0: simply gets hypertrophied past its natural reality.
SPK_0: That grief has a natural role to play.
SPK_0: That's the weirdest and most untasteful thing.
SPK_0: That's the thing you bite into that and you don't like it.
SPK_0: You want to spit it out.
SPK_0: We want to avoid grief at all costs.
SPK_1: Just to hit it.
SPK_1: Because there is a sleight of hand even here.
SPK_1: Not intentionally, and I know you don't mean it,
SPK_1: but in the language there is a sleight of hand.
SPK_1: About grief.
SPK_1: There is a certain context which we need to understand while talking about suffering.
SPK_1: And it connects it both theologically and philosophically to two different realities.
SPK_1: One theological, the easiest way is Isaiah.
SPK_1: There is no peace for the wicked.
SPK_1: Not there is no peace, but that peace is conditional.
SPK_1: Not that there can be a world without suffering,
SPK_1: but it is conditional.
SPK_1: You see where I'm heading?
SPK_1: As long as you live in the wages of sin is death.
SPK_1: Or you can say that the wages of action,
SPK_1: all causality, all pure causality necessarily leads up to the death,
SPK_1: like the terminal death of the universe, even if you want to go down just the most.
SPK_1: So if you just stay on this level, in this separated world,
SPK_1: you should end up in death because it's just where your natural laws of causality is.
SPK_1: So the Gnostic selling point is that can we stay here?
SPK_1: Can we continue sinning?
SPK_1: Can we continue being wicked, but still have something which looks like peace?
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_1: And suffering is an antidote against this.
SPK_1: Not against peace, not like you need suffering in heaven.
SPK_1: Otherwise, I know you don't mean it, but it might have sounded a little bit like...
SPK_0: Actually, you might, by the way.
SPK_0: But the word suffering is a very complex word.
SPK_1: Yes, but I really want to show out what Gnostic sleight of hand is.
SPK_1: So ultimately it was be wicked and have peace.
SPK_1: And unfortunately, this doesn't work.
SPK_0: Nice. Be wicked and have peace.
SPK_0: By the way, if that's just a straightforward marketing slogan, you get a lot of buyers.
SPK_0: Pretty much everybody.
SPK_0: Almost everybody would say, okay, good deal, because I can't be...
SPK_0: Good deal?
SPK_0: Good deal. Yeah, good deal.
SPK_0: Wait a minute. Who's the moron here?
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: Everybody who doesn't buy that deal is the sucker.
SPK_0: Oh, wait, no, that's not how it works.
SPK_0: Because everybody knows two things.
SPK_0: They seek peace and they can't not be wicked.
SPK_1: Well, they can, but...
SPK_0: And Christ offers you peace, but he also offers you a cross.
SPK_1: Conditional.
SPK_1: Ultimately, there's a gap of this conditionality.
SPK_1: And if you remember, again, the story of nativity, it is a conditional statement.
SPK_1: Glory to the God in the highest and peace on earth among people.
SPK_0: Nice.
SPK_1: It's not separated.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_0: It's not one and then also maybe two.
SPK_0: These two things are together.
SPK_1: It's causally related.
SPK_1: Okay, not religious language.
SPK_1: Only if you ordain your causal ladder of attention to the most proper, to the highest, to the realities such which you embody in your whole spirit,
SPK_1: then you can effectively overcome the necessity of entropy and through mystery, miracle, love, trust, basically from all of the...
SPK_1: I'm using this as a metaphor.
SPK_1: Maybe you will use it in a ritual.
SPK_1: But effectively, you make the quantum jump.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: You're making the quantum jump of the causality.
SPK_0: Well, right.
SPK_0: So the language is funny because it's a religious word, but we just have no other better word.
SPK_0: I will often use the Greek because it's less loaded, but it's faith.
SPK_1: Yes.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: And so let me sort of just articulate what I mean by that.
SPK_0: Because one, we know that like all things in the Gnostic civilization, the most important things have been very defamed and perverted.
SPK_0: Faith is perhaps foremost amongst them.
SPK_0: If not very much in the top of the list.
SPK_0: So it has nothing to do with something like willing something very, very strongly.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_1: Imagining.
SPK_1: Not even willing.
SPK_0: Well, I want to do both.
SPK_0: Okay.
SPK_0: It also has nothing to do with imagining something that is not really the case.
SPK_0: It has nothing to do with imagination or a little bit, but very little.
SPK_0: And very little to do with the will or more properly, it has to do with a fully integrated self.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: The whole point is that faith is the faculty of a fully integrated self in relationship with reality, capital R.
SPK_0: And so I oftentimes will use very banal examples.
SPK_0: And it's not, you can say, if I pick up this cup, I have faith that the water will not suddenly come splashing on my legs.
SPK_0: And that's a proper use of the term.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: That's perfectly reasonable use of the term.
SPK_0: We just extend that out all the way, right?
SPK_0: Capital F faith.
SPK_0: And this goes back to that notion of the Gnostic sleight of hand has to break your faith.
SPK_0: If your faith is established, if you are actually in continuity of contact with reality,
SPK_0: then the glory to God and peace on earth will be a lived reality that you can perceive as being a thing.
SPK_1: And self-evident, kind of.
SPK_0: Yes, self-evident.
SPK_0: Exactly.
SPK_0: Or at least, yeah.
SPK_0: And how do you say?
SPK_0: Straightforward.
SPK_1: Straightforward.
SPK_0: And when something happens and these things, this overwhelm, something happens that breaks your faith,
SPK_0: which may just, you know, there's many different ways that can happen.
SPK_0: We shouldn't be narrow because the key thing is your faith is broken.
SPK_0: Then the Gnostic sleight of hand enters.
SPK_0: And the entire cascade and all the different characteristics we've talked about begin to emerge.
SPK_0: It may get you at trying to use rationality to produce a salve, a therapy for the suffering that you're experiencing.
SPK_0: That's one way.
SPK_0: It may produce agency.
SPK_0: No, go, go do, go solve.
SPK_0: You take over.
SPK_0: It doesn't matter.
SPK_0: The point is wherever it can get in, it gets in and then it begins to do its work and separates you.
SPK_1: But it has an ultimate enemy.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: And this ultimate enemy is death, kind of.
SPK_0: Nice.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: And we've seen actually this death happens, as you say, collectively, systemically.
SPK_0: The world that it builds, the civilization that it constructs, dies.
SPK_0: Individually, subjectively, the self that you've been given, the as-if identity that you've been presented,
SPK_0: that you can wear as your power to armor, even as yourself, atrophies to near nothingness, also dies.
SPK_0: It may die locally.
SPK_0: Some event may occur.
SPK_0: That makes it no longer work.
SPK_0: Or it may die ultimately in the sense that you, in fact, corporally die.
SPK_0: Your life on earth ends, on this earth ends.
SPK_0: And it can't solve that problem.
SPK_1: Well, I know it can't, but I know it does a thing which to me sounds like madness.
SPK_1: But what it tries to do is to substitute eternal with endless.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: Very nice.
SPK_0: I know this very cleanly.
SPK_0: I call it the Leibnizian error, actually.
SPK_0: The limit as X approaches infinity.
SPK_0: Infinity equals infinity.
SPK_0: And of course, these are completely wrong.
SPK_0: It's wrong category.
SPK_0: You're not even thinking about reality or infinity properly when you say that.
SPK_0: But yes, they try to substitute endless for eternity.
SPK_1: Yes.
SPK_1: Which they even can't do.
SPK_0: Can't do that either, but that's the offer.
SPK_1: Yes, that's the offer.
SPK_0: It's funny.
SPK_0: They don't even offer you the right thing, and they can't deliver on their offer.
SPK_1: But the tricky part is why it works generationally.
SPK_1: They can create a good enough image of this offer for a certain period of time, for a certain generation,
SPK_1: for a certain moment.
SPK_1: So time really plays a tricky role.
SPK_1: Time, on the one hand, is their ultimate enemy, because that's another hidden desire of Gnosticism.
SPK_1: Stop time, which we didn't talk about.
SPK_1: And this whole eternal global peace they're talking about, it is the stop time clock.
SPK_1: Let's just stop it.
SPK_1: Cut all of the causality.
SPK_1: Because if you think about it on a pragmatic level, okay, we have states, nations, people, borders.
SPK_1: Entropy emerges.
SPK_1: It emerges for reasons.
SPK_1: So, like, life continues.
SPK_1: I don't know.
SPK_1: The population changes.
SPK_1: Or the amount of population changes.
SPK_1: And there is a spiritual sign behind changes in populations, like it or not.
SPK_1: There is.
SPK_1: But ultimately, the state now and the state in a hundred years will be a different state.
SPK_1: And any border, like the whole idea of border, is not stable.
SPK_1: Like, there is no stable border in history.
SPK_1: I'm sorry.
SPK_1: Any border is a dynamic thing.
SPK_1: Like, it's actually Americans understand it very well.
SPK_1: Any border is a frontier.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: Like, but what the proposition of eternal peace is, is, let's say, to make every frontier a border.
SPK_1: Well, there is a hell price to pay.
SPK_1: One of the hell of the prices to pay.
SPK_1: You need to artificially suppress life.
SPK_1: And you need to artificially promote death.
SPK_1: Not death, but almost dead state.
SPK_1: Like, dying.
SPK_1: Like, it's injury.
SPK_1: Not death.
SPK_1: Actually, wow.
SPK_1: Sorry.
SPK_1: I didn't think about it.
SPK_1: But that just in the state politics.
SPK_1: So, you won't.
SPK_1: We won't want to let a state collapse.
SPK_1: Because that's death.
SPK_1: We don't want to let.
SPK_1: Notice that how in the last 400 years, the idea that the state can die.
SPK_1: That the state can be dissolved.
SPK_1: That the state can collapse.
SPK_1: Any state.
SPK_1: It's actually something we feel very scared upon.
SPK_1: Well, that's something new.
SPK_1: But something erupts under the whole global system of the United Nations.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: If state is.
SPK_1: So, we need to kind of keep it dying.
SPK_1: Yes, we cannot make it alive.
SPK_1: For example, a particular state.
SPK_1: So, let's send it emergency relief funds.
SPK_1: Let's send this.
SPK_1: Let's by no means allow its border to be changed.
SPK_1: Even like now there is only 5 million people living on a territory which like 100 years ago there were 50 million.
SPK_1: They can't defend their borders.
SPK_1: They can't do anything.
SPK_1: Like, they cannot feed their own retired.
SPK_1: But now their borders are sacred.
SPK_1: Why?
SPK_1: Why would we do it?
SPK_0: Hold on.
SPK_0: Let's slow down.
SPK_0: Because to get to that.
SPK_0: To get to the point of stopping time.
SPK_0: We get to a very particular place.
SPK_0: But let me back up a little bit.
SPK_0: The deal is this.
SPK_0: One.
SPK_0: Okay, fine.
SPK_0: We'll try to help you live a long time.
SPK_0: But two.
SPK_0: The self that we are going to give you.
SPK_0: That self is attached as part of its identity to something that definitely will last longer than you.
SPK_0: This is what you're saying.
SPK_0: This is the state.
SPK_0: Or whatever.
SPK_0: It could be the scientific institution.
SPK_0: It's a non-human object that has the capacity for us to pretend like it has life.
SPK_0: And now I can say.
SPK_0: And people say it.
SPK_0: It's sometimes called like the immortals.
SPK_0: Einstein is immortal.
SPK_0: They say that.
SPK_0: They say Caesar is immortal.
SPK_0: Not because he will in fact actually enter into eternity.
SPK_0: Or even that he will live a particular time.
SPK_0: But that his name will be known.
SPK_0: His name will cascade down history.
SPK_0: And in fact Caesar's name has cascaded down history.
SPK_1: But Caesar was honest.
SPK_1: He honestly worshiped the goddess of glory.
SPK_1: And he sacrificed everything on her altar.
SPK_1: So that's the thing.
SPK_1: We are not even Caesars.
SPK_1: If Caesar came into modern world.
SPK_1: Oh my goodness.
SPK_1: Like imagine him looking on modern French politicians.
SPK_1: And our Italian politicians.
SPK_1: Like he would be the first honestly to basically do a coup.
SPK_1: And just trying to set up things in some kind of what he would perceive.
SPK_0: But the point is that that's the version of the offer.
SPK_0: Like the best version of the offer is that you will attach yourself to something.
SPK_0: That is in fact actually larger than yourself.
SPK_0: Right?
SPK_0: There's a simulation of transcendence.
SPK_0: That has an endurance.
SPK_0: And life longer than you.
SPK_0: Which is why you feel it viscerally.
SPK_0: When you imagine your state.
SPK_1: But as you said the key part is the simulation.
SPK_1: Because it's not like in a healthy way.
SPK_1: It is a continuation of you organically.
SPK_1: Like it is this.
SPK_1: There is a chain of organic connection between you and this bigger identity.
SPK_1: Like homeland if you want to put it this way.
SPK_1: Which gets a form.
SPK_1: The state of a Gnostic is a very particular thing.
SPK_1: It actually rejects the organic sense.
SPK_1: That's why it rejects the kink.
SPK_1: That's why it creates a simulation.
SPK_1: It's an eternal placeholder.
SPK_1: In a place of the kink and a kink.
SPK_1: Which ideally.
SPK_1: Like originally because that's actually Hobson coming into play.
SPK_1: He was very conscious about writing it.
SPK_1: He was.
SPK_1: Hobs.
SPK_1: He was desperate.
SPK_1: Let's throw the moment of time until Christ comes.
SPK_1: That was kind of his understanding.
SPK_1: Like we can solve this problem until the second coming.
SPK_1: Let's freeze time effectively until then.
SPK_1: And let Christ decide all of this.
SPK_1: Well let's just move a couple of steps forward.
SPK_1: Let's just take Christ out of the picture.
SPK_1: And let's just stop time.
SPK_1: Period.
SPK_1: Because that's the very idea of League of Nations.
SPK_1: Or United Nations.
SPK_1: It's an idea of stoppage time.
SPK_1: It's an idea that you can prevent all of the conflicts.
SPK_1: Simple act of deliberation and good faith.
SPK_1: Because there is no faith in the picture.
SPK_1: And there is a whole crook and moron thing.
SPK_1: Why do we want the morons to willingly submit.
SPK_1: And again it works to an extent.
SPK_1: But then.
SPK_1: The morons who have sometimes nuclear arsenals realizing that they are morons.
SPK_1: They don't like it.
SPK_1: For example Russian morons who got this sign of a deal in the 90s.
SPK_1: They really didn't like when they realized in 2000s that they are the morons.
SPK_1: Hence like what you see right now.
SPK_1: But this is a simple part of the story.
SPK_1: But it's happening all in all.
SPK_1: But on the deepest level you do need to make these two very counterintuitive things.
SPK_1: Because that's how it connects.
SPK_1: You do need to stop movement below.
SPK_1: And ideally you really really really need to slow down the movement above.
SPK_1: I mean the deaths and the births.
SPK_1: That's why kind of big shifts in populations.
SPK_1: Like generally birthing.
SPK_1: But becomes potentially very dangerous phenomenon.
SPK_1: And on the contrary like letting let's say rip the wages of sin.
SPK_1: Which in course of any collective would be.
SPK_1: If you made critical number of mistakes.
SPK_1: Or if you made a critical number of false belief or decisions.
SPK_1: Rip what you saw.
SPK_1: You encounter death.
SPK_1: And that's what war in history is in part.
SPK_1: It's like war is not just.
SPK_1: It is obviously evil, horrible, cruel way.
SPK_1: But ultimately it is like.
SPK_1: Well you have no more people willing to fight for you.
SPK_1: Who?
SPK_1: Like by whose mercy should you have what you have?
SPK_1: Do you see what I mean?
SPK_1: Like so.
SPK_1: You want.
SPK_1: And that's why it's a tempting offer.
SPK_1: Like again another tempting offer.
SPK_1: What if you can have all you have.
SPK_1: Without having to potentially and sometimes actually having to defend it.
SPK_1: That's a good offer.
SPK_1: Like you can keep your power of the plebs.
SPK_1: Without having to die for this plebs.
SPK_1: The deal to nobility.
SPK_0: Very good deal.
SPK_0: What I noticed that I'm trying to get on.
SPK_0: Is I'm finding myself taking all of this.
SPK_0: And coming all the way back to the.
SPK_0: Not the beginning temporally.
SPK_0: But the beginning in sort of.
SPK_0: Why?
SPK_0: Why is this part of reality?
SPK_0: Where is this Gnostic sleight of hand?
SPK_0: Where is this Gnostic civilization?
SPK_0: Where is this notion?
SPK_0: What is its source and origin?
SPK_0: What is it?
SPK_1: Well to me.
SPK_1: I think there are two ultimate presuppositions.
SPK_1: One.
SPK_1: I did express earlier.
SPK_1: But I maybe repeat it.
SPK_1: And it will sound differently.
SPK_1: I think it's some deep, deep, deep belief.
SPK_1: And that's why it's actually a very tragic story.
SPK_1: That not perfect cannot be loved.
SPK_1: Oh.
SPK_0: A deep belief that the not perfect cannot be loved.
SPK_1: Yes.
SPK_1: Why God would die for us.
SPK_0: Wow.
SPK_0: Okay.
SPK_0: That's very intense.
SPK_0: Which is just to say something like.
SPK_0: You.
SPK_0: Individually.
SPK_1: Me.
SPK_1: Personally.
SPK_0: It is ultimately a rejection.
SPK_0: Of.
SPK_0: Salvation.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: On the basis of.
SPK_0: I cannot believe that I can be loved.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: Okay.
SPK_1: And then everything else follows.
SPK_0: Everything else follows.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: It's funny.
SPK_0: Everything else follows.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_1: But there is a tricky part.
SPK_1: I will explain.
SPK_1: Like why it's belief.
SPK_1: Because this experience of this belief will necessarily kind of make or condition you
SPK_1: to love other imperfect things.
SPK_0: Okay.
SPK_1: I actually love them.
SPK_1: And you kind of don't want to do it.
SPK_0: Ah.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_1: You see.
SPK_1: Because it's a dual sword.
SPK_1: If your imperfect self is loved wholeheartedly by the highest power.
SPK_1: You don't have excuse to not love.
SPK_1: And you know from your experience that you do not love.
SPK_1: Just to be clear.
SPK_1: I know from my.
SPK_1: I have been.
SPK_1: So.
SPK_0: So this is.
SPK_0: Let me say this back.
SPK_0: Proposition.
SPK_0: The story.
SPK_0: Is that the world is broken.
SPK_0: The truth.
SPK_0: Is that your heart is broken.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: That is what you were saying.
SPK_0: That's the truth.
SPK_0: The truth is.
SPK_0: Your heart is broken.
SPK_0: And you begin a process of responding to that.
SPK_0: By producing a false reality.
SPK_0: That places the error at the level of the world.
SPK_0: And everything follows.
SPK_1: In collaboration.
SPK_1: I have to say.
SPK_1: In collaboration with knowledgeable agents of much higher knowledge than you.
SPK_1: So it's not just you playing in the story.
SPK_1: You are willing to play in the story to what you think saves the brokenness.
SPK_1: Okay.
SPK_1: Sounds evil.
SPK_1: But effectively you're making an idol out of your broken heart.
SPK_1: It's a final idol you make is your broken heart.
SPK_1: And you center everything.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_0: Okay.
SPK_0: So we can look at the very, very.
SPK_0: Like there's a micro version of this that happens.
SPK_0: Every time you encounter a reality that breaks your heart.
SPK_0: And you endeavor to resolve or solve the problem.
SPK_0: By virtue of in some kind of therapeutic response.
SPK_0: The therapeutic response could be alcohol.
SPK_0: The therapeutic response could be work.
SPK_0: The therapeutic response could be denial.
SPK_0: It doesn't matter.
SPK_0: The therapeutic response could be therapy.
SPK_0: It could be talking therapy.
SPK_0: But instead of actually suffering.
SPK_0: The suffer.
SPK_0: The meaning.
SPK_0: Meaningfulness of the experience.
SPK_0: And being in open heartedness and vulnerability to the reality.
SPK_0: You choose something other than that.
SPK_0: Okay.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: So that happens all the time.
SPK_1: Yes.
SPK_1: And this is.
SPK_1: On the next step you create.
SPK_1: Effectively you create an illusion.
SPK_1: The problem is.
SPK_1: For some reason.
SPK_1: And you don't really want to accept.
SPK_1: It's knocking on your door.
SPK_1: You don't want to think this way.
SPK_1: But you just can't help at certain level.
SPK_1: To observe it's falling apart.
SPK_1: You created a great wonderful illusion of cooperation.
SPK_1: Globalism.
SPK_1: And global trade.
SPK_1: It's falling apart.
SPK_1: Like.
SPK_1: Or something.
SPK_1: You created a perfect illusion within your local level.
SPK_1: Your family.
SPK_1: Or something.
SPK_1: You created.
SPK_1: It keeps falling apart.
SPK_1: And that's why peace through strength.
SPK_1: Your son and I will hold it together.
SPK_0: Just like this.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: So it's.
SPK_0: The cinema version of this.
SPK_0: Would you.
SPK_0: You would be showing a family.
SPK_0: And you should be showing a family where a son dies.
SPK_0: One of four.
SPK_0: And the father then goes through this process.
SPK_0: Right.
SPK_0: His heart is broken.
SPK_0: And he commits himself to protecting his family.
SPK_0: But at the cost of his family.
SPK_0: Entirely.
SPK_0: And of course eventually it falls apart.
SPK_0: And that is the tragedy.
SPK_1: Because in fact the more you hold it.
SPK_1: The more entropy.
SPK_1: The more causes of entropy within it.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: You have not yet lost the love of your other sons.
SPK_0: And the day that your first son dies.
SPK_0: But 40 years hence.
SPK_0: They're all alienated.
SPK_0: They are themselves trapped in this world.
SPK_0: This civilization that you've been creating.
SPK_1: Then.
SPK_1: Like.
SPK_1: In religious language.
SPK_1: The number of sin.
SPK_1: The amount of sin is increasing.
SPK_1: And with sin comes the wages of sin.
SPK_1: And that's the thing.
SPK_1: On every single iteration.
SPK_1: It's actually much harder to keep it.
SPK_1: That's why ideally you need to go through periodical catastrophe.
SPK_1: To just wipe it clean.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: Like.
SPK_1: But the problem is it kind of starts speeding up.
SPK_1: And you still can't control.
SPK_1: Like you can't control.
SPK_1: Neat.
SPK_0: So then.
SPK_0: So the way my mind also turns to this.
SPK_0: Is I can run it through a different way of thinking.
SPK_0: And say.
SPK_0: We have diagnosed.
SPK_0: What would be called in some languages.
SPK_0: A niche.
SPK_0: There is a.
SPK_0: A location where a series of particular characteristics align.
SPK_0: So as to produce a standing wave.
SPK_0: Or something that has stability or endurance.
SPK_0: For an adequate amount of time.
SPK_0: For it to produce itself.
SPK_0: And to reproduce itself.
SPK_0: And what we see is that in the arc of the human experience.
SPK_0: It does.
SPK_0: It has these systemic characteristics.
SPK_0: That it pushes itself out to capture.
SPK_0: And enroll other beings.
SPK_0: And other people.
SPK_0: In its own dynamics.
SPK_0: And the duration.
SPK_0: And the magnitude.
SPK_0: Of its fragility.
SPK_0: Is bound by.
SPK_0: Three.
SPK_0: Limits.
SPK_0: One limit.
SPK_0: Is that it will eventually.
SPK_0: There's a temporal.
SPK_0: It will ultimately.
SPK_1: Time brings change.
SPK_0: Time brings change.
SPK_0: There is the notion of fragility.
SPK_0: That it becomes more and more susceptible.
SPK_0: And then finally.
SPK_0: There is the notion.
SPK_0: Of the trade-off.
SPK_0: Of the fact that you will be.
SPK_0: You will be going from the comfortable.
SPK_0: To the uncomfortable.
SPK_0: That it degenerates naturally.
SPK_0: And so you have this.
SPK_0: In the hypertrophy cycle.
SPK_0: Okay.
SPK_0: The only response.
SPK_0: Is to hypertrophy.
SPK_0: So you increase.
SPK_0: The intensity.
SPK_0: And then.
SPK_0: It degenerates.
SPK_0: And you hypertrophy.
SPK_0: And until you reach.
SPK_0: The natural.
SPK_0: There's some natural limit.
SPK_0: Where you just cannot.
SPK_0: Double down.
SPK_0: Anymore.
SPK_1: Well.
SPK_1: But it might not.
SPK_1: Happen on your life.
SPK_1: Like.
SPK_1: No.
SPK_0: You.
SPK_0: This case.
SPK_0: Is whatever.
SPK_0: Whatever.
SPK_1: Who.
SPK_1: Is trapped.
SPK_0: In this system.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: So this is.
SPK_0: I mean.
SPK_0: A big part of the story.
SPK_0: That I.
SPK_0: magnets.
SPK_0: It runs into limits.
SPK_0: Those limits.
SPK_0: Are.
SPK_0: Bound.
SPK_0: By its.
SPK_0: Identity.
SPK_0: Of.
SPK_0: It.
SPK_0: Of what it is.
SPK_0: It can't change.
SPK_0: It's identity.
SPK_0: So it can only double down.
SPK_0: At.
SPK_0: The core.
SPK_0: If it successfully.
SPK_0: Renews its ability to access.
SPK_0: Resources.
SPK_0: It goes.
SPK_0: but it gets a half-life on that you're on some kind of curve at some point the doubling down
SPK_0: which requires more energy at some point the doubling down hits a limit and then the identity
SPK_0: must go away which then looks like a collapse this is an objective assessment subjective example
SPK_1: because it is a pretty accurate description of the box and the key gnostic sleight of hand is that
SPK_1: you are in the box yeah because as long as you are in the box as long as you are in this gnostic
SPK_1: civilization it's inevitable again the wages of sin is there so like it has to happen yeah what
SPK_1: it doesn't say is what you hinted before so now the deepest level is actually a way of jumping
SPK_1: out of the box so the only solution to the crisis is not within the crisis jumping out of it and
SPK_1: to the point of the final topic it's a beautiful thought which i read in the batista's book but
SPK_1: it's absolutely true from political science perspective
SPK_1: the
SPK_1: to do to war is not peace it's liturgy and that's the jumping of the box which gnostic
SPK_1: civilization can't actually control right not at all not at all not at all agreed so what means
SPK_1: liturgy in that context i guess yeah just saying it like as we said before i can choose let's say
SPK_1: face ultimately so let's say easy example of basic memetic crisis you and me love the same
SPK_1: woman for some like we're young guys
SPK_1: strong like some are strong some are smart some is both maybe there is a certain response but
SPK_1: we love it all together or we want it all together with the giraffe would say desire it all together
SPK_1: we all starting showing our best qualities pursuing her the best we can that's important
SPK_1: part maybe for you it's brain for me it's strengths maybe for somebody else it will be
SPK_1: art for somebody it can be money whatever it is like it's just the best version of yourself
SPK_1: like whatever best again of the most you can show she will choose one and the other is the same thing
SPK_1: will have to face a choice.
SPK_1: And that's the tricky part Gnostic doesn't tell, truly.
SPK_1: That's enthronics.
SPK_1: It talks so much about will,
SPK_1: but they actually cut down the freedom of will
SPK_1: in the most important element.
SPK_1: I can choose whether I use real energy of entropy
SPK_1: in hatred, which really emerges
SPK_1: when my sacrifice is rejected.
SPK_1: But it's my choice whether I use it for,
SPK_1: promote it into violence.
SPK_1: It's my choice.
SPK_1: But this choice is not based on reason.
SPK_1: This choice is based on faith.
SPK_1: This choice can be based on communion
SPK_1: with some higher purpose
SPK_1: or any faith in this higher purpose.
SPK_1: You can pretend,
SPK_1: and the problem is like,
SPK_1: you can pretend it's just an objective rational law.
SPK_1: Like, trust me,
SPK_1: not good enough when it really hits you.
SPK_1: But logically you can,
SPK_1: on a smaller level memetic crisis,
SPK_1: you can pretend to rationally jump out of this way.
SPK_1: On a real memetic crisis, you won't.
SPK_1: It will take faith.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: And that is more than a notice
SPK_1: that this act of we can do it.
SPK_1: And this is,
SPK_1: have you read,
SPK_1: Steinbeck novel,
SPK_1: To the East of Eden?
SPK_1: Like it's...
SPK_0: Steinbeck, yes.
SPK_0: Yeah, yeah.
SPK_1: The key part of the story
SPK_1: is the story of Cain and Abel,
SPK_1: if you remember.
SPK_1: And he spends a lot of time
SPK_1: talking about the most proper translation
SPK_1: of what God tells Cain.
SPK_1: And after all different discussions,
SPK_1: the story comes to that
SPK_1: the proper translation would be,
SPK_1: there is a sin lying in front of you,
SPK_1: but you may overcome it.
SPK_1: So it's up to you.
SPK_1: Why?
SPK_1: The only way you can do it
SPK_1: is through faith.
SPK_1: It cannot be done rationally,
SPK_1: it cannot be done logically,
SPK_1: it cannot be done knowledgeably,
SPK_1: it cannot be done even through will.
SPK_1: Even willfully it truly cannot be done.
SPK_1: But it can be done through faith.
SPK_1: And that's what means the liturgy.
SPK_1: Liturgy is jumping out of the box.
SPK_1: Liturgy is overcoming the memetic crisis.
SPK_1: Liturgy is accepting that there is movement
SPK_1: and there is entropy in any change,
SPK_1: any movement,
SPK_1: but you're choosing not to let the potentiality,
SPK_1: the negative potentiality of this entropy
SPK_1: shine through you,
SPK_1: you're not letting it shine through.
SPK_1: And if there is a critical mass of people
SPK_1: doing the same thing,
SPK_1: then suddenly you're achieving some
SPK_1: impossible states within the Gnostic paradigm.
SPK_1: But the reason only it's possible
SPK_1: is because there is the dual relationship
SPK_1: between the quantum and.
SPK_1: So it wouldn't be possible
SPK_1: without the highest sacrifice.
SPK_1: That's why two commandments of Christ
SPK_1: are in direct, again, causal relationship.
SPK_1: You cannot love your neighbor
SPK_1: without loving Christ.
SPK_1: Physically, you can't.
SPK_1: People suck.
SPK_1: Like, for various reasons.
SPK_1: Like, have you met people?
SPK_1: Like, honestly, like, that's the soul of your joke.
SPK_1: If you don't believe in it, like, why would you do it?
SPK_1: But if you believe in it, well,
SPK_1: there is a chance you will be able to do this.
SPK_1: And if you do this,
SPK_1: then the whole, this quantitative limits
SPK_1: and even theoretical limits, they just stop working.
SPK_1: It's like jumping from linear algebra
SPK_1: into completely different space, topography of space.
SPK_0: Right.
SPK_1: Which we don't know how to operate in it,
SPK_1: just to be clear.
SPK_1: That's the weird part.
SPK_1: We can kind of imagine hell in a way.
SPK_1: Imagining heaven, that's pretty tough,
SPK_1: tough to do.
SPK_0: Well, and of course, the point is that once you've accomplished
SPK_0: an adequate degree of participation in liturgy,
SPK_0: once you've adequately surrendered to living in
SPK_0: and through faith, that's not really a question.
SPK_0: It's, in fact, becomes irrelevant.
SPK_0: Yeah, the image that I had once was like,
SPK_0: first you thought you were falling,
SPK_0: and then you discovered that you were actually flying.
SPK_0: You don't know how to fly, but flying, you know,
SPK_0: flying is what is happening.
SPK_0: You know, it's the feeling, it's the feeling, right?
SPK_0: As you jump, it looks like falling.
SPK_0: You're not in control.
SPK_0: You're surrendering to something.
SPK_0: Initially, you think gravity,
SPK_0: but then you begin to realize that there's no bottom to it.
SPK_0: And it's not falling.
SPK_0: It never was falling.
SPK_0: It just felt like falling when you thought you were a person
SPK_0: who was walking along the ground.
SPK_0: When you thought that you were yourself was something
SPK_0: that under its own will, rationally took responsibility,
SPK_0: responsibility for controlling navigation through reality.
SPK_0: So when that went away, that thought it was falling.
SPK_0: But at a certain point, you recognize that was never reality,
SPK_0: and it was never falling.
SPK_0: It was actually flying.
SPK_1: And that's the tricky part,
SPK_1: because like what we've been kind of also hinting at,
SPK_1: it's in this system of like topological element,
SPK_1: there is what this jump is effectively,
SPK_1: it's becoming more and more,
SPK_1: so it's becoming more of you.
SPK_1: So like, that's the whole idea of humility
SPK_1: and the whole idea of a name.
SPK_1: Like, again, also connects that like why it is maybe
SPK_1: materially possible because effectively through humbling
SPK_1: yourself to your own logos, to your own identity,
SPK_1: you are not becoming less of you and limiting your will
SPK_1: in a direct way.
SPK_1: Like the limit means making something less of,
SPK_1: but the trick happens that you actually,
SPK_1: by surrendering, by taking this,
SPK_1: you are actually starting to becoming more of you.
SPK_0: Right.
SPK_0: Oh, that's interesting.
SPK_0: Although here's the, it's not the trick.
SPK_1: Not the trick, but paradox.
SPK_1: How would I say?
SPK_1: Paradox, let's do paradox for good things.
SPK_0: But there is a trick, and the trick happens here,
SPK_0: which is it doesn't seem like that's actually
SPK_0: how it's going to happen.
SPK_0: And in fact, it feels like exactly the opposite
SPK_0: is absolutely certain.
SPK_0: And I think it has to, right?
SPK_1: Otherwise it becomes a deal.
SPK_0: Otherwise it becomes a deal, exactly.
SPK_0: Yeah, exactly.
SPK_0: Like, hey, of course I'll surrender
SPK_0: as long as I get to be more of my own self.
SPK_0: It's like, yeah, you do get to be more of your own self,
SPK_0: but you're not going to believe that at all.
SPK_1: Yes.
SPK_1: Even if you know it.
SPK_1: That's the tricky part.
SPK_0: You'll experience this absolutely as death.
SPK_0: You'll experience this absolutely as sacrifice.
SPK_0: Everything in you, because of course it really,
SPK_0: in some poor critical sense it is,
SPK_0: because the self that you've carefully constructed,
SPK_0: the as if self that you began to identify with,
SPK_0: is in fact going to die.
SPK_1: Yeah, because again, I mean, generations, you,
SPK_1: like you have a baggage, like let's be realistic.
SPK_1: And the problem is like, you have so much baggage
SPK_1: that you started to treat baggage as you.
SPK_1: Like you kind of don't separate yourself from baggage.
SPK_1: So when your baggage is burning, it burning,
SPK_1: you are burning like in this moment.
SPK_1: Right, right.
SPK_0: Okay, so let's do the, let's do the checksum.
SPK_0: I'm beginning to suspect maybe why you chose
SPK_0: to have this dialogue with me.
SPK_0: As I've mentioned, I don't know if I've mentioned it
SPK_0: while I've been recording,
SPK_0: but I've mentioned it at least a few times.
SPK_0: Up until relatively recently,
SPK_0: I was in fact very actively involved in,
SPK_0: in a profoundly Gnostic effort,
SPK_0: in the sense that we're talking about it.
SPK_0: And here's what I mean.
SPK_0: I and others, I think correctly,
SPK_0: saw that the end of the civilization
SPK_0: in which we live is coming.
SPK_0: For many of the reasons we've described,
SPK_0: we are reaching the fragile stage.
SPK_0: We are reaching the, we can believe in nothing stage.
SPK_0: We are reaching the perturbation of something
SPK_0: like the stochastic barbarian stage.
SPK_0: We're reaching the limits.
SPK_0: We're reaching all of these different metrics
SPK_0: that if you look at it in the objective,
SPK_0: the objective is going to fail.
SPK_0: And we've definitely reached the impotent stage.
SPK_0: We're admired in the impotent stage.
SPK_0: There's no way we can solve the problem with who we are.
SPK_0: But the response that we came up with was initially,
SPK_0: and for the most part,
SPK_0: a response that comes from the Gnostic lineage.
SPK_0: And that is, well, we must constitute some new kind of as if,
SPK_0: some new kind of will, some new kind of agency, yeah,
SPK_0: that is, has, I mean, the language was actually
SPK_0: quite specific, has a level of,
SPK_0: of reason, a level of knowledge and power
SPK_0: that is in fact adequate, larger than the size
SPK_0: of the problems that we're facing, right?
SPK_0: So you say, hey, I have a problem size 10.
SPK_0: I've got a solution size eight.
SPK_0: It's not going to work.
SPK_0: Well, what I'll do is I'll make a problem size 12.
SPK_0: And how do we do that?
SPK_0: There's a variety of different ways you can do it.
SPK_0: And point in fact, there's a variety
SPK_0: of different ways you can't do it.
SPK_0: AI can't solve the problem, oddly enough.
SPK_0: That's the effort that's going to be tried and it won't work.
SPK_0: And so I, and some
SPK_0: others began to try to figure out what is a proper solution look like.
SPK_0: Now here's the problem.
SPK_0: This is where I entered into the portal.
SPK_0: You cannot become an honest pagan,
SPK_0: but I did actually become an earnest pagan,
SPK_0: an earnest effort to become an honest pagan.
SPK_0: And then what I mean is this,
SPK_0: with an adequate amount of reason
SPK_0: and an adequate amount of knowledge,
SPK_0: one of the things that you can accomplish is to recognize
SPK_0: that neither reason nor knowledge can do the thing that they claim to do.
SPK_0: You reach the limits of reason.
SPK_0: You reach the limits of knowledge.
SPK_0: You reach the limits of power.
SPK_0: You experience the limits of as if identity, right?
SPK_0: All of these things actually can be perceived.
SPK_0: If you actually look at them closely enough with enough intensity,
SPK_0: which I did, this then leads into the leap of faith,
SPK_0: which is to say the leap into the category of faith.
SPK_0: But from my experience, the leap of faith was initially a leap of faith.
SPK_0: It was like Socrates, let's say.
SPK_0: Meaning some spirit, I don't even know exactly what that means,
SPK_0: but it's going to be something like that.
SPK_1: Some demon.
SPK_0: Some demon.
SPK_0: Yeah. Some demon.
SPK_0: Some Elohim.
SPK_0: We can even say that.
SPK_0: We can be Jews about it.
SPK_0: We can be Hebrews.
SPK_0: Okay.
SPK_0: But it's interesting because if you're on the path of earnest pagan,
SPK_0: then you're actually beginning to enter into the proper path.
SPK_0: It is not a good path.
SPK_0: It is not an easy path.
SPK_0: It is not a path that separates you even the least bit from suffering.
SPK_0: In fact, because you've now begun the process of leaving the Gnostic,
SPK_0: we call it salve, not salvation, but salve,
SPK_0: you're beginning to feel all of the things that were being held back by that salve
SPK_0: in all the different ways, subjectively, spiritually, emotionally, relationally.
SPK_0: Your identity goes away completely.
SPK_0: And of course, you are in fact finding yourself in too many relationships with too many demons.
SPK_0: And you have to figure out how to deal with that.
SPK_0: But in my case, by the grace of God,
SPK_0: I was brought ultimately to an adequate level of humility to actually receive that grace.
SPK_0: So I stand here as an experiential embodiment.
SPK_0: As an embodiment of the arc of the story that you have been telling.
SPK_0: And I can say, we do.
SPK_0: Oh, good. We both do.
SPK_1: We've been telling.
SPK_0: Oh, we've been telling.
SPK_0: Yes, that I've been participating in.
SPK_1: And I've been telling myself also.
SPK_1: Gnostic itself, like, not as visibly maybe as your story, but in spirit still.
SPK_1: I wasn't still.
SPK_0: Yeah, so I can speak to the hierarchs of the contemporary Gnostic revival.
SPK_1: In a way.
SPK_0: And I can say, hey guys, I can save you some trouble.
SPK_0: I will also be buying you a lot of trouble, but I'll save you a bigger trouble.
SPK_0: It's not going to work.
SPK_0: We know what the right answer is.
SPK_0: The right answer is right there.
SPK_1: It's paradoxical.
SPK_0: It's paradoxical.
SPK_0: It involves even embracing paradox as a part of reality.
SPK_0: Mystery is fine.
SPK_0: Don't worry about it. It's okay.
SPK_1: But the Gnostic paradox cannot work.
SPK_0: Oh, the answer, but the thing.
SPK_0: Sorry, I can finish.
SPK_0: So then you can imagine yourself as a hierarch.
SPK_0: And the problem of this, the problem is quite salient.
SPK_0: If your powered armor is very limited, it's not that hard to get rid of.
SPK_0: But if your power armor is monstrous, your powered armor is powerful, then it's very difficult to exit it.
SPK_0: And here's the only thing that can be said.
SPK_0: You are in fact actually loved.
SPK_0: It is actually the case that your atrophied self is loved, is lovable, and is who you really are anyway.
SPK_0: So although it is terrifying to leave that powered armor, it's the only way to get to the place you want to go to.
SPK_1: Because ultimately you'll look for us.
SPK_1: You look for love.
SPK_1: That's ultimate.
SPK_1: All this running in a circle is all searching for love, which is by definition not inside the circle, but.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: It's funny.
SPK_0: You can almost imagine that the other side of that conversation is a handful of people that one might imagine.
SPK_0: In some sense, you're even talking to the one fallen son.
SPK_1: Well, I think let's end here.
SPK_1: I'm grateful to you.
SPK_1: I'm grateful to the spirit.
SPK_1: And I hope good things will come to it.
SPK_1: I hope good things will come to it.
SPK_1: But I love this journey.
SPK_1: It was a paradoxical and interesting story.
SPK_1: And had warnings, not warnings, heads up ahead, but confession.
SPK_1: I don't know how it happened.
SPK_1: Like if you ask me to repeat the story, I won't be able to.
SPK_1: So that's why I find the most interesting part.
SPK_1: So see you next time.
SPK_0: Yeah, it's a little intense.
SPK_0: That's good.