SPK_0: We have begun with a diagnosis of this problem of Gnosticism and the fact of its presence and the fact of its invisibility.
SPK_0: And now we've begun the part of teasing it apart with the first horseman of the apocalypse, reason and the way that reason operates.
SPK_0: In some sense, a little bit of a sense of, okay, what do we mean by reason?
SPK_0: And how does reason go awry?
SPK_0: We don't want to attach everything.
SPK_0: We don't want to lay it all at the foot of reason.
SPK_0: Reason playing its role improperly is very closely tied.
SPK_0: And if you're paying attention, you saw at least four or five other threads begin to come up.
SPK_0: So now we're beginning to really get into the heart of the matter.
SPK_0: We're starting to really get into the space where there's enough between us.
SPK_0: That hopefully we can actually really, really begin to grasp the problem we're dealing with.
SPK_1: Yeah, so Guilty, even in the previous episode, slipped up several times.
SPK_1: Really wanted to go into this particular direction, what becomes with reason in a Gnostic way, if it follows a Gnostic way.
SPK_1: And what becomes with reason is that knowledge becomes power or becomes equivocated with power.
SPK_1: And power becomes equivocated with knowledge.
SPK_1: There is all this interesting relationship starting playing out.
SPK_1: And to start telling the story of knowledge as a power, which, just in case, is the foundational slogan of our civilization, literally, knowledge is power.
SPK_1: Like, that's how modernity literally started, it's a famous writing of Bacon, like, so it's not an interpretation, taking something from the ground and lifting it in a spotlight.
SPK_1: But this story starts way before Bacon, like, in a way it starts in a garden, but it also starts in a desert.
SPK_1: We won't go into the garden yet, at least I'm not ready to go into the garden.
SPK_1: But I can remember desert, partially because I spent quite a lot of time in the last years in a desert, so it feels very close.
SPK_1: But it starts in the desert in Palestine, where Jesus is tempted by a devil.
SPK_1: And it starts with this first very practical and very particular temptation, which, truth be told, we as a secular people rarely give us even time to notice what is so...
SPK_1: Like, we don't go into the depths of this temptation.
SPK_1: Just a reminder, Jesus is fasting for 40 days, hungry, like, literally.
SPK_1: Like, that's kind of what is mentioned.
SPK_1: So, the desire arose into him, certain desires, and that's as the moment of temptation.
SPK_1: There are three temptations.
SPK_1: We start with the first.
SPK_1: And the first temptation is to turn stones into bread.
SPK_1: So, what it has to do with us?
SPK_1: Because the guy is hungry, make stones into bread.
SPK_1: Let's stop aside.
SPK_1: What is it?
SPK_1: Like, ultimately, like, on its surface level, the moment I pronounce, it's power over matter.
SPK_1: Like, any material form of power.
SPK_1: Like, it doesn't matter if it's a splitting atom.
SPK_1: Whether it's, I don't know, running.
SPK_1: running a 300,000-mile plane or whatever it is, space travels.
SPK_1: It's all about turning stones into bread.
SPK_1: It's a power to transcend material limitations of phenomenons.
SPK_1: Alchemical principle to turn lead into gold.
SPK_1: But that's the premise of the whole, if in effect, reason.
SPK_1: Like, you're still here not exactly on knowledge yet.
SPK_1: You still can even say that that's what, in a way, reason is trying to achieve,
SPK_1: to go beyond the limits, like to go through the limitations,
SPK_1: to feed the hungry, to turn stones into breads.
SPK_1: But it's not just what is happening.
SPK_1: This story is not alone in what is happening.
SPK_1: Why I brought the word power?
SPK_1: Because in the moment when you imagine that you have a knowledge achieved by reason
SPK_1: to turn stones into bread, it immediately creates a new power relationship.
SPK_1: The one who can feed, the one who can do it,
SPK_1: the one who cannot.
SPK_1: And that story tells us a very interesting part of the still-reason part,
SPK_1: which we often overlook.
SPK_1: There is no such thing as neutral reason.
SPK_1: Any reason is necessarily welded by whom.
SPK_1: And in an act of welding this reason, it becomes power.
SPK_1: And that's why knowledge necessarily becomes power.
SPK_0: Very nice.
SPK_0: I mean, Machiavelli very specifically plays with the tension.
SPK_0: And when he advises the prince and he says,
SPK_0: look, you're trapped.
SPK_0: On the one hand, you don't want to change anything.
SPK_0: Because any disequilibrium in your territory leads to some instability
SPK_0: that can overthrow what you're doing.
SPK_0: And yet, you're surrounded by other princes.
SPK_0: And any one of those princes who chooses to take a bite from the apple
SPK_0: has a chance of getting power, an asymmetric advantage,
SPK_0: and you're his lunch.
SPK_0: So you and the other princes are playing the game,
SPK_0: the dark forest game.
SPK_0: So we see this, right?
SPK_0: We see this trap.
SPK_0: That's step two.
SPK_1: Effectively, there's a step two.
SPK_0: There's a step two.
SPK_0: So first, I suppose what I'll do is I will confess
SPK_0: and ground this in very experiential.
SPK_0: Some number of years ago, 10, 15, I can't remember.
SPK_0: I was having a conversation with my friend, Eric Weinstein.
SPK_0: He was in New York at the time.
SPK_0: And he was very frustrated.
SPK_0: With the fact that he could not get anyone to really attend to his physics.
SPK_0: He had a physics theory or even a meta-theory
SPK_0: that implied across different domains like economics.
SPK_0: And he was very frustrated.
SPK_0: And so I counseled him in my Gnostic wisdom.
SPK_0: I said, you're going about this all wrong.
SPK_0: You need to move to Silicon Valley.
SPK_0: And I told him the story, from my point of view,
SPK_0: of what happened with Newton.
SPK_0: Or how did science actually...
SPK_0: And he said, look, science did not actually get born
SPK_0: on the basis of finding truth.
SPK_0: Science was born on the basis of accruing power
SPK_0: to a certain class of people
SPK_0: who are willing to be open to receive that power
SPK_0: so they could win in a conflict with another class of people.
SPK_0: And because the alliance between scientists and merchants
SPK_1: by means of technology...
SPK_1: Unholy alliance.
SPK_0: Okay, unholy.
SPK_0: Precisely against the church and the king, right?
SPK_0: Achieved actual power success.
SPK_0: Then we live in the aftermath of that world.
SPK_0: And so if you would like to find a way to out-compete
SPK_0: the adversary of those who control the current instantiation of that,
SPK_0: whatever's going on with the relationship between
SPK_0: political power and the academy,
SPK_0: which I called the blue church later,
SPK_0: you need to move to a place where there's a new...
SPK_1: New power seed, effectively.
SPK_0: A new seed of power, exactly.
SPK_0: And the technologists of Silicon Valley
SPK_0: are always looking for more gradients of power.
SPK_0: And they will see the possibility.
SPK_0: And they can deploy resources.
SPK_0: They strategically have...
SPK_0: They have strategic capacity.
SPK_0: There's still a lot of strategic...
SPK_0: As Samuel Berger would say,
SPK_0: they're live players.
SPK_0: At least there's a few.
SPK_0: There's a few.
SPK_0: And so that's the story.
SPK_1: It is the story.
SPK_0: That is the exact story.
SPK_1: But the story is that, like,
SPK_1: what we want to at the moment to say,
SPK_1: well, it's just some bad use of knowledge
SPK_1: or some bad use of power.
SPK_1: And the way I say it,
SPK_1: notice how trick happens without us realizing it.
SPK_1: On a step one,
SPK_1: we already completely separated knowledge
SPK_1: from any kind of ethics.
SPK_1: And yet we say it's a bad use of knowledge.
SPK_1: It is a schizophrenic,
SPK_1: Gnostic opposition we do with ourselves all the time.
SPK_1: Because the whole selling point
SPK_1: and the whole argument against,
SPK_1: let's say, historically the church
SPK_1: was it was limiting speed
SPK_1: and of technological advancement
SPK_1: precisely on ethical reasons.
SPK_1: Like asking 20 times,
SPK_1: are you sure it's worth doing it?
SPK_1: Or is it the way...
SPK_1: Because have you thought about,
SPK_1: like, not all,
SPK_1: but have you thought about these consequences?
SPK_1: Have you thought about this?
SPK_1: That's why we completely misunderstand
SPK_1: the story of Galileo's.
SPK_1: We completely misunderstand
SPK_1: the whole classical narrative of,
SPK_1: you know, evil church oppressing
SPK_1: the bright scientific minds pursuing truth.
SPK_1: Just in case, guys.
SPK_1: Not what historically happened.
SPK_1: It's a myth on its own.
SPK_1: And I just don't have really time to go into it,
SPK_1: like in the historical detail.
SPK_1: But let me point this way.
SPK_1: The problem with Galileo's was not
SPK_1: that he was claiming heliocentricity.
SPK_1: The point was general.
SPK_1: The conflict was that the church was very...
SPK_1: putting this ethical limitation.
SPK_1: It did legitimately put ethical limitation
SPK_1: on pursuit of technological advancement.
SPK_1: Sometimes you can argue for good,
SPK_1: sometimes argue for bad,
SPK_1: but it's not what's important.
SPK_1: What is important in this story
SPK_1: is that at least it had a point
SPK_1: from which to argue about good and bad.
SPK_0: Right.
SPK_1: Whereas the whole principle move of reason
SPK_1: is to liberate itself from good and bad.
SPK_1: There is no good and bad beyond the reason.
SPK_1: Reason is in itself good and bad.
SPK_1: Like more reason good,
SPK_1: less reason bad.
SPK_1: Like that's the ethical structure it operates.
SPK_1: But then immediately you jump into conclusion
SPK_1: because that's a tricky true relationship.
SPK_1: There is no reason without power.
SPK_0: Oh, hold on.
SPK_0: Give me more.
SPK_1: Well, simply,
SPK_1: me knowing how to do something
SPK_1: automatically gives me power to do it.
SPK_1: At least potential power.
SPK_0: Yes, yes.
SPK_0: Nice.
SPK_0: Okay, so what we find is that there is both...
SPK_0: It is a two-edged sword.
SPK_1: All necessary and always.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_0: If it didn't do that,
SPK_0: then it would be irrelevant.
SPK_1: Which they find out very quickly.
SPK_0: And so therefore it does.
SPK_0: Okay, fair enough.
SPK_0: A lot of branches here.
SPK_0: What do we do?
SPK_0: I feel like we may want to spend
SPK_0: a little bit of time on the plague.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_1: That's a really good place to do.
SPK_0: And also, again, on this notion of
SPK_0: like a downward slope.
SPK_0: You know, I guess it's sort of the eschaton
SPK_0: at the bottom of this journey.
SPK_1: Yes, there is an eschaton.
SPK_1: Yeah, that feels intense.
SPK_1: But let's start with the plague.
SPK_1: Let's just start with a simple example,
SPK_1: just to have stats somewhere.
SPK_1: Because obviously, plague was a shock for...
SPK_1: Like, again, we recently experienced COVID.
SPK_1: Pretty bad.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: But nothing can close what the medieval people
SPK_1: experienced when the plague came.
SPK_1: In fact, this is where this unholy alliance
SPK_1: between science and power emerged.
SPK_1: Because the only way to control the spread of epidemics
SPK_1: was effectively to enforce a quarantine.
SPK_1: Quarantine is not...
SPK_1: Knowledge forcing is power.
SPK_1: You needed both.
SPK_1: You needed a line of soldiers
SPK_1: standing around the city,
SPK_1: killing everyone coming to and from the city,
SPK_1: and creating effectively a quarantine zone.
SPK_1: And this, those who did it survived.
SPK_1: Those who didn't do, don't.
SPK_1: But that's where you can see this alliance.
SPK_1: Knowledge and power were visibly shown.
SPK_1: It's always the case,
SPK_1: but it was kind of a revelatory moment
SPK_1: that the two guys needed each other.
SPK_1: Like, one step.
SPK_1: Second step obviously came later with exploration.
SPK_1: Knowledge how to do a certain model of ship
SPK_1: really visibly produce you quantum leap
SPK_1: of available resources in form of gold,
SPK_1: or spices, or anything else.
SPK_1: On the one hand, so it's for your internal power struggle.
SPK_1: Sure.
SPK_1: But also, and this is more interesting,
SPK_1: external power struggle.
SPK_1: As later, most famous principle of British,
SPK_1: British colonialism speaks,
SPK_1: I am right and you are not.
SPK_1: I have machine gun, you do not.
SPK_1: Might makes right.
SPK_1: You can pretend you're still,
SPK_1: and remember, connecting with the first,
SPK_1: and all this while bettering the world.
SPK_0: Nice.
SPK_0: Cause you always have to give that therapeutic piece,
SPK_0: a piece.
SPK_0: And the, the...
SPK_1: Improving the quality of life.
SPK_0: The conscience must always be at least a little bit resolved.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_1: We are not barbarians.
SPK_1: Yes.
SPK_0: Right.
SPK_0: Okay.
SPK_0: So let's see.
SPK_0: So we have, in some sense now we're actually doing diagnosis of the mechanics.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: And this is fine.
SPK_0: This is good to explicate because we're in the middle of the arc.
SPK_0: And we're part of the, part of the movements we're in.
SPK_0: The patient is open.
SPK_0: Let's talk about.
SPK_0: So we have a, we have a demoralization event, right?
SPK_0: We have a place where lived faith, right?
SPK_0: The, the, the medieval image.
SPK_1: Very simple.
SPK_1: The, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the,
SPK_1: the demoralization because
SPK_1: you're talking about how God, if God allows this, at least he is not in this
SPK_1: world anymore.
SPK_1: He might have created laws.
SPK_1: He might set up things in motion.
SPK_1: That basically at the birth of daze.
SPK_1: The birth of modern daze was closely connected to plague, to religious war,
SPK_1: to a set of like other pretty catastrophic events in European history.
SPK_1: So,
SPK_1: at least it made it very easy to believe.
SPK_1: Well, if he is, he doesn't care.
SPK_0: And you can, you can feel like the embodied extremists.
SPK_0: Okay.
SPK_1: someone with knowledge say, God is not here.
SPK_0: Prince is here. Well, no, I'm very specifically,
SPK_0: let's say you have a godly Prince or a Prince who really, really is godly.
SPK_0: And you go to him and say,
SPK_0: you're going to have to take your soldiers and surround that town and quarantine it and kill
SPK_0: everybody who wants to go in and kill anybody who wants to go out. And the Prince will say,
SPK_0: but everyone in the city will, I'm leaving them to their death. And you say, yes, but there is
SPK_0: no alternative. This is what must happen. This is going to push a human being beyond the limits
SPK_0: of human morality. It is more than the heart can bear. It is impossible. And this is again,
SPK_0: so we now have speed.
SPK_1: We have scope. We now have intensity. It's very intense. The faith of that
SPK_0: godly Prince must have been broken. Okay. So now we're, we're now in the place where reason steps
SPK_0: in and reason does actually step in. Reason says, Hey, I solved a problem for you here.
SPK_1: Here is some gum powder.
SPK_0: Yeah. Look, the people who didn't do it, they're just gone. You sacrificed
SPK_0: something profound, but now let me rationalize it. If you hadn't done it, you would have lost.
SPK_0: We'll probably do some therapy over here and the flavor of whatever you need. Maybe it's because
SPK_0: you got richer. Maybe it's because fill in the blank. It doesn't matter. Therapy is very easy
SPK_0: as we will know. Maybe you get to eat more mutton. Um, and now we're beginning to, we've
SPK_1: actually look at the art.
SPK_0: You can look at the art. You can look at a beautiful cathedral. Exactly.
SPK_0: All these, all these things that can be put in place. And so we're beginning to get a bit of a
SPK_0: sense, right? At the local level, you will run into some encounter and the encounter will, will,
SPK_0: will overwhelm your capacity to be in relationship with wholeness.
SPK_0: Again, speed, scope, intensity.
SPK_0: Other faculties will step in. And the principal thing that other faculties will do is they will
SPK_0: try to heal the gap.
SPK_0: Try to resolve the problem on the basis of their own capacities. And here's the thing. Locally,
SPK_0: they will probably succeed.
SPK_0: Yes. Right. They will succeed by creating a blind spot.
SPK_0: More importantly, they will succeed very visibly.
SPK_1: Right. Very intensely.
SPK_0: Exactly. But by virtue of creating a blind spot. So they say salience, they will succeed
SPK_0: saliently.
SPK_0: Yes. Focus on the problem in front of you. We're going to have to ignore all the
SPK_0: downstream negative consequences of what's happening because that needs to be resolved.
SPK_0: So, you know, orient from,
SPK_0: the disposition, the posture, the quality of relationship, the community of relevance
SPK_0: towards that, which is focused towards salience. This happens in war. This is why I was,
SPK_0: sorry, a little bit of a bridge, but maybe it's exactly right. I read a book called the,
SPK_0: I think it's called the Ethics of Beauty.
SPK_1: Yes. It's a great book to read anybody, please.
SPK_0: Like, and in it, one of the things that Patizis brings forth, and I'm, this is second order
SPK_0: heresy, not heresy.
SPK_0: Hearsay. Zero degree heresy, I hope. In the context of a just war, the soldier is intrinsically out
SPK_0: of communion.
SPK_0: Yes. The point is not that he is out of communion. There's no way around it. The
SPK_0: point is he can only stay out of communion for a limited period of time. Meaning when you're in
SPK_0: war, you are forced into this moment of salience. You are having to focus on something right in
SPK_0: front of you with significant intensity. To say, to use our metaphor now, your left brain has to
SPK_0: be activated.
SPK_0: All morality is now pushed to the back and there's a very simple focus. Destroy that which is before me. Which means you're out of communion. And now there's a process of how do we come back into communion. But when an entire group is brought out of communion, now you're on a trajectory. Now you're flying willy nilly through what is ultimately a pre-Christian experience. It is communion is shattered. How do you come back into proper communion? And this has an interesting point.
SPK_0: And it has a certain trajectory to it. So the quality we're talking about is that the Gnostic heresy is like an ill-healed wound.
SPK_1: Oh yeah. An ill-healed wound, or just it's a, it's kind of a poison which has a very good numbing effect for something which, and it's a very slow, poison is slow, numbing effect is good. Like really good and like, it's a numbing effect that even works, you can say generationally.
SPK_1: Like poison effect.
SPK_1: works generationally at first doesn't even like it wasn't you don't even understand what is truly
SPK_1: happening because again historical example there is an interesting intermediate part like in this
SPK_1: whole story between plague and the full-on modernity full-on enlightenment and effectively
SPK_1: it's called christian stoicism it's effectively this you know this agape this love this faith
SPK_1: like yeah it's important relevant but let's focus on our duty as a good citizen as a good ruler
SPK_1: it is through duty we actualize us as being a christian let's run about it yeah the tricky part
SPK_1: and that's like why it is inseparable there's an any knowledge it would be okay if you kept the who
SPK_1: in play but you are precisely in the preliminary step removing the who from the picture that is
SPK_1: the trick and yes again referencing the book uh ethics of beauty he writes about it that's the
SPK_1: difference like
SPK_1: what emerges like a tendency in this whole uh the war problem is that instead of accepting the
SPK_1: tragedy of four and sharing it which is very important he talks a lot and that's behind the
SPK_1: reason like in order six the banners are blessed it's not because killing is good it's because we
SPK_1: are sharing the responsibility of the soldiers who are defending and dying for us so we are
SPK_1: participating in it so it's and then we effectively coming be ideally we need to come be healed
SPK_1: together
SPK_1: but it's hard and it's based on different assumptions ontology it has a very different
SPK_1: foundation elements which we already touched but what we can do instead we can do two things either
SPK_1: we can say that it's not bad at all it's beyond evil and good it's just this it's reasonable
SPK_1: it's powerful it's not about good and bad right right it's it's not personal it's not personal
SPK_1: just business yes that's one of the tricks which is easy to happen
SPK_1: and since we have an opportunity to do it and if i don't do it somebody else's does it right which
SPK_0: reason rationalizes very effectively very effectively and the other false promises again
SPK_1: or okay so let's remake the world in a way you don't even have to make such a choice
SPK_1: ah very nice very nice the basket let's give everybody a basket yeah how to solve the problem
SPK_1: of robbery let's give everybody enough very simple logical idea like
SPK_1: on a reasonable rational level it doesn't work because it misses the core point but
SPK_1: you can see how from the assumptions we are working it is the most necessary conclusion
SPK_1: and what is the you already said the word technique behind it that's the knowledge
SPK_1: it's the knowledge how it's the knowledge how to feed it's the knowledge how to
SPK_1: to kill it's the knowledge how it's it's a know-how even like that's what it becomes
SPK_0: oh so let's let's drill into this more i want i want to i want you to spend more time on like
SPK_0: nature of knowledge and and what are like what are the trade-offs of the balance i have a very very
SPK_0: good feel for reason and how reason does what it does and why and where spend more time on knowledge
SPK_1: so i have uh well again knowledge is at least the way i use it in this series is effectively
SPK_1: applied reason yeah knowledge is power this is knowledge is power yeah the trick is that's the
SPK_1: trick is i think we pretend that it's a neutral power
SPK_1: that this is not the power of whom it's just a power so it's just a raw force we do it's just
SPK_1: a raw energy yeah but another book referencing if anybody wants to read technopoly postman
SPK_1: writes a lot about it it's a lie there is no such thing as a neutral technology
SPK_1: any technology actually carries an imprint of a will which created this technology by the fact
SPK_1: that it creates an emergence it creates an asymmetry of relation between the ones who know
SPK_1: how to use a technology and the one who doesn't know and it's a automatic asymmetrical power
SPK_1: relationship so you are trading it's actually interesting thing i didn't think about it but
SPK_1: you are trading organic asymmetry to inorganic asymmetry because we're so that's the thing
SPK_1: notice how weird it is we're so offended with any organic asymmetry it's so unfair to us
SPK_1: you can run plus i don't know how to run fast i'm a man somebody is a woman like people
SPK_1: all these different kinds of natural symmetry deep inside see at least not as as to the
SPK_1: extent i am agnostic it offends me there is something which is carrying offended but if
SPK_1: but if it's a technical asymmetry i'm fine with it like that surely somebody knows how to go code
SPK_1: and create things which control my life so i don't know how to cut but it's not a problem of course but how do you set a upPAW to somehow doing anti- behaviors and how do you set up off-pathass systems in addition to the contributors within the構 existence and form of your code for a good
SPK_1: fine i don't feel any of this sort you know this is how it's interestingly pleasant because why
SPK_1: because we pretend it's neutral remember in the previous conversation we had an author
SPK_0: that pretends to be removed from the picture yes yes yes that's and so neutral it's neutral
SPK_0: within which then also implies something like and therefore in principle you could have learned to
SPK_0: code yes so it is your choice yes you chose yeah and that's games work that way yeah you play you
SPK_0: you play the way you choose to play and it's on you you were not you did not choose how you were
SPK_0: born no so that can be very unfair but you did choose what you studied so that's on you okay
SPK_0: so you want more power gain more knowledge gain more knowledge and it's and by the way because
SPK_0: unequal access to knowledge is unfair we'll make sure that we have equal access to knowledge
SPK_0: so
SPK_0: we're trying to so we have a couple of different pieces here we need to sort of again maybe tease
SPK_0: apart one is is this notion of asymmetry um and as you say i think this is exactly right the essence
SPK_0: of knowledge is asymmetry the whole point of knowledge is asymmetry i know how to dig a well
SPK_0: you don't know how to do well prior to knowing how to dig a well i had a certain relationship
SPK_0: with reality after knowing how to dig a well i have a qualitatively distinct relationship with
SPK_0: reality that change is the point
SPK_1: and it's real it's very real it's yes it is just
SPK_1: to be clear i'm not saying it's not real and it is almost no this is very real
SPK_0: this is very real and then our current world is the maybe the most real um okay so that's one
SPK_0: the reason why i hammer on that is because this is the essence when we say knowledge we mean that
SPK_0: we mean the deliberate intentional effective use of a variety of different human faculty
SPK_0: to achieve an asymmetry in relationship to possibility yes a qualitative shift
SPK_0: in in your capacity to act in the world two because knowledge is not intrinsically universal
SPK_0: it also creates an asymmetry horizontally there are those who have it and those who do not by
SPK_0: definition those who do not are living in a previous state of capacity in relationship to
SPK_0: reality those who do are living in the current state of reality or in the state post knowledge
SPK_0: okay okay three this is a different way of thinking about it but this has to do with the fact of
SPK_0: schism these kinds of asymmetries are they break apart communion and they they break apart
SPK_0: the ways that we have of maintaining wholeness of relationality with each other just a little
SPK_1: bit soft on it and deep on it it creates it creates necessarily a possibility of community
SPK_1: being broken apart here is a possibility yeah yeah fair enough yeah fair enough and the image
SPK_0: the image i have is actually very a very
SPK_0: i have is actually very a very
SPK_0: simple one it's very fun so there's a thing that happens where i grew up where you get into a
SPK_0: uh an inner tube do you know what this is it's like a the thing that's inside a tire okay a big
SPK_0: a big torus filled with air usually black because it gets hot you get in the water
SPK_0: we're all floating down the river with these in these inner tubes and it's very floating
SPK_0: to stay together you link arms as you've now formed a flotilla something that looks like a
SPK_0: wholeness then you hit rapids and you hit water that's moving faster differential shearing
SPK_0: strengths are pushed against it at a certain point under under the right conditions the flotilla
SPK_0: breaks apart that's what we're describing yeah right we are linked together in something like a
SPK_0: wholeness by things bonds relationships that have a certain strength as we enter into knowledge the
SPK_0: differential in terms of power in one direction and the differential in terms of asymmetry in
SPK_0: another direction creates shearings and we're able to break apart the flotilla we're able to
SPK_0: bring and under certain conditions these will break things apart okay so that's part of the kind
SPK_0: of the natural philosophy of knowledge power and community oh so then we have an iteration on that
SPK_0: yes this is the uh the liberal capitulation to pointing towards which is something like there is
SPK_0: no pointing towards because that's the beauty like no no i mean i mean riding the energy of
SPK_0: that okay yeah or or furling the sail
SPK_0: against the winds of asymmetry this is your british right the british come with the straight
SPK_0: face of look i've got machine guns you don't that's where that's how that's how this thing
SPK_0: grounds out at the end right so liberalism kind of says look fuck it this is how it's going to be
SPK_0: so you got a choice you're either going to be the guy who's on the right side of it or the guy is
SPK_0: on the wrong side of it be on the right side of history be on the right side of history and how
SPK_0: is this going to work because i'm going to sell you a bunch of bullshit on how the right side of
SPK_0: history looks like you're not being able to do it you're not being able to do it you're not being able to do it
SPK_0: on the front end of this thing i'm going to get on the front end of this thing more importantly
SPK_1: back to the point of salvation what starts tricking here like i am very inclined like very inclined
SPK_1: effectively to build a pretty good and easy chain i have this technology that's why i'm chosen
SPK_1: that's why this technology came to me oh yes yes very important yeah very important why our society
SPK_1: is better well because we produce machine gun it's self-evident it is and that's the civilization
SPK_0: that's the whole white civilization is agnostic how could you not be superior this is the the
SPK_0: evidence of superiority of civilization is the capacity to produce more stones into bread right
SPK_0: to feed more people to provide good things to clean up rooms more effectively i have robots
SPK_0: you don't have robots what is going on this is self-evident yes very nice and we do it all the
SPK_0: time and the reason we almost can't even think without doing it yeah well
SPK_1: again that's actually trickier because we can at least that's the neutrality part actually plays
SPK_1: a little bit uh softening for an adversary because it does make us ask ethical question
SPK_1: there is something in this idea of neutrality which is uncomfortable in effect to us yeah like
SPK_0: oh yeah well we have we have to talk about the distinction between the the cities of cain
SPK_0: and the ark of noah yes right because what's going to happen next is
SPK_0: this is going to be oh well are you all loaded like basically are you are you rebuking knowledge
SPK_0: qua knowledge that's a very difficult position to be in yes right what that means is you're saying
SPK_0: i'm going to valorize complete and utter ignorance even language has to go away well no in fact we're
SPK_0: saying not that what we're saying is that there's something that distinguishes the gnostic
SPK_1: civilization from something else which we are in a search for naming just in case we are in a search
SPK_1: for naming yeah but the difference is very clear and one is against the idea of wholeness the
SPK_1: north arc is integrated in the whole ontology of reality yeah it's technology is here ethics
SPK_1: axiology is here and ontology or communion is right here and that's no sark in the techno
SPK_1: like techno world knowledge is just here it just is there is nothing above and there is nothing
SPK_0: beyond it right babylon babble yeah why build the tower to the heavens to make a cell phone just
SPK_1: to be clear really but ultimately because we can because we invented the bricks and mortars
SPK_0: we can okay okay so this is so again we we have is something like the this this sort of this
SPK_0: downward slide to degeneracy yeah in the first few steps it looks and feels awesome really good
SPK_0: and in fact in some sense it is this is the problem there's nothing about not dying from
SPK_0: the plague that is bad yes that's a really a good penicillin is nice it's a good thing and this is
SPK_0: where the church has trouble you know if the church says look i've got really big picture
SPK_0: high concept reasons why you shouldn't save your child from death you're gonna get a lot of people
SPK_0: on the wrong side of that and you got somebody over here who says well i'm just gonna give them
SPK_0: all penicillin fuck you somebody's gonna win somebody's gonna lose that fight and it's hard
SPK_0: to win somebody's gonna lose that fight and it's hard to win somebody's gonna lose that fight
SPK_0: it's hard to say by the way i would not even advise saying it because i don't think it's true
SPK_0: but it's hard to say no let these children die in agony because 150 years from now the downward
SPK_0: slope will have played out very negatively uh this is so interesting so are you familiar with
SPK_0: paul king's north and you're familiar with the with the challenge that he's issued and we're
SPK_0: again but remind those people so so he is he is very specifically said that the word christian
SPK_0: and the word
SPK_0: civilization cannot be put together and i now tend to agree with him yes except he's caught in
SPK_0: the false dichotomy yeah there is something else there's a third term we are trinitarians we are
SPK_0: not dualists there's a third term that can be brought into this equation that is this conversation
SPK_0: not equating this conversation that contains christian and contains things like knowledge
SPK_0: and contains things like reason and contains things like technology and other words that
SPK_0: we'll be describing later that is not civilization
SPK_0: and does not fall into any of these um uh downward spirals okay we already mentioned it before and
SPK_1: this question will keep shining and shining and shining again the key question is the question who
SPK_1: nice because uh that's the whole trick of knowledge like it does create a power symmetry
SPK_1: objectively and it's not and it's not neutral in that sense but it also creates a choice it also
SPK_1: really creates a choice you can dig well to save people you can dig well to make profit it is
SPK_1: choice but to face this choice you cannot do it if you keep it but at least empirically if you
SPK_1: keep technology free from ethics you can't even pose this question you can as i said you can say
SPK_1: it's good or bad use of technology but the only good or way the good or bad use of technology is
SPK_1: its efficiency there is no other good or bad characteristics in terms of technology and
SPK_1: instinct to any technology sorry good machine girl skills 100 people bad machine girl skills
SPK_1: no one that's what good or bad any technology is good or bad is a heart again so the problem
SPK_1: with civilization it's built upon taking heart out of the picture how to call a community like
SPK_1: basically it is a neutral i mean we know how it's called effectively you are talking about
SPK_1: something i like neutral new jerusalem but not through the means of technology basically again
SPK_1: it's completely opposite causality technology might come it might come handy but it doesn't
SPK_0: come first so it's interesting because it seems like the reality is the exact opposite of the
SPK_0: instinct that you mentioned earlier in terms of the organic and the inorganic here's what i mean
SPK_0: my uncle was a very large man six foot nine three hundred and something pounds
SPK_0: six foot nine three hundred and something pounds
SPK_0: and he was always big what that meant was that he cultivated an intrinsic ethics he had to learn
SPK_0: how to be careful he had to learn how to control his temper he learned very early that if he didn't
SPK_0: do that bad things would happen and there was something about the speed of development and
SPK_0: the context of development and even the nature of his his metabolism in his heart where he
SPK_0: cultivated that i'm not saying it's necessary but the point is there's a coupling here now
SPK_0: um let's just say me i did not go through that i was never that kind of a person
SPK_0: i could have a gun without developing any ethical capacity i could have access to power bond on the
SPK_0: basis of knowledge the inorganic is strictly decoupled from any process that actually binds
SPK_0: the power that you build or you you have access to from anything that would connect that power
SPK_0: into a fully integrated system that would enable that power to be wielded properly
SPK_1: more importantly the very attempt to do it is considered evil yes and stupid simultaneously yes
SPK_1: because it decreases power yeah that is like on the first step it does decrease power right
SPK_1: legitimately or like speed again the speed the intensity like it does decrease it like right
SPK_0: so so we here we're here sitting on the thing known as the uh the multi-polar trap or the
SPK_0: moloch problem right depending on which culture you're from i kind of like the moloch one now
SPK_0: because it obviously invokes what i now recognize is an actual demon no but yeah it's good to
SPK_1: give sense in all the names
SPK_1: uh because it is multi-polar it is a good way of putting it and um there is another hidden element
SPK_1: here why no knowledge is power to do what and that's this is i think the trickiest part in it
SPK_1: because it is about heart and before we pretend it too hard not to play but knowledge is a power
SPK_1: to have something without being something to have something with a simple example running
SPK_1: i can't move with the speed of a cheetah with a car i can i'm not a cheater but i want the quality
SPK_1: of cheetah i take this quality separate it and get it and it's always a quick part yeah in fact
SPK_0: somebody recently said something that that i found to be intriguing and confusing which is that
SPK_0: the whole point of technology is to give us power without the expenditure of energy
SPK_1: some perpetual engine something like that right so
SPK_0: for me to achieve the ability to run fast as an organic being i would have to do something like
SPK_0: practice running fast for a long time and still be limited not faster than a cheat and never as
SPK_0: fast as a cheetah well maybe you've seen both for a brief moment but in any event
SPK_0: and the point literally the point of technology is to get me that without expending that energy
SPK_0: by the way which is really interesting because i also get the other side i'm going to push the
SPK_0: energy into the blind spot i'm going to push the energy into the blind spot i'm going to push the
SPK_0: energy into the blind space i'm actually expending probably many many
SPK_0: orders of magnitude more energy just not technically your energy that's my energy yeah
SPK_1: oh that's good like literally like kilocalories like you know fuel it's the whole idea of fuel
SPK_1: i'm expending not my energy i'm making a sacrifice well this is an interesting topic i am yeah like
SPK_1: strong i pretends it's just again so maybe that's kind of one of our topic of our conversations is
SPK_1: as if maybe the point of knowledge it's just it's just this i love it so knowledge is power
SPK_0: power corrupts absolute power corrupts absolutely absolute knowledge corrupts absolutely and we see
SPK_1: it playing all the time because then you have another different like that's a tricky part
SPK_1: coming into play one thing it's about let's say moving running etc so it is important but it is
SPK_1: heavy but what about if a human is a part of technology of course yeah very nice how can i
SPK_1: get this beautiful girl without being chosen by this beautiful girl that starts playing very
SPK_1: interesting immediately because it is also knowledge and you have a and just in case i'm
SPK_1: not speaking it even as a theory you know what is the size of a
SPK_1: market for pickup classes in any developed country i don't even want to know no no but i
SPK_1: don't know either but a lot i know like people basically making millions and billions in it
SPK_1: but what i say it's exactly the same pattern you can't get this i will teach you how i will give
SPK_1: you the knowledge how to get this without humbling yourself actualizing yourself and
SPK_1: reaching the point where it will get to you you don't need to do it
SPK_1: skip it skip the line not even the line change rewrite the world rewrite the code change the
SPK_1: like introduce like it's all place in this story and the problem is we start with organic we start
SPK_1: with nature but we end up with hearts the problem with technology i think and i didn't want to talk
SPK_1: about it actually but i i want to talk about it that it has its inherent tendency being left to
SPK_1: its alone to see everything as a
SPK_1: object it has an intrinsic tendency to replace any subject to subject relationship to object
SPK_1: to subject to object but in fact object to object relationship and it is it alone that's a thing
SPK_1: alone it cannot escape it yeah it's built into it so is there a word or do we actually need to
SPK_0: coin a word that represents knowledge that is not
SPK_1: intrinsically separating or separated i honestly think the way in a certain way of understanding i
SPK_0: think art is way better word ah yes you mean the sense of like uh the fine arts no no just
SPK_1: like this whole principle because and this is maybe not the best word but i've just seen from
SPK_1: experience when you see a good craftsman working on a
SPK_1: chair you see that the better the craft craftsman is even with this inorganic matter he acts as if
SPK_1: it is a life yes doesn't treat it as an object it's a dialogue so and hint hint there is also
SPK_1: a certain the story is a spirit between somebody anyway but that's the story that's i think is an
SPK_1: opposite and that's what it is integrated like so but on a human level we use it even sometimes
SPK_1: the art of raising three children yeah the technique of raising children sounds nice dystopian
SPK_1: yeah yeah yeah very good the art of raising children doesn't sound so at least like well
SPK_1: maybe my feeling of english is not perfect but in my uh extremely hackneyed and almost certainly
SPK_0: heretical so therefore watch out uh theology uh i connect the notion of art to beauty and beauty to
SPK_0: the way that god communicates in the most basic fundamental way that god communicates
SPK_1: in the most basic fundamental way at least in our language i think that's what we yes and so a saint
SPK_0: is first an artist um but very particular artist and we'll again talk it's not an artist in a
SPK_1: let's say romantic way of this word because that's very interesting like what's the meaning
SPK_1: of it and it's interesting the topic of art keeps coming into play because it it it is relative but
SPK_1: yes the antidote to technology is art in a broad sense and it is very interesting even
SPK_1: like in our language we can let's say liberal arts they are not arts i'm sorry like it's
SPK_1: effectively technology it's a marketing technology not liberal arts what it is like and that's the
SPK_1: thing the more we have technology the more we technologize our society the less place it is
SPK_1: for truly art like even like on a formal like institutional level why do i need a department of
SPK_0: classical of classical literature we have the same we have the same downward slide so in step one what
SPK_0: do we have in step two we have the notion of all life properly is art yes all proper life is art
SPK_0: any expression of life that is truly connected and truly guided is art step two some expressions
SPK_0: of life that have particular characteristics like painting and dancing and singing
SPK_0: those are art three particular artifacts the actual painting is art not the process of
SPK_0: painting is art four at the end of the day it's really marketing right it's just a downward
SPK_0: slope it'll end up there every time and so there's something about this downward slope
SPK_0: that has to do with disconnectedness right there's an exit object like ultimately it ends like
SPK_1: removing the who and on each step you are removing the who more and more
SPK_0: so let's hit the the name of who or who because what popped into my head then was also the notion
SPK_0: of communion because the way we operate the level of who oh this is so good okay so who is who is
SPK_0: talking right now
SPK_0: you invited me into this with a very powerful thing which was that you had noticed that
SPK_0: monologue for lack of a better word no longer worked so you said this needs to be done in the
SPK_0: process of dialogue or in fact dialogos to use verveke's term because dialogos is the process
SPK_0: of the formation of a who uh pageau right there is a spirit here the who is the spirit that includes
SPK_0: us and that we participate in this is the antinomy
SPK_0: of them which is therefore what you are restored to that person right to the persony and you
SPK_1: choose to do whatever you want with it you can choose to do whatever you want with it but not
SPK_1: just the body control you can do whatever you want with it when you want with it middle
SPK_1: species on this thing you choose with or without a single thought to address it you can decide
SPK_1: to Beit
SPK_1: be an alternative that this effectively an alternative but back to the optimist side any
SPK_1: good true and beautiful thing you ever experienced in your life is of this nature nothing good came
SPK_1: from technique even the good things you came from technique came from you treating technique as an
SPK_1: art for example you can see it like i remember myself sorry like it's actually interesting
SPK_1: with computers like me getting my first computer i was excited but not because of power because it
SPK_1: was a mystery a miracle a wonder i didn't treat this machine as a object like i didn't know that
SPK_1: i didn't do it but in fact i was treating it as something alive something curious something that
SPK_1: wants to meet me something that i want to engage in a weird form of relationship dance etc etc
SPK_1: and that's why i had joy in this moment i buy a new phone i don't feel
SPK_0: but oh oh by the way and they try to give you back a simulacrum of that feeling
SPK_0: you
SPK_0: which is like that sense of allurement or the sense of glamour they turn this feeling into
SPK_0: technology into technique and through marketing exactly okay so so we have the strip mining of
SPK_0: the soul is a known problematic of this downward spiral but we're also talking about and this is
SPK_0: important there's there's a good there's a good message there is good news and the good news is
SPK_0: actually in some sense very practical there is a way and that way has names like you said art
SPK_0: there are ways for us to come into proper communion with each other i can like it's a
SPK_0: realist we're probably going to resuscitate that we're doing good work on symbol i can is probably
SPK_0: later today or tomorrow but this notion of centering moving from from what and how to who
SPK_0: but noticing that when we heal who the idea of individual completely evaporates and that's the
SPK_1: price we don't want to pay for several reasons which we can actually talk about later because
SPK_1: our next topic is exactly about trust
SPK_1: you