SPK_0: Hello, dear friends. I'm excited to welcome you to the second part of a conversation between me and Richard Rowland, which is a direct continuation of the conversation we had a month ago.
SPK_0: We talked about unity and multiplicity. We talked about Pentecost. We talked about Tower of Babel. We talked about the Leviathan. It was a fascinating conversation, and I invite you all to come and listen to it.
SPK_0: And today, as promised, we are having a part two, which, once again, I'm excited to have. Welcome, Richard.
SPK_1: It's great to be back. Christos Voskresi.
SPK_0: Voskresi. Yeah, so we're recording it after Christos, naturally.
SPK_0: And actually, that's a great transition point, because last time you promised that we will start our second conversation talking about St. Thomas, the twin.
SPK_0: And we celebrated his feast a week ago. Not this Sunday, but the previous Sunday. And yeah, all anew, basically, so not to waste time. Let's go.
SPK_0: Yeah, so St.
SPK_1: Thomas is interesting because he, of all of the missionaries of the early church, you can sort of argue that he's the one that goes the farthest.
SPK_1: Now, there are certain apostles who seem to be, you could say, like apostles to the edge.
SPK_1: They're apostles.
SPK_1: Apostles who go to the edge of the world.
SPK_1: So St. Andrew, just as a quick example, is a very, I mean, a very famous example of this.
SPK_1: St. Andrew, there are like medieval illustrations of St. Andrew, like preaching to the dog-headed men, you know, and so on.
SPK_1: Right. So, but St. Thomas is another one of those sort of apostles to the edge, or like the apostle to the extreme edge of the world.
SPK_1: The.
SPK_1: Some of the early missionary workings of St. Thomas are, they're recorded in, in a, in a, they're recorded in an ancient Christian apocryphal document, which sometimes called the Acts of Thomas, and it is sometimes considered problematic.
SPK_1: There are definitely, like many of these, these really old apocryphal writings, there are different redactions out there, and some of them are a little Gnostic.
SPK_1: And of course, there's also very.
SPK_1: Gnostic redactions of the Gospel of Thomas, right?
SPK_1: One sort of famous example.
SPK_1: But, but, but the story itself, the core story itself is, is, has been received in, in the tradition.
SPK_1: And so one of the things we were talking about was St. Thomas, the twin, right?
SPK_1: He's called Thomas Didymus in the Gospels.
SPK_1: So the sort of the question then is like, well, whose twin is he?
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: Whose twin is he?
SPK_1: And it's funny because when I was in like evangelical Bible college and things like this.
SPK_1: They would sort of speculate, oh, he must have just had a twin, right?
SPK_1: He just had a twin and maybe that's why he's not at the upper room.
SPK_1: Maybe he's, he's not there, you know, because he's going to check on his, his brother or something like that.
SPK_1: But the thing is, all of the, all of the apostles, they had family that they could have been checking on, but they're not.
SPK_1: They're gathered in the upper room, we are told, for fear of the Jews, right?
SPK_1: They, they're afraid, well, Jesus just got, it's, it's simple to understand.
SPK_1: Jesus was just crucified.
SPK_1: And now, now.
SPK_1: They're going to be, they're afraid that they're next, right?
SPK_1: So the tradition of the church, and this is a very old, very early tradition in our, in the Orthodox church and in church history in general.
SPK_1: The tradition of the church is that St.
SPK_1: St.
SPK_1: Thomas was Christ's twin.
SPK_1: They actually, he looks so much like Christ that you would sort of mistake them for each other.
SPK_1: And this is why the apostles start to give him the nickname Didymus, the twin, right?
SPK_1: The lookalike.
SPK_1: So this is then kind of the sort of the theme of the writing, the apocryphal, apocryphal writings around Thomas and around his, his travels and his missionary journey.
SPK_1: So as I think most people are aware, St.
SPK_1: Thomas makes it to all the way to India, where he founds several early Christian communities.
SPK_1: In fact, Christian communities in India now, Orthodox, Evangelical, Roman, Catholic, all across the spectrum, very often refer to themselves.
SPK_1: This as St.
SPK_1: Thomas Christians because of this.
SPK_1: So he makes it out to India.
SPK_1: And while he's out there in India, there is sort of very famous stories of the things that he does, right?
SPK_1: Famous stories of the things that he does.
SPK_1: And a lot of them hinge on the fact that he looks like Christ, right?
SPK_1: And so in some way, like he is Christ or sort of Christ double.
SPK_1: And again, some people like make a big deal about this and say it's sort of Gnostic where like Thomas is like the earthly Christ.
SPK_1: And then Christ is the heavenly Christ or something like this.
SPK_1: But I think it's, I think it's something deeper going on there.
SPK_1: And it has to do with the way that the mission of the church goes to the ends of the earth, which is what Pentecost is about.
SPK_1: So the story goes something like when St.
SPK_1: Thomas is when he's at the, you know, it's after Pentecost and the disciples are beginning to kind of go to the different places around the world.
SPK_1: And Christ actually sells Thomas.
SPK_1: Into slavery.
SPK_1: Because God tells Thomas to go to, I know it's weird.
SPK_1: God tells Thomas to go to India, tells him to go to India, right?
SPK_1: And Thomas is like, well, how am I supposed to get there?
SPK_1: Right?
SPK_1: So this is it.
SPK_1: Christ says, don't worry about it.
SPK_1: Come down to the docks and we'll find some passage.
SPK_1: So they get down to the docks and Christ actually sells St.
SPK_1: Thomas to a slave trader.
SPK_1: And the slave trader is the one who gets him to India.
SPK_1: So then, you know, Thomas has this whole journey, this whole trade.
SPK_1: And he finally gets to India and he gets sold to one of the kings there of one of the of one of the tribes in India.
SPK_1: And and St.
SPK_1: Thomas basically becomes like so.
SPK_1: So there's that kind of, let's say, like an overlap or a parallel to both Joseph Kanda and Daniel.
SPK_1: Exactly.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: So it's an overlap of trying to remember the word for this now.
SPK_1: Polyvalence, let's say.
SPK_1: Like.
SPK_1: Like a polyvalence between between Joseph and Christ and Thomas.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: Because Joseph is also a type of Christ where he's actually one of the main ones in the Old Testament.
SPK_1: Certainly, that's how the church fathers saw it.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: So in the same way that Joseph is sold into slavery and then rises to this high position of trust.
SPK_1: That's what Thomas does as well.
SPK_1: And and there are other parallels as well.
SPK_1: So when Thomas gets to India, he rises to this this high position of trust.
SPK_1: And this king who's about to go away.
SPK_1: For a long time, tells him, tells him, hey, why don't you why don't you, you know, I'm going to be gone for a long time while I'm gone, once you build me a palace.
SPK_1: And Thomas says, yeah, no problem, I'll take care of it.
SPK_1: I'm just going to need money for materials and all these different things.
SPK_1: And so the king goes away on a journey and he writes, you know, a few months later, he writes back to Thomas and he says, hey, how's how's my new palace coming along?
SPK_1: He says, it's going pretty well, your majesty.
SPK_1: I just need a little more money for building materials.
SPK_1: And he says, OK, well, you can have this this money and then writes him again, says, how are things going?
SPK_1: He says, oh, it's going fine, but I need money for the roof and I need money for these pillars.
SPK_1: I need money for the throne and like all these different things.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: So the king keeps authorizing more and more money.
SPK_1: And finally, many years later, he comes back, he comes back and he comes back and finds that there's been no palace built at all.
SPK_1: And he starts asking the other men of the court about this.
SPK_1: And Thomas.
SPK_1: And they basically say, no, Thomas has been given all your money away to the poor.
SPK_1: Well, the king gets really mad and by some version of the story has Thomas thrown in prison.
SPK_1: And and then in some versions of the story, the king like dies that night or sometimes it's like his brother that dies.
SPK_1: But basically, usually it's his brother dies and is and is sort of resurrected by St.
SPK_1: Thomas. But like while his his after his brother had died, he's he's being taken to the afterlife and being shot.
SPK_1: And that's the third time Thomas was ever shown in heaven, like all these great mansions.
SPK_1: And he looks over at one massive, really beautiful mansion, like this amazing, gorgeous palace with the columns and the throne and the roof and like all these things.
SPK_1: He says, man, whose place is that?
SPK_1: And, you know, whoever is guiding him to the afterlife says, well, that's your brother.
SPK_1: You know, that's that's for your brother that Thomas built that for him.
SPK_1: Right. And so then he kind of wakes up.
SPK_1: Sometimes the king has a dream.
SPK_1: Sometimes.
SPK_1: Sometimes his brother dies and is raised.
SPK_1: And anyway, the point is that this causes the king to like realize actually where his priorities are.
SPK_1: And he converts and he becomes a citizen of the heavenly kingdom.
SPK_1: This is just kind of one example.
SPK_1: The other interesting thing about Thomas is kind of just a recurring trope of the way that he's always late to things.
SPK_1: So famously in the story of the Dormition of the Mother of God, sometimes people call the Feast of the Assumption.
SPK_1: All of the apostles are brought by the Holy Spirit from the four corners of the world.
SPK_1: All the different places that they've been ministering.
SPK_1: And they're there at present at the repose of the Mother of God, except for St. Thomas, who's still in India.
SPK_1: And so after her burial, you know, as her soul is departing this life and ascending up into heaven,
SPK_1: St. Thomas shows up right then and he says, where are you going, O Holy One?
SPK_1: You know, like, you know, I just got here.
SPK_1: Where are you leaving?
SPK_1: And so famously in one story, that's when she bestows her girdle upon him as sort of like a parting gift so that he won't be like without consolation.
SPK_1: So there's a lot of interesting things going on with Thomas.
SPK_1: He's someday when I have some more time to think about it, I would like to kind of look at the missionary journeys and the kind of the symbolism of each of the apostles.
SPK_1: And the ways that different.
SPK_1: Early Christian communities tie themselves to one particular apostle, obviously, Antioch and Rome, both famously very attached to Saints Peter and Paul.
SPK_1: St. Andrew also, though, is one that really gets around, obviously, for Constantinople.
SPK_1: He's an important saint for the the Slavic peoples.
SPK_0: He's an important saint, but also do you know about the interesting because I just wanted to mention about St.
SPK_0: Andrew, according to Russian Orthodox tradition, especially, you know, like all the Orthodox tradition, obviously, it went up.
SPK_0: The Dnieper River.
SPK_0: And that's more or less people know.
SPK_0: That's why he went, let's say, to the modern Kiev area.
SPK_0: And that's where people mostly know the story today.
SPK_0: But actually, according to the old tradition, it came even way further north.
SPK_0: It came as far north as like the Balan Monasteries.
SPK_0: It's kind of it's it's very it's it's north.
SPK_0: Let me put it this way.
SPK_0: It's it's to the north of modern St.
SPK_0: Petersburg. So he went up until that point and founded this first, let's say, broader monastic communities.
SPK_0: And that's how.
SPK_0: Tradition goes.
SPK_0: So that's actually the community is way older.
SPK_0: And that's you mentioned that he is from the Scots.
SPK_0: It's also, in a way, apostle of the north in a way.
SPK_0: So the whole kind of the whole northern region, the north and also just places that are kind of on the extreme edge.
SPK_1: Like it's difficult to imagine being more on the edge of the world than somewhere like Valaam or Scotland.
SPK_1: Right. Yeah. Yeah.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_0: And and, you know, even nowadays, so this Andrew Cross, it's on a it's on a flag of Russian Navy, for example, even now and still kind of
SPK_0: keeps on with the part of this tradition.
SPK_0: So it's interesting how this original tradition is still in some state symbols even until now.
SPK_0: That's right.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: Same thing. I mean, obviously, St.
SPK_1: Andrew's Cross is the is the cross of the the Kingdom of Scotland.
SPK_1: And it's it's interesting.
SPK_1: So what I would like to do one day is to kind of like look at each of the apostles and kind of where they ministered and the way that these early communities kind of identified with them, tied themselves.
SPK_1: But then you have other places that
SPK_1: where the patronage of one of the apostles becomes really important a long time after I was so so I mean, just for instance, the importance of St.
SPK_1: Mark in Venice.
SPK_1: Right. Obviously, St.
SPK_1: Mark didn't die in Venice.
SPK_1: He died in Alexandria.
SPK_1: But at some point they brought his relics back to Venice and they're like, oh, St.
SPK_1: Mark, he's our patron now, along with all this other stuff we looted from Alexandria.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_0: But that's a very questionable story.
SPK_0: How he ended up in.
SPK_0: Yes, yes, yes, yes.
SPK_1: But I mean, also, like, I'll I'll just put it this way.
SPK_1: A lot of a lot of.
SPK_1: Relics ended up in Venice suspiciously.
SPK_1: But but yeah, I think that so to kind of tie that back into Pentecost, right, one of the the elements of the icon of Pentecost, right, that you'll see is I wish I had an icon of Pentecost in here.
SPK_1: I've got one somewhere else in the house, but in an icon of Pentecost, you'll very often see this sort of door that's got a black background.
SPK_1: And then there's a figure standing in the door.
SPK_1: And Jonathan has done a video about this a really long time ago.
SPK_1: It's like, I think one of his.
SPK_1: First videos that was really big.
SPK_1: But in in very old icons, like sometimes you have to see a dog headed figure in that door like the.
SPK_1: But then in in modern icons, usually it's sort of depicted as like an old man with a crown.
SPK_1: And then he's holding in his like a sort of a a towel or something or a tray sometimes.
SPK_1: And it's got all these scrolls on it.
SPK_1: Right. And then around this guy's.
SPK_1: His head will be the word cosmos, which is his name.
SPK_1: Right. So this is the this is like a anthropomorphic representation of the cosmos.
SPK_1: And the scrolls that he's holding are the are the words of the apostles.
SPK_1: In other words, the gospel.
SPK_1: Right. And this is you could say it's like a visual representation of their sound has gone out into all the earth and their sayings to the ends of the cosmos.
SPK_1: Right. Which is a line from the Psalms, which is originally about the stars and planets, but which the church.
SPK_1: Applies to the the apostles.
SPK_1: Actually, the New Testament also applies it to the apostles.
SPK_1: Right. Which is the church, obviously.
SPK_1: But but, you know, for instance, that's the if you go to church on one of the feasts of the holy apostles, that will be the procune on their sound has gone out into all the earth and their sayings to the ends of the cosmos.
SPK_1: Right. So anyway, that the point of point of all is to say that these these saints, saints like St.
SPK_1: Andrew and saints like St.
SPK_1: Thomas in particular.
SPK_1: Are very closely connected to all that, and again, I'm just very interested in this idea is Thomas is sort of being the twin of Christ, but then also like, you know, sold into slavery by him, you know, for this missionary work.
SPK_1: And it's I mean, if you think about that, you can take this sort of the Gnostic associations out of it and say the focus is on the way that Christ, who is the king, makes himself a slave to the nations.
SPK_1: Right. And you can and this is even tied into the way that the Christian faith manifests, you know, to kind of loop back around to talking about to talk about all this has to do with like nationhood and all these different things, the way the Christian faith manifests in different times and places so that there can be such a thing as Russian orthodoxy or or, you know, even.
SPK_0: Antiochian orthodoxy, Syrian orthodoxy.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: An example we really like to.
SPK_1: Use here in the States is the the way that the orthodox faith was brought to the Aleutian Islanders in Alaska and because they weren't they weren't forced into the faith.
SPK_1: And actually, many of them came to the faith, despite the fact that so many Russians were taking advantage of them.
SPK_1: Right. You know, like this, like the fur traders and and so on, like, you know, people treating them really, really poorly.
SPK_1: And of course, that is why the you know, that's why St. Herman and the other missionaries, that's why they came to look after these people.
SPK_1: And it was.
SPK_1: The the testimony of holiness that these men had, especially St.
SPK_1: Herman, living among them and and, you know, them being able to see that this is a holy person.
SPK_1: Right. And so they came into the faith.
SPK_1: They weren't forced into it, but they came into it in this organic way and in this way that allowed them to preserve their sort of distinct cultural identities while also being orthodox and also bringing in Russian things.
SPK_1: Right. Because that's the way the faith came to them.
SPK_1: And, you know, this is an ongoing conversation that we seem to be.
SPK_1: Constantly having in the Orthodox Church in North America, where there are people, especially who are converts, converts from evangelicalism or from some other Western form of Christianity.
SPK_1: And there's sometimes a lot of anxiety.
SPK_1: There's a lot of anxiety about like, OK, well, when are we going to get like a real American orthodoxy?
SPK_1: It always comes down to it always comes down to tangible things like music, which I'm sympathetic to.
SPK_1: Like, I like the idea that, you know.
SPK_1: We should know we should eventually sort of figure out, like, what is you know, how how do we do like orthodox chant that's also American or something?
SPK_1: And and there have been some neat some neat efforts made in this direction, which I which I like.
SPK_1: There was a really beautiful one that somebody did for Holy Week this year, and it was kind of an Appalachian style chant, which is actually historically is tied very closely to like old Celtic, like still Christian, but like really old Celtic.
SPK_1: And so in that sense, you know, there is a connection that goes all the way back to the roots of of the Christian faith in the West and even before the racism and everything else.
SPK_1: And so and so a lot of people are like, oh, this is really great.
SPK_1: I think this is so beautiful.
SPK_1: This is the music of my people, et cetera, et cetera.
SPK_1: And then, of course, there were a lot of people who are like, oh, this is no good.
SPK_1: This is garbage because it's not it's not the received tradition.
SPK_1: Like you should be using Russian music, not this stuff, or you should be using Byzantine tones, not this.
SPK_1: But, you know, at some point, the Russian music was also new stuff and controversial.
SPK_1: And and there's a process.
SPK_1: What I would say to people who are worried about this sort of thing is that you just have to give it some time.
SPK_1: Like if we're going to be Orthodox, then we need to also function with an Orthodox scope of time where decisions sometimes take, you know, decades or even centuries to be made.
SPK_1: And problems take a long time to resolve.
SPK_1: And it's better this way.
SPK_1: It's better this way.
SPK_0: Well, I just want to build up upon it because I think you actually managed to touch one of the key problem, not of just not problem, but pattern of not just orthodoxy, but also in Christianity as such.
SPK_0: And it's kind of where actually the distinguishment between Christianity and Gnosticism comes in a huge play.
SPK_0: In the Acts, there is this very famous line when the disciples asks the Lord, like, will thou at this time?
SPK_0: Restore again the kingdom to Israel.
SPK_0: And he said unto them, it's not for you to know the times or the seasons.
SPK_0: And I think that's actually one of the key, if you want, temptations we like humans have after Christ, because it didn't really exist before Christ, because before Christ was clearly more or less.
SPK_0: It sucks.
SPK_0: You go to the Hades or if you're a superhero, maybe you kind of go into like Elysium, but it's very small portion.
SPK_0: But for most, it's just Hades.
SPK_0: After Christ, it's clear that, let's say, eschatology, basically eschatology comes into the life of everyone effectively, willingly or not.
SPK_0: It doesn't matter whether you're Christian or not Christian.
SPK_0: But eschatological thinking is becoming a paradigm of thinking, generally speaking.
SPK_0: But the Christian answer is very counterintuitive to anybody.
SPK_0: It's like, yes, it is eschatology.
SPK_0: And even more like in the Revelation, we know very well how the eschatology is going to play out.
SPK_0: But.
SPK_0: The exact times and seasons are not for you to know.
SPK_0: You need to let it kind of develop upon you, like through you, but not for you to know.
SPK_0: And that's actually is this anxiety is incredibly hard for within tradition and outside of the tradition.
SPK_0: We know multiple examples of basically reforms and we don't want to go too deep.
SPK_0: And we can go into it.
SPK_0: It's very interesting.
SPK_0: We know that everybody knows the Reformation.
SPK_0: The Reformation is the big Reformation of Martin Luther, et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.
SPK_0: But in a way, the first great Reformation happened within the Catholic Church, with the great popes of the 10th of the 11th century, with Thomas Aquinas being kind of the biggest fruit of this reforms.
SPK_0: But for like for three centuries, the great popes were trying to improve, like to improve the church around them, to reform.
SPK_0: Whereas and it achieved many great results.
SPK_0: But then again, in three centuries, people became anxious again.
SPK_0: OK.
SPK_0: There have been three centuries of great reforms.
SPK_0: And yes, there are certain, let's say, successes.
SPK_0: But then also like we see people are still not, you know, in this ideal, perfect, holy condition, which we're expecting them to become after these reforms.
SPK_0: And the next cycle of anxiety comes into play.
SPK_0: And anxiety creates two ultimate ways out.
SPK_0: Like you can argue that there are only two types of principal reactions out of anxiety outside of, let's say, it's either to double down.
SPK_0: And here we see Luther, Reformation.
SPK_0: So go.
SPK_0: Go really, really deep.
SPK_0: Or the second hand is humanism, which is also like, let's just focus on the secular time.
SPK_0: OK, we can't know anything about Revelation.
SPK_0: Like it's kind of somewhere, something here, but we can't really know.
SPK_0: So if we can't have it here and now, let's just put it aside, put it into bracket and focus on what we can control.
SPK_0: And that's kind of the two options you have when you can't incorporate this waiting.
SPK_0: But again, it's not a passive waiting.
SPK_0: And that's what I think is very cool in your example.
SPK_0: The Christian waiting.
SPK_0: This is the one which is, at least we are called to do, orthodox waiting is a metamorphic, like it's a metamorphic, so it's the waiting, which is transforming you.
SPK_0: And that's kind of actually counterintuitive.
SPK_0: It was never super intuitive, I would say, as a mainstream thought process.
SPK_0: But it's even less counterintuitive for us nowadays when we want.
SPK_0: OK, so that's my goal.
SPK_0: That's my KPI.
SPK_0: That's how I achieve it.
SPK_0: How to I can attack.
SPK_0: You can't put you can't basically transform it into technology, and that's a big challenge for our like time that there's there's a this is actually what I've been thinking about all week.
SPK_1: So I'm really glad that you mentioned reforms because there's something about the action of reform that always results in the sort of like the gathering of power, right?
SPK_1: Actually, Babel is a good example of this.
SPK_1: Like you.
SPK_1: People, you should think about Babel as a reform, like it's a reform movement, because what happens is humanity is scattered because of the flood, you know, or like where humanity is destroyed because of the flood.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: But in other words, the world is the world experiences chaos, right?
SPK_1: This is this is chaos.
SPK_1: And the thing that we want to avoid is being subject to chaos.
SPK_1: If you want to go back to Hobbes, right, this is what Hobbes says is that there's no supreme good, but there is a supreme evil and the supreme evil is the fear of violent death.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: And so, well, if we can't achieve the supreme good others, we can't be saints, then we may as well try to make a stable political order.
SPK_1: And as defined by a place where everybody is is safe.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: And this is more or less this is what our society is accepted today.
SPK_1: So Babel, they say, let's let's let's reform things or let's reform things and rebuild the world.
SPK_1: Well, how are we going to rebuild the world?
SPK_1: Let's make a tower and a city.
SPK_1: What's the tower going to do?
SPK_1: It's going to protect us.
SPK_1: But it's also going to it's like you could say building an artificial mountain.
SPK_1: So when the floodwaters rise, in other words, when we experience chaos again, we'll all be safe and we'll be we can build a wall that will keep that out.
SPK_1: Go ahead.
SPK_0: I just want to add again, there is this very important detail in the tower and so tower.
SPK_0: And sorry for the sound.
SPK_0: Obviously, that's when you need to happen.
SPK_0: But what they started to do before building towers, actually starting to making bricks.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: And you can argue that it is effective.
SPK_0: Symbol of any technological process, because people think bricks are intuitive sink nowadays.
SPK_0: But if you ever been to Middle East learning to make bricks, it's a gigantic technological step forward.
SPK_0: Like, and the fact that they kind of making more or less what we use nowadays for roads, types of substance.
SPK_0: So it's not just like, so they're collecting this power and they're collecting the power of material change over the world that's happening in a parallel.
SPK_0: So it's not just the yeah.
SPK_1: And there's an interesting detail.
SPK_1: In the book of Jubilees, that says that where they get the stuff like the bitumen that they're going to use for the mortar is that they're getting it from the sea.
SPK_1: So, and the sea, the sea is, you know, obviously the story, the sea is chaos, right?
SPK_1: So the idea is not just that we're developing technology, but it's like, we're going to take chaos and we're going to use it to build a wall and a tower and to keep chaos out.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: And so that's the, that's the, and, and so that's the reforming impulse.
SPK_1: If you want to talk about Western Europe.
SPK_0: It's taking the energy of stasis and transforming it.
SPK_0: Sorry, go on.
SPK_1: So there was, there's this long period of actually waves of reforms that begin, as you said, in about the 10th century.
SPK_1: And then, you know, culminate obviously in the Protestant Reformation.
SPK_1: Actually, it's not even really correct, I think, to talk about one Protestant Reformation because it was really a gathering of different movements.
SPK_1: Some of them quite opposed to each other.
SPK_1: And so in the, so it begins in the.
SPK_1: The early 10th century, there's something around the year 910, there's something called the Cluniac reforms.
SPK_1: I don't know if people are aware of this, but it's really actually quite important to understanding how the papacy emerges like it does over the 10th and the 11th century.
SPK_1: And because basically the Cluniac reforms, which is the reforms within the Benedictine monasteries all across Western Europe, what basically happens is they say, oh, well, look, all of the normal clergy.
SPK_1: I'm going to simplify a little bit.
SPK_1: But all the normal clergy.
SPK_1: And the normal bishops and everything.
SPK_1: They're just, they're super corrupt.
SPK_1: And what we need is holiness.
SPK_1: So we're going to do an end run around that.
SPK_1: So like instead of like sort of fixing what's going on with the bishops where you have situations like where you have bishops and those bishops have sons, maybe illegitimate sons.
SPK_1: But they're nonetheless, they're like passing on the bishopric to their sons or to their nephews or whatever else.
SPK_1: And so basically what happens with the Cluniac reforms is that they establish a monastery.
SPK_1: A network of monasteries across Western Europe, which is not accountable to the local bishop, but is instead like this very powerful network that's under basically under an ordinary, like under somebody who's in charge of the whole network of monasteries, who's not a local bishop.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: And this allows them to get around the corrupt local structure.
SPK_1: So it's building a tower.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: It allows them to get around the corrupt local structure.
SPK_1: The idea is now we're organized and we can be holy.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: But what happens as soon as you organize a big network like this?
SPK_1: You start gathering power to yourself and that usually power in the form of wealth and power in the forms of, you know, in these other forms as well.
SPK_0: And that changes very importantly is the understanding of monastic life, which adds up like so.
SPK_0: It's not about metamorphosing yourself, but it's about fulfilling a particular task.
SPK_0: Many monastic orders are becoming like I like to actually use this metaphor like in my some classes.
SPK_0: That's a kind of, you know, this space Marines of church, like for people who are like, so it's a battle brothers who just, you know, go into.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: So they've kind of in a way becoming this.
SPK_0: For example, we have a specific task.
SPK_0: For example, we have a problem of education.
SPK_0: Let's have benefits.
SPK_0: We have a problem with Protestants.
SPK_0: Let's set up Jesuits.
SPK_0: But you have a task and for this task, you create effectively an arm of a state institution.
SPK_0: So it is.
SPK_0: And it's giving you a lot of power.
SPK_0: And amazing examples of work.
SPK_1: This is a sort of a weird aspect of Western Christianity to me.
SPK_1: And I like to me, it's the thing that the development of all these different orders and confraternities in Western Christianity in the Middle Ages sort of like foreshadows the way that Protestantism will split into all these different denominations where you're focused on like one particular thing.
SPK_1: And so now you just sort of split off and you become your own church.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: And there was something like this already happening in the Middle Ages.
SPK_1: Starting with that.
SPK_1: Starting with these waves of reforms.
SPK_1: But eventually, you know, eventually you have somebody like Francis of Assisi or, you know, people come along and they found the Franciscan order, the Dominican order, the discount Carmelite order, the, you know, all these orders get founded.
SPK_1: And then we say, oh, no, we need we is not pure enough.
SPK_1: So we need to split off now and found the Carthusians.
SPK_1: And, you know, it goes on and on like this.
SPK_1: And every time that they did this, what they what would end up happening.
SPK_1: So it's a weird thing.
SPK_1: If you read the history of there's a book, actually, that people might be interested in.
SPK_1: Hold on.
SPK_1: I've just been I've just been reading it this week.
SPK_1: So this is why this is on my mind.
SPK_1: Wonderful.
SPK_1: It doesn't start quite this early, but it's it starts in about the 14th century.
SPK_1: It's just called Reformations.
SPK_1: It's by a guy named Carlos M.
SPK_1: and Erie.
SPK_1: E. I. R. E. Carlos Erie.
SPK_1: And.
SPK_1: But he one of the one of the interesting things that keeps happening because he's talking about the sort of the Protestant Reformation and the like the early sort of proto Protestant reformers.
SPK_1: But also in tandem, he's talking about all the reformations that are happening inside the Roman Catholic Church at the same time.
SPK_1: And one of the weird things that happens is the way that anybody who's a reformer ends up becoming like a like really draconian authority, you know, totalitarian kind of dictator within their group.
SPK_1: Once they reform it.
SPK_1: And he says so.
SPK_1: So.
SPK_1: So he'll give an example of, yeah, there was this this group of monasteries and there was this one person that tried really hard to reform them.
SPK_1: And as a result, this group of and and and and, you know, I don't know what the confessional, you know, commitments of the author, if any, are.
SPK_1: I don't I don't know anything.
SPK_1: But but he'll talk about it as like, oh, it's really bad that the Catholic Church had all this wealth and power.
SPK_1: And then.
SPK_1: And so this group came along and they said, we want to get rid of it.
SPK_1: We want to get rid of all the wealth and power.
SPK_1: So they organize and they build the tower.
SPK_1: And then suddenly and then he says, and because of this, they gained all this wealth and power and influence kind of talking like, isn't that great?
SPK_1: But the the problem is that this creates this the cycle of constantly trying to rebuild the tower constantly.
SPK_1: This sort of like you build you try to to to construct something that's orderly.
SPK_1: And then as you amass wealth and power to yourself, you get scattered.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: And so eventually the organization breaks down.
SPK_1: The Protestant Reformation itself is a good example of this.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: Where it starts out as a single movement.
SPK_1: We're trying to get away from the Catholic Church.
SPK_1: We're trying to purify things back to what they thought.
SPK_1: And I believe genuinely at some point thought that this was more biblical.
SPK_1: Now, I don't believe it was.
SPK_1: Obviously, I used to be Protestant.
SPK_1: I'm not anymore.
SPK_0: But but no, but there are motivations in the beginning.
SPK_0: Like, it's pretty clear if you read like and if you read Martin Luther, that's also very important that he was a guy who effectively tried.
SPK_0: The way.
SPK_0: So he tried as good as he can to follow, let's say, the instruction to holiness offered to him.
SPK_0: And he was genuinely terrified, disappointed, et cetera, et cetera.
SPK_0: So it's not like he just woke up with this wonderful way.
SPK_1: I mean, there's Luther's an interesting example because I like he's he's actually this whole babble pattern on a micro scale because he tries to, like, build the tower just in his own life.
SPK_1: He's like, OK, I'm going to be a holy person.
SPK_1: I mean, they're rid of all my sin.
SPK_1: You know.
SPK_1: So by his own account, Luther was going to confession multiple times a day.
SPK_1: Now, you sort of like imagine like your father confessor, your parish priest or whatever, like if you're going to him, you're like three or four times a day for confession.
SPK_1: Eventually, he's going to tell you you need medical help.
SPK_1: You know, like and I there's a you know, I and I I've always kind of suspected, you know, nowadays we'd probably look at Luther and say maybe he he had like bipolar disorder or something like this.
SPK_1: But the point is, like, he really suffered from scrupulosity.
SPK_1: So he tried to build the tower.
SPK_1: And then his life fell apart.
SPK_1: He experiences the scattering.
SPK_1: And then he says, oh, it's the church's fault.
SPK_1: I've got to reform the church.
SPK_1: And so he starts to build the tower again.
SPK_1: And then with the Protestant Reformation kicks off again, like almost immediately, there's a scattering.
SPK_1: There's a Tower of Babel moment where almost immediately we go from fighting the pope and fighting the Roman Catholic Church to fighting each other.
SPK_1: As all these different Reformation leaders sort of split off and you've got Luther's doing one thing and Calvin's doing another thing.
SPK_1: And Zwingli's doing another thing.
SPK_1: And they can't agree on the Eucharist and they can't agree on actually what books should be in the Bible.
SPK_1: They can't agree on the most fundamental things in the Catholic faith.
SPK_1: And then another generation and you have like the Anabaptists coming along and they're they're changing the definition of marriage and they're changing all these different things.
SPK_1: And and it's this real scattering, this real scattering that sort of happens that is very much, I think, that sort of shape of the Tower of Babel.
SPK_1: And one of the interesting things is that that I think sort of comes about.
SPK_1: And this isn't this wasn't Luther and Calvin's generation.
SPK_1: But this this comes along sort of later is this idea.
SPK_1: Well, I guess we all we tried to make everybody a saint.
SPK_1: I mean, this is the.
SPK_1: The project of Calvin's Geneva or some of the the the Calvinist cities, the reform cities in the Netherlands.
SPK_1: Right. Where the idea is we're going to force everyone to live in a certain way so that they can become a saint.
SPK_1: So then it's like instead of reforming a monastery where at least people are here, more or less involved.
SPK_1: More or less voluntarily. Right.
SPK_1: And they've all agreed on a certain rule of life and everything else.
SPK_1: Well, with Bill, when Calvin started building Geneva, you know, like trying to make it this like the perfect Christian city.
SPK_1: Right. You know, it got to the point where by one account there were people whose job it was to, like, check and see how many spoons you owned.
SPK_1: Right. Like like in other words, like how much silverware do you have?
SPK_1: Like back back when silverware was actually silver. Right.
SPK_1: So check and see, like, how many spoons, how many forks, how many knives to make sure that you weren't.
SPK_1: Like accumulating wealth to yourself that would put you over somebody else in the community.
SPK_1: Right. So it gets to be like a little draconian.
SPK_1: And now the now those places are the most secular places in the world.
SPK_0: And it actually makes total sense.
SPK_0: Sorry again for suffering the sound, but I think it's coming.
SPK_0: She's connected to groups and one important element, important element.
SPK_0: As I write in the article, I sent you.
SPK_0: He had a very particular understanding of what a human is.
SPK_0: And that's actually I think kind of connected altogether.
SPK_0: He calls it a person. And in English, you know, a person is just normal word.
SPK_0: We use it every day. But it's actually coming from Greek prosopon, the mask.
SPK_0: And we can argue that it's the mask, which is the social like and we all wear the mask.
SPK_0: You can say that you wear the mask when you work for your boss.
SPK_0: When you are in a way, you're talking to me like it's different social roles and actors.
SPK_0: But we are groups was crucial. And that's what I think is the point.
SPK_0: He kind of narrowed down for the whole of human.
SPK_0: The whole of an individual to this mask.
SPK_0: And then it becomes clear if all we are is a mask.
SPK_0: And that's actually very contingent with this whole legal way of thinking about life.
SPK_0: Let's say jurisprudential like so like.
SPK_0: And if we understand, for example, the confession in a legal way, that's also like, let's say, my mask is confessing.
SPK_0: Let's say I broke the law. I need to contest it.
SPK_0: Then it naturally is that you want to make it hard.
SPK_0: Like, obviously, like, then you want all the masks to be good because because how else could it be?
SPK_0: Because then if one of your masks, it changes the purity of the whole structure.
SPK_0: Whereas if you consider more, let's say, and where it's definitely orthodox tradition, orthodox understanding.
SPK_0: But I would argue Christian general tradition, which we are called to.
SPK_0: We argue that no mask is enough to describe person.
SPK_0: There is this mystery of inner life.
SPK_0: And this mystery can, in principle, not be touched by any structure.
SPK_0: By any reform, by any like external forces.
SPK_0: It can be only to be transformed through Christ and through within.
SPK_0: Like, but it's always this organic process of waiting.
SPK_0: And there is no deadline. Like, it's not a timetable.
SPK_0: Like the salvation train doesn't come on a schedule.
SPK_0: If you want, like effectively, effectively as a metaphor.
SPK_0: But then it definitely changes almost expectations.
SPK_0: Then you can leave the room for impurity in a social structure, in a social system.
SPK_0: You don't have to.
SPK_0: You don't have to ultimately to build a tower.
SPK_0: Because there is no, basically, you personally won't be late, let's say, to be saved in a way.
SPK_0: So you can leave time for it.
SPK_0: Do you see what I mean?
SPK_0: I think it actually comes to the core understanding of our whole.
SPK_0: What do we mean to be a person?
SPK_0: What is it?
SPK_0: Is it just the sum of our social relations?
SPK_0: Or is it something which can never be put even into, on a scale, except by, let's say, the heart.
SPK_0: The Orthodox tradition calls about is the heart.
SPK_0: Nobody knows the depths of the heart.
SPK_0: What is the heart?
SPK_1: I mean, all of this, I was actually thinking this even before you said this.
SPK_1: So again, we're tracking.
SPK_1: We're on the right path here.
SPK_1: I think all of this for me really sort of highlights the importance in our tradition of St.
SPK_1: Gregory of Palamas and his life and the writings that he left.
SPK_1: But even his homilies, like even his homilies directed at lay people.
SPK_1: For people who aren't aware.
SPK_1: St.
SPK_1: Gregory essentially defended the Orthodox faith against humanism.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: So you've got Barlaam, who's he is a monk.
SPK_1: He's an Orthodox monk, but he's a very sort of worldly or like very humanistic monk.
SPK_1: He's steeped in Greek philosophy and kind of secular learning and everything.
SPK_1: And he goes to Mount Athos.
SPK_1: And here's all these Orthodox monks.
SPK_1: They're praying the Jesus prayer.
SPK_1: And they don't have any of the education that Barlaam has.
SPK_1: And he basically, I mean, he calls them navel gazers.
SPK_1: That's literally, that's the epithet that he uses for them and basically says, this is a huge waste of time.
SPK_1: What you should be focusing on is education.
SPK_1: And it's basically the statement, right, that I was mentioning a moment ago.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: The kind of the idea of, I don't want to paint with too broad of a brush, but let's say like just like the worst, the worst examples of humanism.
SPK_1: And, you know, to go back to Hobbes as a friend.
SPK_1: For instance, right.
SPK_1: To say that, well, you can't ever be like totally holy in this life.
SPK_1: So you may as well not try.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: You may as well instead like focus on just like making human life as good as human life can be.
SPK_1: And so the idea that St. Gregory is defending against Barlaam, among other things.
SPK_1: And again, this is very complicated stuff.
SPK_1: A lot of technical reading if you want to get into this.
SPK_1: But what he's really defending actually is, first of all.
SPK_1: What you just said about the hiddenness of the heart and that that is true both for us, but it's also true for God.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: And God, you're not going to find God through through, you know, philosophical training or human learning.
SPK_1: And it's not to say that a lot of people haven't.
SPK_1: What I mean by this is to say is that, you know, if you if you read a bunch of books and you do a lot of philosophical training.
SPK_1: And then some.
SPK_1: And then one day you sort of wake up.
SPK_1: And you realize, oh, the thing I've been actually looking forward for this entire time has been God and to know God and to have a relationship with him.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: Well, he's revealed himself to you.
SPK_1: Now, he might have used all of these other things, but these things didn't reveal God to you.
SPK_1: God revealed God to you.
SPK_1: And this is the only way.
SPK_1: And so God's heart.
SPK_1: God's heart.
SPK_1: His essence.
SPK_1: I mean, this whole idea.
SPK_1: His essence is unknowable.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: But also the essence of each.
SPK_1: You know.
SPK_1: But our essence is unknowable.
SPK_1: Like the the human heart, like who we are and what we are is is unknowable.
SPK_1: But I know you through the relationship that I have.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: But also, I have to understand that there's always a little bit of a gap there between them.
SPK_1: The more perfectly we work, we we live into that relationship, the more perfectly we live into that relationship, the more the better.
SPK_1: I know you.
SPK_1: But with God, he has the capacity, let's say, to reveal himself, to reveal himself.
SPK_1: And, you know, this is through through his divine energies.
SPK_1: But to reveal himself, you know, sort of directly to the human heart in this in this actually in an unmediated way.
SPK_1: Because this is the this is the crux of the argument is that the energies of God are not media media.
SPK_1: They're not immediate.
SPK_1: They are God himself.
SPK_1: That's what I'm trying to say.
SPK_1: So the question becomes a sort of a question about the no ability.
SPK_0: Sorry.
SPK_0: I noticed.
SPK_0: And that's exactly the solves the problem which we're talking about.
SPK_0: It's a problem of anxiety.
SPK_0: Because that's another metaphor.
SPK_0: Basically what St.
SPK_0: Paul, I guess it's like you can no God, not as an abstract concept.
SPK_0: But effectively, you can feel like you think he uses as a metaphor of a sun and one day and energy effectively is the warmth of the sun.
SPK_0: So you can actually stand in this sun and feel it like but not just centrally feel the technical terms.
SPK_0: How exactly does this feeling happens?
SPK_0: Yeah, but and we can argue.
SPK_0: So what?
SPK_0: Why does it matter?
SPK_0: But that's kind of the crux of the argument of the whole medieval time.
SPK_0: It was a principle question.
SPK_0: Because, for example, alternatively.
SPK_0: You have people falling into despair.
SPK_0: If you read Petrarca of the same time, he is in despair because whatever I do, I'm not good enough to know God.
SPK_0: And what's the point?
SPK_0: Like, and that's a very real issue.
SPK_0: And you can if not for nowadays, you can say perfection.
SPK_0: Like, whatever we do, we're never good enough for this perfect image, whatever we put into our head.
SPK_0: So what do we do?
SPK_0: How can we live with this anxiety?
SPK_0: So it is a very it's the same problem.
SPK_0: It's the same pattern developing in different areas.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: It matters because and this is how it ties back to bevel.
SPK_1: And this is how it ties back to everything we've talked about last time in this time.
SPK_1: It matters because the question is like, what's the telos of the human being?
SPK_1: Like, what's the thing that you're made for as a human being?
SPK_1: And what St.
SPK_1: Gregory says and what St.
SPK_1: Paul says and what the church has always sort of maintained is that the thing you're made for is union with God.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: To not just know things about God, but to really know God.
SPK_1: Basically, what basically what Barlaam was arguing for is this idea that you can only ever know about God.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: So pursue philosophical learning, pursue education, pursue theological learning.
SPK_1: That's all fine.
SPK_1: But don't think that you, you know, because you're sitting on a mountain in a monastery sitting with Jesus prayer and you're seeing, you know, the uncreated light and all those things.
SPK_1: Don't think you have more of experience of God than I do.
SPK_1: You know, that kind of a thing.
SPK_1: But then like the.
SPK_1: I mean, Barlaam is the one who taught Petrarch Greek.
SPK_1: Like these these guys are really connected.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: And this, you know, and so there's this kind of this kind of this idea that, well, once you abandon the idea that the thing your life is for is actually to know God, then what you're all you're really left with.
SPK_1: There's no sumum bonum.
SPK_1: All you're really left with is to say, well, how can I just make human life as great as it can possibly be?
SPK_1: And reform is always.
SPK_1: You know, a really important part of that.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: And it's not to say there's not like a good way to go about reform.
SPK_1: Actually, one of my favorite examples of a reform controversy is are you I'm sure you're familiar with the possessor controversy in Russian Orthodox history.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: So it's basically it's basic.
SPK_1: What's that?
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: Sure.
SPK_0: And the Russian is called.
SPK_0: Like you said.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: Like the possessor.
SPK_1: Non-possessor controversy.
SPK_1: It's usually how it's it's translated in English.
SPK_1: And basically, it's a it's an argument between the successors of St.
SPK_1: Sergius of Radonj about or how do you say that word, by the way?
SPK_1: Is it Radonj?
SPK_1: Radonezh?
SPK_0: Radonezh.
SPK_0: Sergi Radonezhski.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_1: Radonezh.
SPK_1: Okay.
SPK_1: I hear people in English say it all kinds of ways.
SPK_1: And Russian is not a language that I know very well.
SPK_1: Although I think I found somebody to teach me finally.
SPK_1: So.
SPK_0: So maybe.
SPK_0: Nicholas.
SPK_1: No, no, no.
SPK_1: There's somebody here in my community here in Texas.
SPK_1: But I'm hoping so maybe someday.
SPK_1: No promises guys, but maybe someday we do these conversations in Russian.
SPK_1: That would be .
SPK_0: If you need any practice just let me know.
SPK_1: That would be great.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: So anyway.
SPK_1: So St. Sergius, his successors, you know, there's kind of an argument about, well,
SPK_1: should we build our monasteries in the cities so that we can look after the poor and do
SPK_1: all these things?
SPK_1: but also that means by the way you have to own property right you have to own property and which
SPK_1: means you have to have somebody administrate it and then you start building wealth and all the
SPK_1: problems that come with that or do we just do we live off in a wood in the woods somewhere and just
SPK_1: pray and the amazing thing about the orthodox church is that we canonized both of these guys
SPK_1: canonize them both and to me that's just always just kind of an amazing uh uh something that's
SPK_1: very hard for a western mind to grasp but something i've really come to appreciate in
SPK_1: the orthodox church is that the answer is is usually both and usually if you find yourself
SPK_1: in a kind of a uh either or place and this is this is the the problem with every reformer
SPK_1: in uh uh this is the problem with every reformer in western history is is that they're they're
SPK_1: usually people who could only see things one way right and they're because they
SPK_1: they're they're fixated like they can only see things in this one particular way so luther says
SPK_1: no it's got to be all grace why because i already tried and i failed so if i failed obviously
SPK_1: everybody has failed right so it could only be grace it's got to be all grace right so they can
SPK_1: only see things in one particular way and that's the that's the building the tower that's when you
SPK_0: get scattered it's this is very wonderful and you said that i just wanted to add like speaking
SPK_0: about reforms because in like russia
SPK_0: it has its own even in church example example of a pretty bad reform and it happened later
SPK_0: in seven yes yes yes and i would argue that's the wound which is kind of if you want to
SPK_0: understand russian history you need to understand the 17th century like and that's just it's
SPK_0: a topic for another conversation it's kind of how to do things the wrong way uh how to
SPK_0: do the things the right way though like in both of these guys uh both and just like
SPK_0: possessors not possessors because possessors kind of they were also building up on part
SPK_0: of a tradition which starts with moscow metropolites
SPK_0: for example the hola metropolit of alexia of moscow who is in fact you can argue the creator
SPK_0: of moscow state like in a way like not maybe from legal perspective but he played a huge role
SPK_0: but i would argue that the key difference for us to notice here and it's a very broad speaking
SPK_0: is the different principle the difference how would i distinguish between good reform and bad
SPK_0: reform good reform seeks only to effectively become a rock doesn't matter whether you're in a forest
SPK_0: or doesn't matter whether you're in a city
SPK_0: and then around this reform kind of certain radiating light is happening or some movement
SPK_0: is starting to happen and then the trans the metamorph like metamorphic transformation
SPK_0: of a place around this rock is happening whereas bad reform always tries to go to the
SPK_0: place to collect the place and to build the tower and that's exactly the difference the
SPK_0: problem is the second one pass is which much clearer you can build expectations you can
SPK_0: have program it's it's very very clear the first
SPK_0: reform
SPK_0: is way less tangible it's way less predictable it's way less uh yeah you can't put it into
SPK_0: timetables that's what makes it much much harder but the change is that within its past you keep
SPK_0: the core issue where the core phenomenon which i think the whole orthodoxing percent is based on
SPK_0: the problem of a subject it puts a subject as an individual not separated but as a precisely agent
SPK_0: you can even argue into the center and you leave it
SPK_0: it's freedom to turn to be transformed to be like you don't even have to tolerate that's another cool element which often likes another going into the wrong direction is what's okay so if this is all happens let's just not be clear about anything okay if any attempt to build something creates in a tower so let's not just build anything or let not be clear in anything but it's also a wrong way you can be clear and like let's say all the monks were very clear like what were all fathers were very clear maximum the confessor was so clear it was
SPK_0: he had a very difficult life because of because of his clarity but he didn't try let's say to go and start a revolution that's that's what that's the difference i mean so you can be as clear in your agency and experience you know being an acting subject but you're almost realistic about the extent you can invoke change in ourselves you leave it to them to invoke change in ourselves and and very importantly when this goes well
SPK_1: it goes well because there's a holy person at its center right who's who's holding things together who's who's become there's a phrase used about saint seraphim of sarov which i just really love that he was totally transparent to jesus christ right so if you have a holy person at center even if i mean and holy does not mean the same thing as polite you know there are famously some saints who who were uh maybe not people you'd want to have over for dinner you know but um but to have a holy person a person who's
SPK_1: totally transparent to jesus christ in the time and place where where god has put them in the way that they're supposed to be um then uh when a reform happens around them it sort of it carries the authority but it's the authority of christ it's the authority of holiness and it's not the authority of a top-down structure that somebody like rigidly you know um i mean uh to think of like another monastic reformer right saint basil the great who literally if you're
SPK_1: orthodox wrote the book on monasticism i mean literally the book right um saint basil the great
SPK_1: and and uh we've never had we don't have another kind of monasticism in the orthodox church like we
SPK_1: don't have orders we don't have you know any of those things just sort of like we just sort of
SPK_1: follow the pattern of life the rule of life that that uh saint basil and obviously others you know
SPK_1: the egyptian desert that inheritance as well but but the the but it the things that he wrote
SPK_1: right the and the legacy that he left continues to be with us today because of this sort of the
SPK_1: authority of his holy life and the the saint that he was the holy person that he was and obviously
SPK_1: somebody that got you know had uh an extraordinary you know a number of natural talents right a gift
SPK_1: for all these different things it uses those things for the kingdom of god but he's still
SPK_1: uh at the end of the day the most important thing about him is that he was a saint right he was a
SPK_1: saint and um and uh you know and then on you know sometimes
SPK_1: also you know they kill you first right you know or they exile you first you know another great
SPK_1: reformer saint john chrysostom you know uh was exiled died in exile you know before people
SPK_1: started you know really listening to him and taking him seriously sometimes and so anyway and
SPK_1: there are many other such cases but i i think this is the this is the other thing is that um
SPK_1: something that really seems to me i don't want to be uncharitable to people especially the dead
SPK_1: but something that really seems to me to characterize
SPK_1: many of the reformers just as i'm kind of reading back through uh you know this this book i'm reading
SPK_1: right now it's really the first time that i've read i mean i used to study and teach about the
SPK_1: reformation all the time as an evangelical this is really the first time i'm revisiting it after
SPK_1: many years of being orthodox and uh the um the uh thing that seems to really characterize
SPK_1: these men as opposed to the saints right is a really just a lack of humility right
SPK_1: um a lack of a willingness to sort of submit themselves to a higher authority right especially
SPK_1: you know when luther goes and he starts deciding which books are in the bible and aren't or
SPK_1: starts deciding like which parts of tradition do i keep or don't right he just sort of says well
SPK_1: i'm the one that decides right and um which is an effect like a temptation we all have because
SPK_0: that's like we really like i like this part of tradition i like this part of scripture
SPK_0: this one i don't really like so let's where is the
SPK_0: goal is and or and it's hard it's a very difficult labor we need to admit like because for every let's
SPK_0: say citation from a bible you have a different like opposite citation from a bible that's it
SPK_0: creates an enormous freedom of you to let's say pick up whatever you want and you can build very
SPK_0: different interpretations which can technically be reliable upon the same scripture and but the
SPK_0: job is to integrate everything to accept it as a like wholesomely and that's a hard job to do and
SPK_0: like so i just again so you said you wanted to be charitable to these people so i think yeah
SPK_1: we look in the mirror we can see the same in us well i mean this is the thing i'm not i'm not saying
SPK_1: that i'm a humble person i mean this is part of like i'm i'm i'm you know uh you know so for i
SPK_1: mean people who don't know i was a i was a protestant minister before we came to the orthodox
SPK_1: church and one of the things that you know when we left everybody asked us so are you going to
SPK_1: start your own church like this is what you do in the world that i came from if you're not happy with
SPK_1: things
SPK_1: at your current church you're supposed to leave and start a new one right and this is just what
SPK_1: you do and so everybody assumed they asked us oh well let us know when you start your new church
SPK_1: and things like this i was like no i'm never starting any churches ever again like i'm just
SPK_1: you know i've got to go somewhere that's been there that's older than me right i i i uh uh
SPK_1: you know i i know too much about myself to want to be a part of any church that i start you know
SPK_1: and and um yeah and so that's the that's the thing like
SPK_1: it is just um uh we have to have humility we have to be patient um and i think it's really also
SPK_1: really important to kind of to kind of just be able to kind of see yourself with some distance
SPK_1: and and perspective the the thing that ties together humanism and all the big reform movements
SPK_1: of the 15th and 16th centuries and all that stuff is is a uh is a is a shortening of perspective
SPK_1: right where people are you know i've got i've got the answer now boy wait till you guys hear
SPK_1: i've got the solution for this problem and you know there's something like especially as americans
SPK_1: there's something daring about that that appeals to us because yeah i mean because you're the new
SPK_0: world and you're above history ultimately like history doesn't matter like it's it's for this
SPK_0: european freaks we are beyond the laws of history and this is why we don't understand why i mean
SPK_1: this is why americans don't understand why people in europe can't get their crap together like come
SPK_1: on guys we've already solved all of the world's problems look how great we have it you know why
SPK_0: let's just get on board with the program but the same pattern if you notice like you say about this
SPK_0: whole uh leave it start your own church the same if you notice the pattern of state creation exactly
SPK_0: the same pattern yeah i don't like this state okay let's move to the free land and build my
SPK_0: own state like it is it is i agree like for american if you can under it is an effect now
SPK_0: in american tradition or american pattern it has this huge element of here and now uh then but you
SPK_0: absolutely right that is about i just wanted to notice that where the trick happens after you
SPK_0: it's all religious religious mumble jumble so what your religious people talking about but after
SPK_0: the god let's say with secularism for many people was put behind this equation the very same pattern
SPK_0: is now playing with the state we expect now just not the church to create the heaven on earth but
SPK_0: the state to create on heaven and earth and ideally within the next five years like ideally
SPK_0: with these guys who win the election we want him to create literally heaven on earth within the
SPK_0: next four years if he doesn't he's not good enough maybe four years is too much ideally
SPK_1: the next night and and it's one of the things that i mean this is why i kind of got really
SPK_1: tired with american politics i grew up in a very like politically active family worked on different
SPK_1: campaigns and things like that when i was young and and but just like i at some point i realized
SPK_1: like the cycle is impossible there is no way that you can affect meaningful change in a country of
SPK_1: 300 million people 300 million people like the romans couldn't do it and they had like a tenth
SPK_1: generation like there's no way that you can you can affect meaningful change in a country of 300
SPK_1: million people in four in a four-year cycle like that's this complete nonsense you couldn't do it
SPK_1: in four generations uh and and but you cannot not expect but the whole pattern of expectation
SPK_0: is already so deeply ingrained that we don't realize where it's coming from but it kind of
SPK_0: almost rules over us that's i think one of the most fascinating pattern i just wanted them to
SPK_0: finish like as an opposite like uh do you know like uh
SPK_0: as a philosopher uh he's a really good russian like strongly russian philosopher of the 20th
SPK_0: century and has a quote which i really love uh which kind of distinguishes in my opinion the
SPK_0: diagnostic approach to the state and powers with uh like more skeptical and realistic which
SPK_0: here he says that the purpose of the statement is not to create a heaven on earth but just
SPK_0: let it not to dissolve in hell immediately
SPK_0: like yeah and i think
SPK_0: it is just this changing of an optic and changing of expectations it's also very to me characteristics
SPK_0: that people talk about freedom all the time and again this topic hopefully we'll have after you
SPK_0: will have like back in august or in september because i would want to continue it that uh
SPK_0: we're so we're so rooting for freedom but at the same time we expect
SPK_0: something external to give us this freedom and to create it on our behalf which is also kind
SPK_0: of almost a paradox like because if you realize that much into freedom and i agree with that
SPK_0: christians we are all very much into freedom just it's the freedom to transform yourself
SPK_0: and this freedom is specifically not from the state like no state no president no like can give you
SPK_0: this particular freedom and that is the freedom which you actually seek so it is very paradoxical
SPK_0: and like as you i know in jonathan's circle you call it the clown world and i think it's a
SPK_0: very accurate description how all of the ideas are intertwined to become to be almost a mockery
SPK_0: of what they used to be but still repeating the same pattern which is also very fascinating
SPK_0: okay so yeah i guess we are wrapping up so again thank you for amazing uh conversation again i'm
SPK_0: very grateful for your time i hope we both have more in the future i definitely do wanna i've got
SPK_1: a bunch of travel coming up but when i get back i would love to talk some more um and uh your
SPK_1: audience thanks to your audience you guys don't know how hard it has been to nail me down for
SPK_1: conversation paul's been very very patient so thanks to him and thanks to you all uh you're
SPK_1: very kind to have me on thank you very much
SPK_0: thank you okay guys and yeah subscribe to no actually richard doesn't have a channel so don't
SPK_1: subscribe to the channel he doesn't yeah yeah don't i i actually so i i have a youtube
SPK_1: channel that i don't post anything on i really studiously try to avoid having my own channel
SPK_1: because uh there's just too much i've got too many other things to do and i feel like if i had to
SPK_1: if i had to do what you do or like what jonathan does like jonathan has like you
SPK_1: know three videos a week or something i would just lose my mind like uh so i'm
SPK_1: I'm very happy just to have
SPK_1: cool friends.
SPK_0: I try to limit
SPK_0: to one a week.
SPK_0: Three is too much, but
SPK_0: I know you're working on several
SPK_0: really cool projects, so
SPK_0: once you put them into
SPK_0: process, I will also post links to them
SPK_0: later.
SPK_1: We can talk about those
SPK_1: as well. Everything that I'm doing right now
SPK_1: is pretty much going to be coming
SPK_1: out through Symbolic World Press. I still have
SPK_1: a couple of projects that I'm doing with Ancient Faith,
SPK_1: but most of the
SPK_1: projects that I'll be doing in the future will be through
SPK_1: Symbolic World Press, so people can
SPK_1: go watch there for all that, and
SPK_1: then come and find me in places
SPK_1: like this.
SPK_0: Okay, then, thanks again,
SPK_0: and Christos Voskreisik.
SPK_1: Voicenos Voskreisik.