SPK_1: paradox that the dead were the dead are and the dead will be and we're living it all in one moment
SPK_0: in that toast yes and and you will live you will die but if somebody will raise a toast for you
SPK_1: and if they don't you will live this is actually a part of the toast often not all time but i'll
SPK_1: say it but they say we member again yes those who have died now so that our children will
SPK_1: member us again and so we don't die a second death and that is a that is that is that is it
SPK_1: i find a lot of people when they say who's your god i'm not talking i'm talking about good people
SPK_1: this isn't atheism isn't about people being good or bad it's about itself as its own philosophy
SPK_1: being bad yep it's just wrong or let's say it this way not in alignment with the design of
SPK_1: the universe how about that i like that but
SPK_1: you
SPK_1: what i find is is my dearest friends who are in these marriages they cannibalize each other
SPK_1: right and what happens is then they stay in the marriage for the child and it is wild to watch
SPK_1: because they have no way out of the marriage because the only way out is that you attend to
SPK_1: the third and i attend to the third and every now and then i'll look at you too every now and then
SPK_1: i'll come to you to say right to be in union but it's only so that we can go there so have you
SPK_0: noticed that
SPK_0: like basically it's a pair like so uh i believe in one god the father almighty and one lord so
SPK_0: jesus christ the son of god so prayer of god and lord and this pair of god and lord for us is very
SPK_0: not self-evident we just say it like even sorry um we don't really deeply think what it means and
SPK_0: it's good we don't always need to deeply think just saying but for the same the context where
SPK_0: it was given it was very clear everybody had a god and everybody had a lord like
SPK_0: in a very practical meaning of this word slave and master relationship in a very practical way
SPK_0: meaning again was a very down to earth it was not abstract but again that's good sir so why it's
SPK_0: important in the creed to heaven and one lord jesus christ well it means actually any other
SPK_0: relationship of power any other relationship of worship any other than relationship of service
SPK_0: is against the face of this one and then it can work you know what is the trickiest part about
SPK_1: like why more than political system fantastic one lord yeah that's right
SPK_1: i i heard it theologically you know as the the one i mean obviously it has many meanings
SPK_1: i'm giving you one but i just never read it that way which is one master for all of us in all of
SPK_0: our endeavors wow one spirit around our table right and then this relationship of power at
SPK_0: least have a chance not to result in cannibalism that's right there is no guarantee i don't have
SPK_0: to fight you if we're i don't have to i can still do it because i'm a sinful creature but
SPK_0: at least i don't have to fight you because i'm a sinful creature but at least i don't have to fight you
SPK_0: because i'm a sinful creature but at least i don't have to fight you and that's important
SPK_1: distinguish that's that's i think that's why i'm still married because when we fight
SPK_1: it's resolved into one lord and i'm i'm not bragging about it because that's the last
SPK_1: thing it's it's messy you're married i know it's messy that one that's that evenly yoked idea but
SPK_1: and then i didn't read it that way that's helpful sorry no that's the thing so all i'm saying is it
SPK_0: is a logical necessity that's what i'm saying if you don't have one lord you're not going to
SPK_0: on on a level of reality the creed is just the most universal well the same way as any table is the
SPK_0: image of this universality so but on any level of reality if you don't have the one lord you will
SPK_0: end up cannibalizing you you will have to it's the trade and this is the tragedy i'm not saying
SPK_0: it's something good or something we need to be happy about or to feel even blamed for but we
SPK_0: need to i think it's good if we see it because we think like even i will tell you something
SPK_0: corporation we want to serve the people we want to serve the people we want to serve the people
SPK_0: we want to serve the people we want to serve people we're not saying we should treat them
SPK_0: you to do that is you can't substitute this one lord with fear that's what we most do like we have
SPK_0: lord just this not one lord but mostly the eyes is a lot of greed was a lot of fear but because
SPK_0: only true service and sorry any relationship of power implies the relationship of service so what
SPK_1: What you're saying is, is Amazon, can I make it funny?
SPK_1: I don't know if it's going to be funny.
SPK_1: Are you saying then that the one lord at Amazon is not that everybody agrees that it's so great to move products around the world?
SPK_1: That's the one lord.
SPK_1: I'm doing this so I can be the one who participates in the movement of products.
SPK_1: That's not the one lord.
SPK_1: It's fear that I can't pay my rent, so I'm going to drive this frigging truck around.
SPK_1: That's what's going on.
SPK_0: That's what's going on.
SPK_0: And that's why you don't have true service.
SPK_0: You have imitation of service, which is, yes, unfortunately, oppression.
SPK_0: What is oppression?
SPK_0: It's imitation of service without the spirit of service.
SPK_1: But can you have?
SPK_0: You can.
SPK_0: It's much harder.
SPK_0: I can tell you already what you would need to sacrifice.
SPK_1: Okay, I want to hear this.
SPK_0: You will need to sacrifice predictability.
SPK_0: You will need to sacrifice safety, a lot of safety.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: And you will most probably will need to sacrifice some speed in a modern way.
SPK_0: Oh, this holy grails of modern.
SPK_1: 100%.
SPK_1: 100% on the speed and wealth, efficiency and wealth.
SPK_1: You have to sacrifice.
SPK_0: If you narrow the wealth down to the number of money, yes.
SPK_0: Again, wealth is bigger words than money.
SPK_1: Okay, let's just call it money.
SPK_0: Money, yeah.
SPK_1: Yes, I agree with that.
SPK_1: And so that's not happening.
SPK_0: No.
SPK_0: No, it can happen.
SPK_0: That's the beauty of it.
SPK_0: It can happen any time.
SPK_0: And I think that's the beauty of what you are doing and why it's good.
SPK_0: As you said, it's good for insurance company to come.
SPK_0: It might destroy them first.
SPK_0: It might give them.
SPK_0: Right.
SPK_0: But it will.
SPK_0: But it gives them a chance.
SPK_0: I will be honest, very tiny chance to build something truly beautiful.
SPK_0: And why it's not just truly beautiful if you want in the long run, that's the only things which can survive.
SPK_0: And that, you know, like nowadays people talk about resilience all of the time.
SPK_0: Sustainability is not a hot buzz anymore.
SPK_0: Everybody is now talking about resilience.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: In business world.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: But the ways I understand resilience is being capable of.
SPK_0: Moving forward without a handout, which is not what it is at all.
SPK_0: They are understanding as a result of trying to build resilient companies, they end up creating the most vulnerable companies, which can not extend any external shock because there is no deep connection in them.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: It's the same problem.
SPK_1: They don't have one Lord.
SPK_0: They don't have one Lord.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: They don't.
SPK_0: There is no true service.
SPK_0: There is always necessary scheming about finding the right magical trick.
SPK_1: Can we do, can we play a game for a second?
SPK_1: A historical game and we can get back to the table, but I think this applies to the table.
SPK_0: I think this applies to the table.
SPK_1: It does, a hundred percent.
SPK_1: Play a game with me.
SPK_1: Let's just call it 1310.
SPK_1: 1310, I don't know, Western Russia, we can go to Europe if you want, village.
SPK_1: Now, I lived in a village that I swear in West Africa that was, I lived there in 19, let's say, 89, but it was 1310.
SPK_1: There was no running water, no electricity.
SPK_1: It was beautiful on a lot of levels.
SPK_1: Okay.
SPK_1: And it was hard.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: Go to that village for me and then everyone's making fun of Amazon.
SPK_1: I just made fun of Amazon.
SPK_1: Everyone's making fun of the meaninglessness of working for Hershey's chocolate and, you know, wrapping up bars all day long.
SPK_1: I get it.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: There's a lot of, there's a lot of crisis of meaning.
SPK_1: Yes.
SPK_1: What's the one Lord in that Russian village in 1310?
SPK_1: Don't they have the same problems?
SPK_0: No, they, I would say they do have Christ.
SPK_0: It's pretty straightforward.
SPK_0: And even like an English medieval village, you would have it.
SPK_0: They might not be able to formulate it this way, but they would have their one Lord and one God.
SPK_0: They would also have very immediate Lord and God, like a master.
SPK_1: This is my question.
SPK_0: They would have it.
SPK_1: They still have, I've got to get the goats, you know.
SPK_0: They would still have it.
SPK_1: Protected from the snowstorm.
SPK_1: They still have.
SPK_0: All the toils and troubles of life would still be there.
SPK_0: But here is important distinction.
SPK_0: They would be more capable of facing the, that's a great connection.
SPK_0: Sorry, they would be way more resilient.
SPK_0: Sorry.
SPK_0: Imagine the life, famine constantly, survival not guaranteed, hurricanes, war, like war constantly in a modern way.
SPK_0: For example, we think about war, that's someone's fault.
SPK_0: If you look for a law for the word war in any old traditional language, it's more like it's a tragedy that fell upon us.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: That's kind of something upon us.
SPK_1: It was the spirits.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: It came on us.
SPK_1: Yes.
SPK_1: It came to us.
SPK_0: And there was a life, like my village is burned.
SPK_0: Life continues.
SPK_0: So in fact, these people would be way more resilient.
SPK_0: Why?
SPK_0: Because everything they do is happening in the face.
SPK_1: And it's recapitulated in the notion of Christ in those villages.
SPK_1: In the village I was in, there was, I'm not calling, this isn't about equality, things being the same, but there was a resiliency in the call to the Quran.
SPK_0: Mm-hmm.
SPK_1: On Fridays, on Jummah, there was a type of unity that got them through.
SPK_1: And so today we lack that.
SPK_1: Is that what we're saying?
SPK_0: I think we're saying that.
SPK_0: Oh, yeah, man.
SPK_0: We don't have it at all.
SPK_0: We want to replace it with images of power, with might, you can call it this way, I don't know, attributes of power, I guess that would be the word.
SPK_0: So if I have a trillion dollars, I'm safe.
SPK_0: If I have 20 airships, we're safe.
SPK_0: If I have nuclear bomb, we're safe.
SPK_0: No.
SPK_0: No, just in case.
SPK_0: No, but on personal level, on collective level, we all want to attributes of power without the service to the source of power, which is very arrogant, if you think about it.
SPK_1: It's very arrogant.
SPK_0: But very understandable, because any true relationship of service requires, again, vulnerability.
SPK_0: You know, any service is a relationship vulnerability.
SPK_0: That's right.
SPK_0: Let's look at the table.
SPK_0: Anytime you give the toast.
SPK_0: It's a moment of vulnerability.
SPK_0: The tricky part, it's vulnerability for the two.
SPK_0: It's vulnerability for you, the tamada, who has the power, and it's vulnerability for the person who receives the toast.
SPK_0: Even if it's around the third person, that's the reason why it's so hard.
SPK_0: You're still putting me in the spotlight.
SPK_0: And you still, as I noticed, like on a personal level, the thing you might say about me is not what I like in me, or I value in me, or I might be ashamed of it.
SPK_0: Like, there is a lot of like, but the only antidote is trust.
SPK_0: So you trust the speaker.
SPK_0: You trust the spirit of the table, or the source of your power, that somehow, mysteriously, in the long run, what you do will end up being right.
SPK_0: That's right.
SPK_0: I trust you, that you are a good tamada, that you won't humiliate me.
SPK_0: Simply, when I'm at your table, I trust that you won't humiliate me.
SPK_0: Sounds self-evident.
SPK_0: Well, it's not.
SPK_0: It's not.
SPK_0: If we could trust people that they won't humiliate us, we would not need the many institutions in our society.
SPK_1: This is the microcosmos.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_1: You're right.
SPK_1: All that's happening at the table is happening in life.
SPK_1: All the time.
SPK_0: That's why it's universal.
SPK_1: Yes, that's exactly right.
SPK_1: And that's also why, again, I really, I have to think, this mists of time known to me as Georgia and their adoption of Christianity, it has a special place, also because of the special place of Georgia geographically.
SPK_1: They've been pressed and compressed between Muslim.
SPK_0: No, first it was Byzantium versus Persians.
SPK_1: By the way, the Byzantians were the first ones to press in on the Georgians.
SPK_1: And they fought them.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_1: As Christians, they fought the Byzantines.
SPK_1: You're right.
SPK_1: Then it's Russians.
SPK_1: Then it's Western.
SPK_0: Even before, actually Russians came pretty late.
SPK_0: Then first it was like just different nomadic tribes of the Caucasian mountains because, you know, there are all different, hundreds of different tribes constantly warring between each other.
SPK_0: Then Mongols came, Arabs, Persians.
SPK_1: This is the diamond effect of a nation.
SPK_1: Yeah, it is a diamond.
SPK_1: And there is something special there.
SPK_1: There's something special about the table.
SPK_1: Now, everybody I know in the old world.
SPK_1: So say.
SPK_1: Say Indians, South Asians come to the table and then there's also some over there, there's some wasps, the wasps understand the table less naturally.
SPK_1: The South Asians, the Hindus, they understand the table naturally.
SPK_0: Again, sorry, I'm not defending the wasp, I'm just hating modernity.
SPK_0: Sorry.
SPK_1: Yeah, I see wasps out there, but it's a type of.
SPK_0: No, because it's important.
SPK_0: You know who would understand the table equally good?
SPK_0: English, Welsh and certain 10.
SPK_0: Yeah, I agree.
SPK_0: They would understand the table the same perfectly.
SPK_0: Totally understand.
SPK_0: That's why we love English ballads, all of the fall.
SPK_0: No doubt.
SPK_0: That's why people go to Renaissance fairs.
SPK_0: They are still looking for this.
SPK_0: Just.
SPK_1: That's a great point.
SPK_0: Like safer environment.
SPK_0: All of this.
SPK_1: Do Russians go to Renaissance fairs?
SPK_1: I really wanted to know that.
SPK_1: Don't do that.
SPK_1: Don't do that, right?
SPK_0: Don't really, no.
SPK_1: They're like, this is Ivan the Terrible's village.
SPK_1: Let's recreate it.
SPK_0: No, there is an element of it, but more like a tourist.
SPK_0: But not like, it's not the same, not translatable what Renaissance fair is here.
SPK_1: But have you seen an American Renaissance fair?
SPK_1: You must laugh at that.
SPK_1: It's nutty, right?
SPK_0: It's cute.
SPK_0: It ends sad.
SPK_1: I'm not even against it.
SPK_1: But you're right.
SPK_1: You're right.
SPK_1: It has a philosophical idea.
SPK_1: It's quite interesting.
SPK_1: Like, what is that?
SPK_0: Ultimately, where I was going.
SPK_0: Okay.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: So all of the, all I'm saying is the resilience effect or all of the old world effect, the
SPK_0: diamond effect.
SPK_0: As you said, it's about the face of it.
SPK_0: The being in the face of it.
SPK_0: Ah, remember where I was going to do.
SPK_0: Because we brought war, tragedy, resilience.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: Resilience.
SPK_0: And you already talked about it earlier.
SPK_0: Just a little bit too early.
SPK_0: I think now our conversation can begin.
SPK_0: The death part.
SPK_0: Like the fifth toast.
SPK_0: Why is there resilience?
SPK_0: Well, because there is not just physically alive people are present at the table in the
SPK_0: same manner as not just physically alive people are present in a village or in life or in a
SPK_0: society.
SPK_0: We just don't know what to do with them.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: It can take form of memory war.
SPK_0: History war.
SPK_0: Let's topple down this monument.
SPK_0: Let's erect this monument.
SPK_0: Let's build this Ark of the Triumph.
SPK_0: Let's do some other form of this.
SPK_0: Or, in a modern culture, let's just forget about dead altogether.
SPK_0: Right.
SPK_0: There is a special place for that.
SPK_0: And we don't think about that.
SPK_0: Literally.
SPK_0: Notice like how the more new world culture becomes.
SPK_0: And it's again global process.
SPK_0: Maybe started here.
SPK_0: You can see the effects everywhere.
SPK_0: There is a special place for dying.
SPK_0: There is a place for good, for the good.
SPK_0: There is a special place for death.
SPK_0: It doesn't present anywhere else.
SPK_0: But unfortunately, no matter what Elon Musk or anybody else is trying to do, we're still mortal.
SPK_0: So you can build true resilience if you don't face death.
SPK_0: But you can't face death without true life.
SPK_0: That's the tricky part of it.
SPK_0: Because we are not truly alive.
SPK_0: And what it means to be truly alive, it's where we start.
SPK_0: Because we, me, you, relationship between me and you, that's all hidden.
SPK_0: There is only empty function.
SPK_0: Well, function is by itself not a life.
SPK_0: It's a function.
SPK_0: It's dead.
SPK_0: It's done.
SPK_0: Literally, it's done.
SPK_0: So function cannot give this true life.
SPK_0: But then I can't face the death.
SPK_0: And if I can't face the death, I need to put it, let's say, to the edge.
SPK_1: But this makes true life harder.
SPK_1: Almost impossible.
SPK_1: No.
SPK_1: I think so.
SPK_0: On the surface, yes.
SPK_0: But in the long term, that's the only way to live.
SPK_0: That's the tricky part.
SPK_1: To push death?
SPK_0: No.
SPK_1: Well, I'm saying, as you push death to the edge, this makes true life impossible.
SPK_0: It makes true life impossible.
SPK_0: But even the imitation of true life, it makes it super fragile.
SPK_0: Anything becomes a catastrophe you can't deal with.
SPK_1: Yeah, okay.
SPK_0: You can't deal with it alone.
SPK_0: Because sacrifice becomes impossible.
SPK_0: True service becomes impossible.
SPK_0: Because in service, one might die.
SPK_0: Or more importantly, in service, one dies.
SPK_0: It's a little bit of a poetic metaphor, but it's not just a metaphor.
SPK_0: Therefore, in a way, Tamada has to die for the table.
SPK_1: Yeah, that's right.
SPK_1: That's, again, the design of all life.
SPK_1: So when you say, when the Georgian Supra puts the toast to the dead right in the middle,
SPK_1: that's a call to true life.
SPK_0: It's a call to true life, yes.
SPK_1: Which is the crucifixion.
SPK_0: It is a crucifixion, but also in this moment, the connection happens.
SPK_0: Because surprisingly, and here is what I learned in Georgia,
SPK_0: I find it like some linguistic game.
SPK_0: I actually forgot the word.
SPK_0: The story is like, so the word for dead in Georgian,
SPK_0: it's not something who were kind of behind us.
SPK_0: If you, like, the way we think about dead is something we are here,
SPK_0: and they are somewhere behind.
SPK_0: They're not truly present.
SPK_0: In Georgian, they are for.
SPK_1: They're in the future.
SPK_1: That's right.
SPK_0: They are not in the future.
SPK_0: Even future is wrong, but they are ahead of us.
SPK_0: So the whole time, space continuum, sorry,
SPK_0: it kind of becomes unity in this fifth toast moment.
SPK_0: That's right.
SPK_0: And only in this unity, sorry, true resilience can happen.
SPK_0: Service, love, vulnerability, power, all of these things become one.
SPK_0: They all only can happen against the face of death.
SPK_1: That's right.
SPK_1: Can I add that I think, I think that toast is the Trinitarian paradox
SPK_1: that the dead were, the dead are, and the dead will be.
SPK_1: And we're living it all in one moment in that toast.
SPK_1: Yes.
SPK_0: And you will live.
SPK_0: You will die.
SPK_0: But if somebody will raise a toast for you, and if they don't, you will live.
SPK_1: This is actually a part of the toast often, not all time, but I'll say it.
SPK_1: But they say, we member again, those who have died now,
SPK_1: so that our children will member us again, and so we don't die a second death.
SPK_1: And that is it.
SPK_1: That is it.
SPK_1: Can I tell a story?
SPK_1: I want to tell this story.
SPK_1: And some people on my podcast heard it already.
SPK_1: It's probably the, there's two, there's two stories.
SPK_1: But I'm going to tell this one.
SPK_1: There's another one we should tell later in the pod.
SPK_1: I watched this table.
SPK_1: I wasn't the Tamada of this table.
SPK_1: And my friend was the Tamada.
SPK_1: And he, two or three of his friends, I think it was two,
SPK_1: they came because together, the Tamada, this guy,
SPK_1: and his friend, he was the Tamada.
SPK_1: And his friends, they were all, they were served in Iraq together,
SPK_1: and they fought in Iraq, and they fought also in Afghanistan.
SPK_1: And they saw bad death to their friends.
SPK_1: One of the guys was rather disturbed still by his friend's death.
SPK_1: And he, let's call him unsettled about it and angry.
SPK_1: And my friend, who was the Tamada, kept saying, come, come and do this.
SPK_1: It's good.
SPK_1: We're going to honor these men.
SPK_1: So he got them to come.
SPK_1: He was, like, working hard.
SPK_1: And they came.
SPK_1: As a type of therapy, right?
SPK_1: Well, at the table, there were 20 people.
SPK_1: It was a public table, meaning it was a community table.
SPK_1: Everybody joined who wanted to join.
SPK_1: And they got to the toast to the dead.
SPK_1: And Tamada, my friend, made the toast and said,
SPK_1: let us remember those who have died.
SPK_1: He made the toast knowing that his friend wanted to,
SPK_1: Sagrada, take the toast because he wanted to honor his friends.
SPK_1: And so he said to those who have died,
SPK_1: and then he was turning to his friend.
SPK_1: And right then, someone at the other end of the table said,
SPK_1: may I have the toast?
SPK_1: Can I say a word?
SPK_1: And he said, please do.
SPK_1: I think you know this story.
SPK_1: I sure don't.
SPK_1: No, you don't know it.
SPK_1: So guess what happened at the other end?
SPK_1: A gentleman stood up and said, I want a toast to Jenny,
SPK_1: who had to die so I could become Jim.
SPK_1: The whole table was like, what?
SPK_1: This is in the South.
SPK_0: This is where we are.
SPK_1: It's right upstairs.
SPK_1: It's the South.
SPK_1: So this person is implying that their previous self died.
SPK_1: They're trans.
SPK_1: They're transitioning.
SPK_1: Leave that to the side for a second because watch what happens
SPK_1: because it's about to get ugly.
SPK_1: If you leave that to the side just for a second,
SPK_1: something bad happened to this person,
SPK_1: and they think something good is now happening.
SPK_1: Fine.
SPK_1: I'm not really sure that's death because you know how I am
SPK_1: because I watched it.
SPK_1: But this guy who came to toast to his dead friends,
SPK_1: started cursing.
SPK_1: What the, what is the, and he's loud.
SPK_1: And he's like, you're telling me you brought me here for this?
SPK_1: This is, what the, and he, and my friend is like trying to,
SPK_1: the table's like blowing apart.
SPK_1: This is supposed to be solemn, you know?
SPK_1: And he turns and he, and he does a brilliant thing,
SPK_1: which I highly recommend to people at home
SPK_1: whenever somebody's flipping out.
SPK_1: Suddenly, somehow get them to become, in an instant,
SPK_1: a public speaker.
SPK_1: And he just went,
SPK_1: Ella Verde, it's your toast.
SPK_1: And he's just like, ah, and he just went,
SPK_1: now everyone's watching him.
SPK_1: And he gave a toast.
SPK_1: And he didn't talk about the transgender death.
SPK_1: He talked about his friends, and the whole table was crying.
SPK_1: And the whole table came to him as a type of rescue.
SPK_1: Not that they were like saying, Jenny didn't really,
SPK_1: they weren't, it wasn't political,
SPK_1: but they recognized his pain.
SPK_1: He started crying.
SPK_1: They all started crying.
SPK_1: It was a, it's a very sad story.
SPK_1: And in the end, they embraced this guy
SPK_1: through their own toast and a recognition of his pain.
SPK_1: And he goes, what happened at the end?
SPK_1: They all took a picture together,
SPK_1: including Jenny the trans, or Jimmy the trans guy.
SPK_1: How about that?
SPK_0: Well, that reminds me of the other story.
SPK_0: Like there's a story about Stacey or whatever,
SPK_0: like the one you did.
SPK_1: That story too.
SPK_0: Again, death.
SPK_0: Like, is it painful?
SPK_0: Obviously it is.
SPK_0: Like, that's a tragic.
SPK_0: Problem is like the only way through this pain is in a way you said,
SPK_0: it's actually communal.
SPK_0: We, there is a popular phrase like we live alone, we die alone.
SPK_0: To an extent, but not, but no, that's actually not what I believe.
SPK_0: No, actually opposite is the case.
SPK_0: We actually die together and we live together.
SPK_0: That's very opposite.
SPK_0: We forgot about it.
SPK_0: And that's why living is so hard and dying is so hard.
SPK_0: And the only way is to bring them together.
SPK_0: Again, in a proper order, proper place.
SPK_1: Do you blame?
SPK_0: I don't blame.
SPK_0: If you're looking what cause the cause is.
SPK_1: I want to blame.
SPK_1: I want to ask you that using that word blame.
SPK_1: Um, cause you're a philosopher in the, in a real true sense.
SPK_1: You take time with, with, I'm a philosopher in that I've read and I love it and I wrote
SPK_1: about it, but I don't take time with the, with, with the pieces.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: And I don't, I don't dig down.
SPK_1: But do you blame a type of this?
SPK_1: Modern loneliness on a series of very innovative philosophers like John Locke, uh, Rene Descartes.
SPK_1: Do you blame this unique loneliness that we have on these characters?
SPK_0: Well, they are partially responsible to it.
SPK_0: Whereas even the main guys, no, I think it goes just way deeper than this.
SPK_0: It goes way deeper than this.
SPK_0: It goes in a very subtle moment and, and often with best intentions, like what is so bad to focus on?
SPK_0: How we can make this life materially better.
SPK_0: Roger Bacon, whose first thought that like through, basically he had a very Peter Thiel argument, uh, effectively
SPK_0: that, uh, like, you know, when already antichrist will come, so he will use the weapons of technology and science to his, to
SPK_0: advance, to destroy the bad guys, to destroy us good guys.
SPK_0: So we need to master this arts before him.
SPK_0: So we can give him a good fight effectively.
SPK_0: Like pretty serious.
SPK_1: Peter Thiel argument, you're right.
SPK_0: Just, I'm saying it's not really new.
SPK_1: You're right.
SPK_1: That one, uh, there's another one.
SPK_1: Mr.
SPK_1: Bacon.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: Bacon, different bacons and like the cards and then it's all starts.
SPK_0: Like ultimately I think what happens is, well, and it, I blame us ourselves.
SPK_0: Like again, our human nature, which we didn't keep.
SPK_0: And not even, this is not true.
SPK_0: Basically it all comes down to heresies and schisms.
SPK_0: I will be honest.
SPK_0: I think the.
SPK_0: Problems of philosophy are only the consequences of our theological problem.
SPK_0: And what, what was lost is like exactly this participation, like we understood participation wrongly.
SPK_0: Like, and then ironically, when we try to solve the problem of like participation, we solved it wrong.
SPK_0: Like that's very human thing to do.
SPK_0: What I mean is a true participation.
SPK_0: I mean, the understanding that the relationship precedes anything that who is doing something comes first before doing.
SPK_1: I think you can say reality.
SPK_1: Reality is only known in a relationship.
SPK_0: Reality is only visible.
SPK_0: Like even the words don't have meaning outside of relationship.
SPK_1: Well, Tolstoy, this is my favorite short story and don't blame me.
SPK_1: I know Tolstoy, he's, he's problematic, but what men live by one of the lessons that it's just magnificent.
SPK_1: Sure.
SPK_1: So have you read it?
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: He says, men don't know what they need.
SPK_0: We don't know.
SPK_1: And you know how we learn by our neighbor who loves us, shows us.
SPK_1: This is amazing concept.
SPK_0: This is amazing concept.
SPK_1: Like, but really, like Jeff Bezos doesn't really know what he needs.
SPK_1: No.
SPK_1: He's only shown through those who, who he loves and loves him.
SPK_1: That's a pretty wild concept.
SPK_0: We think, but also like in any teaching experience, uh, the only reason people come to teachers is because anything teaching in anything like me admitting, I don't know what I need to, like, I don't know what to do.
SPK_0: I trust you.
SPK_0: You will be a good teacher and here is a tricky part.
SPK_0: What's the difference between, back to the point, what's the difference between good teacher and bad teacher?
SPK_0: Pretty straightforward concept if you think about it.
SPK_0: Uh, so the way I answer, the way I answer is like a good teacher teaches without an interest.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_0: The word interest is actually a very, I think the problem was started when we started introducing interest or user, like basically.
SPK_1: Oh, you're in my discipline, wheelhouse.
SPK_0: But it is.
SPK_0: Okay.
SPK_0: It's all surprisingly connected to even, that's why I find surprising, even on language, for example, it doesn't work in, in Russian, like we don't, the word for interest is different, like, so it wouldn't work, it's percentage, so it doesn't work.
SPK_1: But usury tells you a lot.
SPK_0: But usury tells you a lot, but we tend to narrow it down, but it's a problem of a true giving and that's why love is legitimately hard.
SPK_0: You kind of need to give something without interest as a service, but without interest, that's hard.
SPK_1: This is amazing.
SPK_1: Because obviously there's a double entendre there, but man, I'm telling you in the restaurant business, what we learned, we're successful.
SPK_1: We don't make as much money as we could, but as a restaurant, we make money and here's why, is what you just said.
SPK_1: There was a spirit in the restaurant somehow that said, no, when they don't, when you see someone in the menu saying, I can't afford that, give it to them.
SPK_1: Give it without interest.
SPK_1: In other words, give it without.
SPK_1: Give it without having an interest in your own well-being, like just give it, it's not of interest to you as per your own well-being, because I can tell they want it or need it, and I'm just telling you it's its own, it's not the secret, it's not all that garbage about, you know, if you're nice, then God will give it back to you, it's not that, it's not that, it's.
SPK_0: It won't because of what you said right now, it's already an interest, that's why it's tricky, the moment you start thinking about it this way.
SPK_0: It's already turning into interest.
SPK_1: It's, it's, you're shaped by the giving, in other words.
SPK_0: You're trusting the third, ultimately what you're doing, you're trusting the third.
SPK_1: You're trusting God, and that God is then shaping you in that potential vulnerability, because you, you could actually use that money, you know what I mean?
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_1: They tell us all the time that we shouldn't do supra because we don't keep track of the wine.
SPK_1: In other words, it's really hard to see how many glasses people pour, you know, you've been to supra.
SPK_1: And they're like, you're going to never make any money.
SPK_1: I was going to say, I, we found out, no, we'll make money, we won't make maybe as much as you would like us to make, but we've got other forms of wealth now.
SPK_0: That's more important.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: And, but that's the thing, you notice how it's, here is a paradox, this formula, like, I'm sorry, yes, I'm trying to put into words something which might not, like, it's limited, it works both ways.
SPK_0: What I mean is like giving without interest or serving without interest, it doesn't matter on which level of hierarchy.
SPK_0: You are, it doesn't matter whether you're a tamada or whether you're a guest at the table.
SPK_1: That's right.
SPK_0: Because if as a tamada or as a person of power or teacher or doctor, I give, I need to give without interest.
SPK_0: It makes me vulnerable.
SPK_0: Because what is it, vulnerability?
SPK_0: It might not be received.
SPK_0: That's the thing.
SPK_0: Whenever somebody teaches, I can't accept it to be received.
SPK_0: I can put my best, like, into it, but it will still not work.
SPK_0: You can make the most beautiful toast.
SPK_1: That's a good point.
SPK_0: From your opinion, it won't work.
SPK_0: But if you give it in sincerity without interest, like, somehow the spirit will not let this fact to destroy you.
SPK_0: On a lower level, like, if you're, let's say, that's actually the tricky part, notice, like, by everybody is a king at the table.
SPK_0: Yes, you're kind of the big king as a tamada, but the moment you give the toast, in this very short moment, ontologically, you're already becoming the servant.
SPK_0: That's right.
SPK_0: Because the power to accept or reject is the power.
SPK_1: Yeah, that's right.
SPK_0: So in this moment, he is a king, but then the dance continues.
SPK_0: The moment he accepted or rejected, it's the next choice how to react to what it is, and this he can control.
SPK_0: So it's constant dance of vulnerability, constantly moving up and down the ladder of hierarchy, constantly joint service, and that's why it works.
SPK_1: It's why also, as our guys know, the most, let's call them problematic, because they're still good people and good tamadas.
SPK_1: But the most problematic tamadas?
SPK_1: This equation comes very difficult to them.
SPK_0: And for a good reason, because, again, it creates way more, okay, that's the tricky part.
SPK_0: The problem with this truth, if you follow it, it creates infinitely more possibilities of chaos while actually decreasing them, while actually decreasing actual chaos.
SPK_0: Do you understand what I mean?
SPK_1: Say it again, say it again.
SPK_0: So it's infinitely, I think, increasing the possibilities of chaos.
SPK_0: Mm-hmm.
SPK_0: So all of that.
SPK_0: The unknowables.
SPK_0: The actual amount of unknowables is growing.
SPK_1: That's right.
SPK_0: But what you will learn from experience, and you can run mathematical models on it if you want, or somebody may.
SPK_0: I don't know.
SPK_0: I just know it from experience.
SPK_0: If you actually do it, you will notice that actual amount of chaos decreases around the table.
SPK_0: They're actually just things starting to happen good.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_0: So the possibility of this, and that's what we're talking about, the possibilities of things turning bad at any moment when everybody's giving without interest.
SPK_0: That's right.
SPK_0: And that the fact that this person is vulnerable isn't necessarily increasing.
SPK_0: But they're becoming reality, just doesn't happen.
SPK_0: But you can't control it.
SPK_0: And that's the biggest challenge.
SPK_0: You can't control it.
SPK_0: Right.
SPK_0: No matter how many good supers you do, or how many years of good marriage you have, you can't control it.
SPK_1: No.
SPK_1: And by the way, you shouldn't.
SPK_0: And you shouldn't.
SPK_0: It's one thing you can't, and the second thing you shouldn't.
SPK_0: But you can see where adaptation comes.
SPK_0: Let me clarify.
SPK_0: Yeah, maybe.
SPK_1: It's not clarify.
SPK_1: Rephrase.
SPK_1: Let me add.
SPK_1: from again like at a plebeian level the art of the tamra is what you just said it's it's offering a
SPK_1: toast that's not from you for them it's in them and you're putting words to what they already
SPK_0: are okay it's even trickier they have to please because it's still too horizontal so it's more
SPK_0: like you're offering something which you notice in there above passing through you but this
SPK_0: something was already in them so it's kind of so something so there is a relationship between
SPK_0: something above and something in them which they don't see but you see and this energy you got it
SPK_1: you're the mediator of remembrance yes it's not new and it's not yours and it's not it's not just
SPK_0: in them so it's not just in them you talk
SPK_1: not to them but to you talk well if you really want to get into it what are in georgia we we have
SPK_0: teachers we have some surprising that sorry for interrupting but it says just uh this kind of
SPK_0: request for you to dive deeper so uh what i say sounds weird and like it's us uh alien new world
SPK_0: is rediscovering which old world knows it i think that's what i want you to do that so the old world
SPK_0: actually knows what i've been like kind of talking
SPK_1: so what you've been doing is is putting like intellectual bones or word flesh on guilty on old
SPK_1: world bones which is something like this is i'm just going to do my best with this and again i'm
SPK_1: using georgia but also all these other places where we work is there's a there's there's a
SPK_1: natural and the hindus and the buddhists are really good at this language but there's a natural wisdom
SPK_1: in being small so this is what christ talks about with the meek
SPK_1: and we just don't even know what the meek are anymore in the west the meek is the worst thing
SPK_1: you could possibly worry yeah it's kind of worst i used to when when we go and work in west africa
SPK_1: there's always some somebody that will come and carry your stuff and then they'll make sure you
SPK_1: have food you don't barely know them and you're like what are you doing and they're serving you
SPK_1: almost like it's very uncomfortable but what what the georgians know the tamada knows is
SPK_1: if they stay in that place now they have to stand up
SPK_1: give the image of power and strength but if they stay in that place of meekness and humility
SPK_1: then everybody else is drawn out yeah and that's what you're saying the common thing
SPK_1: is your the tamara invites you to the thing that exists in you but really through the one
SPK_1: through god that's why you said earlier the table is filled with the holy spirit
SPK_1: a good table with sometimes well the tamara can invite bad spirits
SPK_1: but it's always a spirit it's it's some spirit belongs to the table i agree and so what i want
SPK_1: to say is what i've noticed what i the great division between old and new world is is it's
SPK_1: just simply a modicum of control to what degree in the old world could you control a very low
SPK_1: degree because the whole idea is either the god was doing it or your god christ demanded meekness
SPK_1: of you right no he's still doing it he will still do it still doing it the new world is the great
SPK_1: divide is is i can't
SPK_1: figure this out to me that's really so when we talk about babylon what's what's babylon that's
SPK_1: old world that's that's this before the enlightenment but the thing is is they had the
SPK_1: same spirit oh yeah we're gonna figure this out and we're gonna do it ourselves we're gonna build
SPK_1: a name for ourselves and and the old world that place that cavernous dark simple i think of it as
SPK_1: like a like a small little underground georgian church made out of stone that world it doesn't
SPK_1: communicate or understand well this this world of command and control notice what happens so on the
SPK_0: on the surface this world becomes way more vulnerable a nuclear bomb example or a big
SPK_0: army like it can destroy most of the nowadays especially in the enlightenment era as famous
SPK_0: pioneers of this new world alternative a a brits said uh i am right and you are not i have machine
SPK_0: gun you do not like classical new world solution to this problem
SPK_0: but in the long run the new world is killing itself to an extinction that's what's the tricky
SPK_0: part when we are talking about resilience the only world which can survive long term is the
SPK_0: old world like the one which is actually go lets the control away no doubt on my podcast
SPK_1: that things have become very evident to me as a history podcast of sorts is i love to pit old
SPK_1: world versus the newer world i love to pit the old world versus the newer world i love to pit the
SPK_1: world as a teaching device but i would argue that true christianity lived like in the spirit of
SPK_1: christ is really neither it's it's really it's universal it's the royal path it's what covers
SPK_1: both but it's fun to place it in the old world because of many of those old world concepts are
SPK_1: they percolate within the christian narrative like you can feel them in there but it's
SPK_1: so but i would say that the old world has you know it's not an elixir it doesn't fix everything oh
SPK_1: it doesn't but we can learn so many things okay from the communitarian world view of so many of
SPK_0: those small villages absolutely and places here is a tricky part we can't just go back that's
SPK_0: important that's why the table is universal what we are guessing call to on doesn't matter which
SPK_0: level of service of power we are i mean either mind or physical power or family or house
SPK_0: to recognize and to see again this pattern this dance this relationships and to embody themselves
SPK_0: now in a very particular way that's the thing and the tricky part is any table is particular
SPK_0: the exact embodiment as we talk will be particular us trying to recreate old georgian
SPK_0: village or old russian even village it won't work it won't work it's dumb even even our georgian
SPK_1: friends tell us don't do that by the way they never get mad at you
SPK_1: that we quote appropriate they're they're like please they start crying well because it's a gift
SPK_1: they say they you got it but they say honor it yeah honor it but they say you have to do it your
SPK_0: way i think that's the thing so honor it but do it your way what it means so you must find a way
SPK_0: to kind of do it in the same spirit the spirit must be the same yeah but the face of the spirit
SPK_0: i would say maybe you will disagree or maybe you will agree that the
SPK_0: basically all spirits of good tables of god all god supers are kind of the
SPK_0: relatives of one or the proxies of one or the the one good spirit but they all look different and
SPK_0: that's kind of what i totally agree with in the same way that all good families are in a way you
SPK_1: can see the similarity it's the same spirit but i'm telling you there is a moment it's not all
SPK_1: tables but there's a moment when these tom and our guys they know it and i know it too
SPK_1: you're like
SPK_1: that's a good table and it's got nothing to do with somebody's good toasts oh they're so poetic
SPK_1: it's got to do with the ability for people to sit still and want to stay in that spot
SPK_1: and whenever you see that you're like this is a good table and this is an it is an image of
SPK_1: heaven to an extent don't you want to stay in heaven that's the whole idea the whole idea is
SPK_1: once you've acquired that no i'm not going anywhere and the time that i will say like
SPK_1: like if someone says i gotta go they're going to say i'm not going anywhere i'm not going anywhere
SPK_1: but what could be where would you go where would you go where is so important to go and then you're
SPK_1: like well i gotta get home watch netflix they'll be like okay but really why and it's that little
SPK_1: moment that has changed my life yeah amen