SPK_0: Well, hello, Jordan. We'll start our conversation with meeting each other. And I think it is
SPK_0: important that every story, and we're here to tell a story, begins with the storytellers
SPK_0: sitting together and not just floating in the dense air of ideas. But it is the dense
SPK_0: air we're going to talk about. Because our story is not the usual story. Our story is
SPK_0: about the air we breathe, the water we swim in without knowing where we're even swimming
SPK_0: in it. It's a story about how we build a tower, and we're living on its 200th floor, and the
SPK_0: shade of the tower has completely obscured the foundation of the tower. So the foundation
SPK_0: became self-evident. So we're going to talk about these things. We're going to talk about
SPK_0: the self-evident assumptions about the nature of reality, which can be summarized
SPK_0: under the smart-sounding word Gnosticism. But the reason why I am going into this story
SPK_0: is to share my fascination with it and to make a step aside. If I'm a fish, I want to
SPK_0: jump out of the water for a moment and look from this thing, you know, a flying fish is
SPK_0: doing and look a little bit on the water to see what is the air we are breathing. If I'm
SPK_0: a fish, I want to, for a moment, imagine myself it's being an author. It's a tricky part, we can,
SPK_0: but I don't think we can truly do it alone, and that's why I invited you here to this place,
SPK_0: which is symbolic and meaningful to me, but also I hope to you as well, and happy to be around you.
SPK_1: I'm loving the experience of somebody who would be watching this and might be curious about
SPK_1: where this place is, and even if it is.
SPK_1: I'm not going to resolve that question.
SPK_0: That's a good part. It's already hinting in what we're going to talk about in the future.
SPK_0: Small salt of mystery in any good story is necessary. But anyway, so the name of the
SPK_0: story is The Gnostic Civilization, How Our World Is Made. And truth be told, it's a pretty good
SPK_0: title. Like, it actually covers what we're going to talk about. So we're going to talk about
SPK_0: civilization, we're going to talk about Gnosticism as these underlying meta-principles,
SPK_0: under which most of the stories we share are structured, willingly or unwillingly.
SPK_0: And the way we're going to do it is we're going to look straight into assumptions. We're not doing
SPK_0: it chronologically. We're going straight into principles and how they manifest in us, because
SPK_0: the truth is part. Guilty, partially Gnostic myself. Like, still, like, it's not something I
SPK_0: can say I'm free of it. No, it's part of me. So I'm going to talk about it. And I'm going to talk
SPK_0: about it. I'm telling effectively my story. But also, like, how it manifested 2,000 years ago,
SPK_0: 500 years ago, yesterday, and most probably will even manifest tomorrow. But right before we jump
SPK_0: into it, I do want to put you on a spotlight. Tell me, why are you interested in this story?
SPK_0: Like, why did you agree to talk about this story?
SPK_1: I have to rewind, because the last week
SPK_1: has been super saturated with significance and
SPK_1: signs that I want to use to answer your question. But of course, I agreed well before that.
SPK_1: To be perfectly honest, the beginning of the invitation was you said that you had been called
SPK_1: to this inquiry, and that you noticed that you could not do it monologically. It required
SPK_1: dialogue. And this felt very right in the sense of an insight. And for whatever reason,
SPK_1: a conversation with me would be there. A good idea, let's say. And so I inquired into what is
SPK_1: this question? Like, just from the hints. Because you notice there's an interpolation in just that
SPK_1: way of speaking about it that tells you a lot.
SPK_1: And when I say inquired, we could say I prayed.
SPK_1: And because that's exactly what happened. I was not alone in the inquiry. And the image that came
SPK_1: up was actually very intense.
SPK_1: And I could actually feel almost a certain sense of fear of being in this chair, having this
SPK_1: conversation, which I've learned means go that direction. And if I'm invited rightly, then it is
SPK_1: almost certainly the direction that I am specifically supposed to go on. So to put it
SPK_1: a different way, I heard that this was a call. So that's why I'm here.
SPK_0: This is the first conversation of the seven we're going to have. And as any good story,
SPK_0: has to have a beginning. So let's start with the beginning. What is the most basic underlying
SPK_0: agnostic assumption? And to an extent, our assumption. And it is very tricky. It is
SPK_0: such an innocent claim that the world is made flawed. The world is broken. That there is
SPK_0: something inherently wrong with the way the world is. And let's look at the trick. And the trick is
SPK_0: in the beginning. In Genesis, the world is created good. So the world is not, by its nature, bad.
SPK_0: And in Gnosticism, there is some original flaw with the world. The difference is very subtle,
SPK_0: as with all of the stories we're going to tell. But from these subtle differences,
SPK_0: all of the big tree of conclusions emerges, which became so natural to us.
SPK_0: Like one way.
SPK_0: The second manifest, which we often experience, is that the world is a form of prison. A prison
SPK_0: you need to run away from. And I think it's worth to go in the beginning first. I think, yeah,
SPK_0: it makes relevant. Like how is the subtle difference? Because they do have a God even
SPK_0: in the story. But it's not the Christian God. So the Gnostic original, the most basic Gnostic
SPK_0: story, runs in something like this. There is a realm of ideas. Or not even ideas,
SPK_0: but the spiritual reality. There is a realm of a spiritual reality. And this spiritual reality,
SPK_0: is good. But a part of this, and there is something which they would call God there,
SPK_0: in this reality. But one of the spirits in this reality was pretty ugly. It's actually,
SPK_0: they would call like some ugly form, some reject of this perfect being. And in its imperfection,
SPK_0: it created matter. It created the material world, which became a trap for the souls,
SPK_0: for the immaterial.
SPK_0: And that's how the world worked.
SPK_0: we live in, says Gnostic
SPK_0: mycosis, this early times
SPK_0: is made. And this
SPK_0: is so radically different
SPK_0: from the idea of a world
SPK_0: created good, but then
SPK_0: falling.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: So,
SPK_1: in some sense,
SPK_1: this is the story of reason.
SPK_1: This is the story of reason
SPK_1: personified. This is the
SPK_1: experience of reason.
SPK_1: If yourself is reason,
SPK_1: then that's the actual experience
SPK_1: of the reality you find yourself in.
SPK_1: And then
SPK_1: when reason, on reason's own basis,
SPK_1: endeavors to make sense of the experience that reason
SPK_1: finds itself in, it
SPK_1: tells this story.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_1: Inescapably, because that is
SPK_1: the story of reason, which is to say
SPK_1: the story of a faculty of the
SPK_1: whole separated from the whole,
SPK_1: which cannot by its very nature recapitulate
SPK_1: or recommune itself with the whole,
SPK_1: but is, when separated,
SPK_1: has the capacity
SPK_1: to usurp the position
SPK_1: of the throne, let's say,
SPK_1: and tries on the basis of its own power,
SPK_1: its own will, to recover
SPK_1: the wholeness from which it is left.
SPK_0: Yes. Because that's where the story is diverged.
SPK_0: Like, now we have a seat,
SPK_0: we have a trunk of a tree, and here
SPK_0: the story is diverged. This recovery
SPK_0: can happen in many different ways.
SPK_0: The classic Gnostic way
SPK_0: is to run away
SPK_0: from a prison. That's why
SPK_0: early Gnostic sects often end up in
SPK_0: suicide. Yes, mass suicide.
SPK_0: And it makes sense. So you need
SPK_0: to free your spirit. And the most
SPK_0: radical form of liberation
SPK_0: of the spirit is to free yourself
SPK_0: from the matter. And
SPK_0: since, again,
SPK_0: here it depends on different traditions, but
SPK_0: ultimately, through different, like,
SPK_0: let's say, practices
SPK_0: or
SPK_0: wills or intentions or predestinations,
SPK_0: some souls are capable
SPK_0: to jumping out of the prison back
SPK_0: into this realm.
SPK_0: And you can see how
SPK_0: it doesn't sound that appealing.
SPK_0: Like, this version of
SPK_0: reclaiming your position does not sound
SPK_0: truly appealing to us. Some
SPK_0: very deep feeling in us is still
SPK_0: clinging to life. Like, we don't really
SPK_0: want, like, again, we can do it on, like,
SPK_0: sometimes cases happen individually, but
SPK_0: it would not become a massive story.
SPK_0: Like, the massive story of Gnostics wouldn't become
SPK_0: massive. This whole feeling of a broken world
SPK_0: would not become truly
SPK_0: appealing to masses of
SPK_0: people. And to us, it
SPK_0: wouldn't become the doxa of
SPK_0: modernity if it were a state
SPK_0: here. And that's actually where
SPK_0: Christianity played a big role, surprisingly.
SPK_0: Because Christianity brought
SPK_0: a very interesting thing we also
SPK_0: hold to be self-evident, which
SPK_0: was not for most of the cultures
SPK_0: ever in history.
SPK_0: That optimism.
SPK_0: Gospel is a good news.
SPK_0: If you look for an ancient Greek,
SPK_0: the idea that you can expect anything
SPK_0: good of this world is
SPK_0: madness. Like, it's if anything
SPK_0: human hubris, which got
SPK_1: banished.
SPK_0: The idea
SPK_0: that some radical improvement
SPK_0: can happen.
SPK_0: The idea that, like,
SPK_0: anything good can follow
SPK_0: in part through your actions,
SPK_0: through will, like, through human
SPK_0: participation, you can say. Like, let's even
SPK_0: steal now and further. In the beginning, it's
SPK_0: just about participation. So, this
SPK_0: idea is Christianity in its
SPK_0: natural. And it
SPK_0: came, and it transformed,
SPK_0: it created the Christian
SPK_0: tradition. And then, millennia and centuries,
SPK_0: between the point of good news
SPK_0: and between the return, you can
SPK_0: say, of this Gnostic spirit.
SPK_0: The spirit went a little bit in a slumber.
SPK_0: It kind of slept. Stayed under the
SPK_0: shadows.
SPK_1: Well, we should say,
SPK_1: the spirit has an internal mandate.
SPK_1: Yes.
SPK_1: The internal mandate is
SPK_1: to, in fact, to consume all.
SPK_1: As you say, if it is not subtle,
SPK_1: it will consume only a very, very
SPK_1: narrow few. So, it must
SPK_1: become more subtle.
SPK_0: Yes. And
SPK_0: this subtleness
SPK_0: basically until
SPK_0: we became tired.
SPK_0: Because there is one very interesting
SPK_0: part of the Christian story,
SPK_0: Christian optimism, that it
SPK_0: requires a lot of
SPK_0: patience. Like, my
SPK_0: favorite part is Ascension,
SPK_0: when Christ is going
SPK_0: into heavens, and the Apostles
SPK_0: ask him the most normal,
SPK_0: rational, human question.
SPK_0: When are you going to come back?
SPK_0: Effectively. Please tell us
SPK_0: time, date, we can prepare.
SPK_0: It's not your business to know.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_0: Very radical proposition
SPK_0: and very counterintuitive proposition
SPK_0: for us. Let me put it this way.
SPK_0: So, we don't know.
SPK_0: And this not knowing is
SPK_0: essential part, like
SPK_0: Christian life. But it's not
SPK_0: an easy part. And over the
SPK_0: course of millennia, with
SPK_0: many different stories playing around,
SPK_0: which we're going to talk about, mention it,
SPK_0: but some big events, let's say, some stuff
SPK_0: like plague, religious wars,
SPK_0: stuff like
SPK_0: general appeal
SPK_0: to reason, rediscovery,
SPK_0: what the people would call renaissance,
SPK_0: love reason. Like,
SPK_0: the waiting became tiresome.
SPK_0: Especially among
SPK_0: people which usually have the most free time
SPK_0: on their hands. Elite.
SPK_0: Like, I mean, elite,
SPK_0: both intellectuals and
SPK_0: physical elites.
SPK_0: And the Christian
SPK_0: understanding of unfallen world
SPK_0: slightly changed.
SPK_0: Now it became a fallen
SPK_0: world, which you need to improve.
SPK_0: That's a subtle, slight step.
SPK_1: Yeah, we have to be very careful with that.
SPK_1: And I don't mean,
SPK_1: if we want to get it right, we'll have to
SPK_1: spend the time to be able to get to
SPK_1: the bottom of that.
SPK_1: And allow that subtlety to be,
SPK_1: to unfold, because it's a very
SPK_1: significant move.
SPK_0: What I mean is,
SPK_0: like, it's one thing
SPK_0: to say that the
SPK_0: world is fallen,
SPK_0: and to understand it as
SPK_0: the result of
SPK_0: effectively a fall of human heart.
SPK_0: It's the same understanding, but different
SPK_0: ways of explaining it. Like, one says
SPK_0: it's effectively the history, the price
SPK_0: of the falling of angels.
SPK_0: So, first angels fallen, that's why
SPK_0: the history emerged, like, this whole
SPK_0: time is effectively an
SPK_0: entropic time. Emerging like
SPK_0: the originally created world
SPK_0: would be free of entropy. Like, we don't know
SPK_0: how it is, but some traditions effectively say
SPK_0: that's what has happened. And then there is a whole
SPK_0: garden, and the whole Adam and Eve,
SPK_0: falling. And that's why it sounds even weird to a modern
SPK_0: environment when we say, like, that even
SPK_0: like, death is an outcome
SPK_0: of sin. Like, so that would
SPK_0: be the most orthodox Christian
SPK_0: understanding. But it's another saying,
SPK_0: the world is fallen, but
SPK_0: you have will, reason, power
SPK_0: to make it a better
SPK_0: place while you're still waiting to the
SPK_0: Christ. That's a very important part.
SPK_1: Yes, so,
SPK_1: let me put two things out.
SPK_1: You have
SPK_1: the notion of you should be patient.
SPK_1: But the root of that
SPK_1: is to be a patient.
SPK_1: Which is the opposite
SPK_1: of agent. You have agent
SPK_1: and patient. Those are the complements.
SPK_1: They're complementary. One is an
SPK_1: agent, one is a patient.
SPK_1: The call, the Christian call is
SPK_1: to be a patient,
SPK_1: not to be patient.
SPK_1: The slippage is what happens when you take an agent
SPK_1: and you say, wait.
SPK_1: Hold back your agency for
SPK_1: some period of time.
SPK_1: To the English ear, when we say patient,
SPK_1: we don't mean to become a
SPK_1: patient. We would not say to become an
SPK_1: ontological transition to
SPK_1: receptivity. What we say
SPK_1: is hold back your agency
SPK_1: for some period of time. Like a
SPK_1: kid. I want to go play.
SPK_1: Be patient. Your will
SPK_1: will be realized, but you
SPK_1: have to hold it back.
SPK_1: I'm going to propose that that is a chasm.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_1: That is a tremendous
SPK_1: chasm.
SPK_1: Second, the very ordinary experience.
SPK_1: My house,
SPK_1: gets dirty
SPK_1: over time. And if
SPK_1: I don't clean it, it will not clean
SPK_1: itself. This is very
SPK_1: ordinary. If I am told,
SPK_1: and by the way, I can
SPK_1: clean it. This is also very important.
SPK_0: It's a very important part.
SPK_1: You can clean it.
SPK_1: I can clean it.
SPK_1: In fact, if I work with
SPK_1: my wife and my daughter and we work together, we can
SPK_1: actually clean it together in a way that is both
SPK_1: easier and better
SPK_0: and beautiful.
SPK_1: So, there's a sleight of hand
SPK_1: where we somehow
SPK_1: get demoralized into believing
SPK_1: that to be patient
SPK_1: is to lack access to this form
SPK_1: of beauty.
SPK_1: And so, in that sleight of hand,
SPK_1: somebody comes along and says,
SPK_1: but we can make the world a better
SPK_1: place. And now we're
SPK_1: back into the story.
SPK_0: And that's why
SPK_0: coming back into the story, but let's stay
SPK_0: in the story you brought it up about
SPK_0: this whole, because the second
SPK_0: part of this, it's not just
SPK_0: you can make the world a better place,
SPK_0: and it's not even you should make it a better place,
SPK_0: but it's
SPK_0: all you can make.
SPK_0: That's the real trick of happiness.
SPK_0: That's all you have access
SPK_0: to is cleaning your house.
SPK_0: And that's where
SPK_0: the trick would have happened in this metaphor.
SPK_0: Like, that's the limit. You're absolutely
SPK_0: right how
SPK_0: the vulnerability for this trick
SPK_0: happens, and that, I think, is great. Yeah, so it's
SPK_0: not about patience. It's a patience.
SPK_0: It's, yeah, it's even transcending
SPK_0: this category. Like, I used patience
SPK_0: in a...
SPK_1: We're trying to tease them hard, because
SPK_1: these things live in the grammar. They live in
SPK_1: the language. They live in these weird
SPK_1: confusions where something
SPK_1: is, like you said, the basement. It becomes
SPK_1: a blind spot that we've built
SPK_1: on top of. We've forgotten even what the
SPK_1: bricks were that we used to get there.
SPK_0: Yeah, so the, like, when
SPK_0: Christ was in ascension, it was not,
SPK_0: he was not called to apostle to sit and do
SPK_0: nothing. Like, he told them,
SPK_0: I will send you a spirit and go proselytize,
SPK_0: et cetera, et cetera, et cetera. So it's very much away
SPK_0: from being a,
SPK_0: from being patient in the way you described.
SPK_0: But to their direct question,
SPK_0: and it is a question, so when you will
SPK_0: come back to which, let's say, secularize
SPK_0: it in a modern way, when the world will be
SPK_0: perfect. Like, ultimately, when is this,
SPK_0: when does the story end, when it's
SPK_0: all great and good, and, like, when it's,
SPK_0: like, when it's going to happen like this.
SPK_0: Give me precise timing.
SPK_0: In that sense, you need to be patient.
SPK_0: And that's the trick. You need to do
SPK_0: somehow, and that's what
SPK_0: saints do.
SPK_0: You keep on moving, but you move with,
SPK_0: without expectation and without a deadline.
SPK_1: Exactly.
SPK_1: Which is, again, I am going to propose
SPK_1: that this is the
SPK_1: quality of being that the name
SPK_1: patient, in the ontological
SPK_1: sense, is.
SPK_1: And this is, I want to be subtle,
SPK_1: what I think is that one of the confusions that has
SPK_1: been wrought upon us,
SPK_1: what is this called? Lie.
SPK_1: The lie is
SPK_1: that patient
SPK_1: means nothing,
SPK_1: or do nothing, in all,
SPK_1: doing, lives in the category
SPK_1: of agent.
SPK_1: And what you are saying, the saint,
SPK_1: belies that.
SPK_0: He is beyond this contradiction.
SPK_1: He is beyond this contradiction, exactly.
SPK_1: He shows that, and we see this in the concept
SPK_1: of freedom. True freedom
SPK_1: only lies in fully surrendering to
SPK_1: God's will. This is a very confusing
SPK_1: thing to a modern mind.
SPK_0: And we're going to talk
SPK_0: about it.
SPK_1: But this is
SPK_1: the same idea.
SPK_1: It is the same idea. And so,
SPK_1: the fall, the fall is
SPK_1: the moment where we find ourselves
SPK_1: demoralized,
SPK_1: by something
SPK_1: about the nature of that contradiction
SPK_1: and the challenge of transcending
SPK_1: it, and tempted
SPK_1: precisely into
SPK_1: something that is easier to grab a hold
SPK_1: of, and is a simulacrum
SPK_1: of the real thing. Yes. This is both.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_0: But
SPK_0: it creates the imperative. And once
SPK_0: the imperative is created,
SPK_0: the story actually starts moving much
SPK_0: faster. Because once you are in this
SPK_0: imperative, very shortly
SPK_0: you came to the realization you don't need
SPK_0: God at all in the picture. The world
SPK_0: is still broken, but it doesn't
SPK_0: really matter why it is broken. Right.
SPK_0: And, again, here is a big claim. But I do
SPK_0: think it's, on a deep level,
SPK_0: it's still the statement, God, bad
SPK_0: God created a bad world. It's
SPK_0: still an act of subconscious rebellion.
SPK_0: But, again, subconscious
SPK_0: is a tricky topic, and I don't want to tell
SPK_0: people what they think. I'm just showing how this story
SPK_0: manifests. For example, let's say
SPK_0: that in the stories, like, dialectic
SPK_0: or the laws of nature,
SPK_0: and we're just upholding them, and we're
SPK_0: just moving them forward. Or, like, it's
SPK_0: an objective reality. Currently, the
SPK_0: world is built upon
SPK_0: this bad, broken class
SPK_0: system. We can remake it,
SPK_0: repurpose it
SPK_0: if I go in a different direction.
SPK_0: The world is built on scarcity.
SPK_0: The scarcity is bad. It's broken because
SPK_0: it is scarce. Let me find this
SPK_0: underlying principle and
SPK_0: fix it through this. And that's actually a good
SPK_0: point to bring it up. Why Gnosticism?
SPK_0: Because what is... We never talked
SPK_0: about Gnostic effectively. It's an idea of
SPK_0: Gnosis. It's a knowledge.
SPK_0: So, how it connects. There is
SPK_0: some kind of brokenness,
SPK_0: but there is a knowledge to fix
SPK_0: it. And you are the one to use
SPK_0: this knowledge to fix it.
SPK_1: So, it's in the direction of, say, the occult,
SPK_1: meaning...
SPK_0: Like, it's reason, but
SPK_0: simultaneously, it is occult.
SPK_1: There's a secret.
SPK_1: A secret to reality that you...
SPK_1: Those who are
SPK_1: not in on the secret are...
SPK_0: Are blind to it.
SPK_0: Are blind.
SPK_1: And sometimes,
SPK_1: it's... How do you say?
SPK_0: Not awakened?
SPK_1: Subordinate, or even
SPK_1: enslaved by their blindness.
SPK_1: You, perhaps,
SPK_1: can become one of those who is awakened
SPK_1: to it. And here's the secret.
SPK_1: The world is broken. There is
SPK_1: something at the root of the world, but there's
SPK_1: the other secret, which is very interesting,
SPK_1: which is that somehow, those
SPK_1: who can see that secret can fix it.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_1: And, in fact, must.
SPK_0: And, in fact, must. Yeah.
SPK_0: And that would not be possible,
SPK_0: like, why it is important. Like, it would not be
SPK_0: truly possible for the original
SPK_0: Gnostics, because they didn't have this optimism.
SPK_0: But it's possible once you experience
SPK_0: a Christian. So, it is an ape of
SPK_0: Christianity.
SPK_1: Yeah. Yeah, I can
SPK_1: see it almost, like, as a rearguard action
SPK_1: of the serpent.
SPK_0: Well, it's pretty crafty.
SPK_0: I don't know how I'm going to give a credit
SPK_0: when it's due. Because, such a
SPK_0: tempting challenge. Like,
SPK_0: and it makes sense. Yeah. And we will
SPK_0: talk about this later, but
SPK_0: it makes sense. Yeah.
SPK_0: If you make the assumption that
SPK_0: the world, that if you forget that
SPK_0: in Genesis the world is good, if you forget
SPK_0: the beginning, and that's why it is
SPK_0: the first stage. If you forget that
SPK_0: in the beginning, he made the
SPK_0: world as good, and saw that it is
SPK_0: good. He didn't saw
SPK_0: it as flawed. He didn't saw
SPK_0: it as bad.
SPK_1: Yeah. So, another
SPK_1: name that I'm playing with for this
SPK_1: world of Gnostic civilization
SPK_1: is the Luciferian
SPK_1: Gospel.
SPK_0: Effectively, yes.
SPK_1: The Gospel lands.
SPK_1: Now, Satan's in trouble.
SPK_1: But he has a
SPK_1: move. He knows that among people
SPK_1: the right move is to always tell
SPK_1: a particular quality of lie
SPK_1: that captures
SPK_1: an image of the truth
SPK_1: and provisions it
SPK_1: in a way that a part
SPK_1: of the human can
SPK_1: grasp and feel real, real
SPK_1: power?
SPK_1: I don't know.
SPK_1: What is it? It is,
SPK_0: well, it is power. It is knowledge.
SPK_0: It is pride.
SPK_0: What you said, like, a saint once said that
SPK_0: any heresy is
SPK_0: taking apart and
SPK_0: as a whole.
SPK_1: Yes. And that's
SPK_0: what it is. Because there is some brokenness
SPK_0: in this world. It's not fly.
SPK_0: Like, and it would be absolutely lie,
SPK_0: let's say, to come to a broken person
SPK_0: and to tell him, no, the world
SPK_0: is rainbow and perfect and, like, there is no
SPK_0: suffering. Like, come to a mother of a
SPK_0: sick child and tell her this story.
SPK_0: So, and
SPK_1: of course, the most powerful version
SPK_1: of that is to take a virtue
SPK_1: and tell the virtue that
SPK_1: by being itself it is the whole. Yes.
SPK_1: So, we want to go to reason
SPK_1: and say, reason, you and you alone
SPK_1: can save the world.
SPK_1: Courage, you and you alone.
SPK_0: It's a second conversation.
SPK_0: Just a heads up
SPK_0: those of you, but yeah.
SPK_0: But even the brokenness. The real
SPK_0: trick, I think, though, like, if we're speaking about
SPK_0: what is my understanding of the true
SPK_0: distinguishing between two views,
SPK_0: it is a distinction between internal
SPK_0: and external.
SPK_0: The phrase, the world is broken,
SPK_0: quote, quote,
SPK_0: liberates you from your
SPK_0: responsibility
SPK_0: in a way, from your
SPK_0: spiritual, ethical, true
SPK_0: ethical responsibility. It is
SPK_0: the world that is broken, not you.
SPK_1: Certainly it allows that move.
SPK_0: At least it allows this move.
SPK_1: Yeah. Which then means you will
SPK_1: take it, we should say. It's not the same
SPK_1: move. It allows the move and
SPK_1: you'll take it.
SPK_0: Yeah. If you
SPK_0: reach this point, most probably you
SPK_0: cannot take it. It works in a very
SPK_0: interesting way.
SPK_1: Ah, yes. I've been
SPK_1: there. I know this exactly.
SPK_1: Exactly.
SPK_0: How it works
SPK_0: a little bit psychologically,
SPK_0: like, and where
SPK_0: is the seed of truth? So, we arrive,
SPK_0: like, and this is, I want to reference a guy
SPK_0: I didn't saw in a long reference, it's this Russian
SPK_0: philosopher called Nismelov from the
SPK_0: late 19th century, not widely known,
SPK_0: but effectively he'd written a book
SPK_0: A Science of a Man. But what he points out
SPK_0: is true, that there is indeed
SPK_0: in any human, and it's what kind of drives
SPK_0: all movement in us,
SPK_0: this urging feeling that
SPK_0: we are not
SPK_0: exactly what we should
SPK_0: be. Like, I'm not
SPK_0: yet fully me.
SPK_0: And all
SPK_0: movement is effectively this
SPK_0: process of expansion of a human.
SPK_0: Like, it's me trying to grow
SPK_0: into me, which is simultaneously
SPK_0: expansion and
SPK_0: going in and going out in the same
SPK_0: time. Somehow it works. Like, it's
SPK_0: a paradox, but it's the way it works.
SPK_0: So, what happens? Why is the trick happens?
SPK_0: It is true. We all have this
SPK_0: feeling that there is something is
SPK_0: off. We all have this nudging feeling
SPK_0: that is off. But the trick
SPK_0: comes. It's not about you.
SPK_0: It's about the world.
SPK_0: It's about the laws of dialectics. It's about
SPK_0: the laws of society.
SPK_0: It's about the laws of nature.
SPK_0: It's about this. It's about that. It's not about
SPK_0: your heart. It's about literally anything
SPK_0: else but your heart.
SPK_0: And you have a knowledge
SPK_0: but you feel this
SPK_0: inadequacy. You have this tension.
SPK_0: Here is the knowledge to fix this tension.
SPK_1: Absolutely.
SPK_1: So, this is the
SPK_1: how do you say?
SPK_1: Let's take it step by step.
SPK_1: So,
SPK_1: obviously everybody who plays
SPK_1: in the technological world
SPK_1: participates
SPK_1: in this to some extent.
SPK_1: And again, there's
SPK_1: a simple
SPK_1: seduction, which
SPK_1: is that somebody invented
SPK_1: that bottle. And there was
SPK_1: an objective error in reality, which is
SPK_1: it's hard to carry water in your hands.
SPK_1: And Nessie.
SPK_1: So, somebody invented a bottle
SPK_1: and it worked. And the world became better.
SPK_1: Okay. So, here's the problem.
SPK_1: You can always do that. You can always say, hey,
SPK_1: it is really the case that there are objective
SPK_1: problems in the objective world and they are
SPK_1: subject to objective solutions
SPK_1: and it actually makes things better.
SPK_1: Which is all true.
SPK_1: So, this then becomes
SPK_1: for certain kinds of people.
SPK_1: I'm not sure if it's all people,
SPK_1: but for certain kinds of people, people like me
SPK_1: becomes a very seductive addiction
SPK_1: because I have a high degree
SPK_1: of efficacy in the objective
SPK_1: and a profound
SPK_1: lack in the subjective.
SPK_1: To put it another way, I have a lot
SPK_1: in the head and not so much in the heart.
SPK_1: Certainly by the age of 10.
SPK_0: Perfect example. And let's see
SPK_0: how a story came to manifest
SPK_0: as actually something which surrounds all of us
SPK_0: cities.
SPK_0: Let's plan a city. Let's design
SPK_0: a city. Let's design it the
SPK_0: most effective according to our current
SPK_0: knowledge.
SPK_0: And that's why you have beautiful cities
SPK_0: which were not designed and
SPK_0: very efficient but pretty ugly cities
SPK_0: when you design them.
SPK_0: And it's not to say that design
SPK_0: is bad, but it is this
SPK_0: excess which you
SPK_0: draw.
SPK_1: So then you get
SPK_1: this interesting build over time.
SPK_1: Layers. Those who are
SPK_1: the most strategic,
SPK_1: which is a combination of intelligence
SPK_1: and agency.
SPK_0: Both.
SPK_0: Say will.
SPK_1: I wouldn't agree. And will. Yeah, sure.
SPK_1: Intelligence, agency, and will.
SPK_1: They discover.
SPK_1: What is it? Give a man a fish.
SPK_1: Teach a man a fish.
SPK_1: Oh, nice.
SPK_1: Build the university called
SPK_1: Fishing Sciences and everybody
SPK_1: can fish. So not just the men.
SPK_1: Which is a strategic move.
SPK_1: How do I make change in the world?
SPK_1: How do I make the world a better place with more leverage?
SPK_1: How do I make more good
SPK_1: actually happen? Well,
SPK_1: I can fill up your water bottle
SPK_1: or I can carry more water in my hands.
SPK_1: Okay, well, that's stupid. I can
SPK_1: build the water bottle. Okay. I can build
SPK_1: a bottling factory that taps it.
SPK_1: Oh, okay. There's something that's happening there.
SPK_1: Now, iterate this generation after
SPK_1: generation. Those who orient
SPK_1: themselves towards the heart
SPK_1: maybe actually make very important success
SPK_1: for two or three
SPK_1: people. Those who orient themselves
SPK_1: after the head, a small
SPK_1: number, but enough, make
SPK_1: durable, significant, I mean, the word
SPK_1: significant, significant.
SPK_0: And durable
SPK_0: also.
SPK_1: Visible.
SPK_1: Visible. Or to use cognitive
SPK_1: science language, salient.
SPK_1: I can look at it and say, clean water
SPK_1: for lots of people. I can hang my
SPK_1: hat on that. So the next generation
SPK_1: comes and they look around. It becomes
SPK_1: increasingly self-evident.
SPK_1: Effective agency, doing things
SPK_1: right, making the world a better place,
SPK_1: participating as a human being in
SPK_1: the world, consists
SPK_1: either of
SPK_1: something like foolishness,
SPK_1: at the very local level, at the heart
SPK_1: level, or intelligence,
SPK_1: at the level of what is the most
SPK_1: effective strategic maneuver that has the
SPK_1: highest leverage to produce the highest good for the highest
SPK_1: number. I mean, even using the
SPK_1: what is it called? The language, the
SPK_1: particular spellcasting
SPK_1: of a whole subculture. Absolutely.
SPK_1: Effective altruism.
SPK_0: Effective
SPK_0: altruism. Creative destruction.
SPK_0: That's actually my favorite one, but
SPK_0: like something called the sword, but
SPK_0: absolutely right. And
SPK_0: it unfolds. It unfolds to a point
SPK_0: to a very dangerous point.
SPK_0: And I think ultimate dangerous point,
SPK_0: which we will go into later, but
SPK_0: this subject-object relationship,
SPK_0: it's very easy to start seeing
SPK_0: a fellow man as an object.
SPK_1: In part, increasingly
SPK_1: necessary.
SPK_0: And oh, that's
SPK_0: increasingly necessary.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_1: Absolutely. Maybe
SPK_1: we used this in previous conversation,
SPK_1: but I just call this society.
SPK_1: Society is
SPK_1: a context of human relationships
SPK_1: where your relationships are
SPK_1: always mediated by
SPK_1: something that is not human and
SPK_1: therefore always puts the other as an
SPK_1: object. I know this
SPK_1: when I went to go buy coffee the other moments ago.
SPK_1: I used a medium called money
SPK_1: to cause another human being
SPK_1: to have to do what I wanted them to do
SPK_1: without asking any real questions about who I was
SPK_1: or why I wanted coffee.
SPK_1: Give me the coffee. Go.
SPK_0: And very efficient.
SPK_1: And very efficient.
SPK_1: Lots of coffee.
SPK_0: Actually, very good. Very good coffee.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: Utility.
SPK_1: My utiles were very high.
SPK_0: But I hope you
SPK_0: guys see where
SPK_0: the danger lies. How this trick
SPK_0: necessarily in the end will
SPK_0: lead to pretty scary pitch.
SPK_1: Well, we'll probably spend
SPK_1: some time teasing out that necessities
SPK_1: because I assure you that it is not
SPK_1: obvious to most.
SPK_0: Okay. That's a good point. Another
SPK_0: final point I really wanted to bring
SPK_0: is a great story which actually
SPK_0: we don't really compare them often.
SPK_0: How the difference
SPK_0: between two worldviews, between broken
SPK_0: world and broken heart, effectively.
SPK_0: So there is a famous story
SPK_0: of St. Augustine's Confessions.
SPK_0: How he remembers how
SPK_0: he has stolen a pear
SPK_0: in a garden. And how
SPK_0: it leads to him to hold the liberation
SPK_0: confession, like change of heart, effectively.
SPK_0: And because it is effectively the first
SPK_0: diary put on a paper
SPK_0: in literature tradition,
SPK_0: we can still experience it. Like anybody
SPK_0: who read Augustine's Confession notices
SPK_0: this whole... It's a very powerful
SPK_0: scene. Anybody who didn't read it, I highly
SPK_0: encourage, go and read it.
SPK_0: But effectively, he accepts
SPK_0: responsibility. He accepts the change of heart.
SPK_0: He talks with the God. He talks with the Spirit.
SPK_0: So that's the story. That's what we call
SPK_0: the Orthodox story. Well, there
SPK_0: is effectively a very parallel
SPK_0: story written in Enlightenment time
SPK_0: by Jean-Jacques Rousseau.
SPK_0: When he mediates
SPK_0: on how he's stolen
SPK_0: a basket of asparagus.
SPK_0: And what he came to, let's say,
SPK_0: effectively, it's... Well, it wasn't
SPK_0: just me. It wasn't really me.
SPK_0: It was like, you know, objective laws of causality.
SPK_0: They led to this. It was effectively the cruel
SPK_0: society which made me do this thing.
SPK_0: But it was not about me.
SPK_0: And that's what actually you will necessarily
SPK_0: have in a world of efficiency.
SPK_0: It's not about you.
SPK_0: It's not about me. It's not about us.
SPK_0: It's about something we didn't
SPK_0: tweak right. Or somebody
SPK_0: who with the knowledge didn't tweak right.
SPK_0: Somebody who is not possessing the right
SPK_0: theory. The same semantic
SPK_0: structure works in the classical story of
SPK_0: dialectics. Like those who
SPK_0: realize dialectics now have a duty
SPK_0: to change the world according to the laws of dialectics
SPK_0: and could make everyone happy.
SPK_0: That's the natural of communist
SPK_0: manifesto. The same story about
SPK_0: liberal principles. Those who realize the truth
SPK_0: about, let's say, the human nature
SPK_0: according to the teachings of, let's say,
SPK_0: Locke, Hobbes, and other
SPK_0: guys. Or like, that's the true, like,
SPK_0: that's what the true meaning of human is.
SPK_0: Now you have a rule to spread democracy
SPK_0: and capitalism to the whole world.
SPK_0: And it is a sacred duty. Notice how also
SPK_0: it becomes a sacred duty. That's also very
SPK_0: interesting. You can't just, once you see this
SPK_0: knowledge and this story, you have
SPK_0: to act outwardly.
SPK_0: Whereas in the broken heart, once
SPK_0: you see your broken heart, you have to
SPK_0: act inwardly.
SPK_1: So there's
SPK_1: one arrow towards the truth
SPK_1: and two arrows towards the lie.
SPK_1: The arrow towards the truth is
SPK_1: you are
SPK_1: in fact objectively improving the world
SPK_1: in certain ways. We have to be careful with that.
SPK_1: It's very important
SPK_1: because we don't know how the world works
SPK_1: very well.
SPK_0: That's another
SPK_0: very important point.
SPK_1: The arrow towards the lie
SPK_1: is
SPK_1: this notion of pushing agency
SPK_1: into the objective.
SPK_1: And then the other one
SPK_1: with regard to the broken heart
SPK_1: is then pushing repentance
SPK_1: to therapy and coping.
SPK_1: So I, as Rousseau,
SPK_1: I rationalize
SPK_1: into the objective
SPK_1: or I cope
SPK_1: in the subjective. And some
SPK_1: combination of rationalization and cope
SPK_1: then causes me to be able to be
SPK_1: in the contradiction, in the reality
SPK_1: that I'm actually not really living in reality.
SPK_1: And then I can
SPK_1: convince myself to participate
SPK_1: in this movement that
SPK_1: has this ability to, ah,
SPK_1: you can see it, it's such a sad thing.
SPK_1: How can I actually be effective
SPK_1: in the world now? Now I'm now very
SPK_1: narrowly focused on a very narrow path, which is
SPK_1: I participate in this machine in society.
SPK_0: If I'm low,
SPK_0: I only discuss. If I'm high, I
SPK_0: create a machine that fixes, which makes,
SPK_0: no one else ever makes such a choice.
SPK_0: Let's give everybody a basket of asparagus.
SPK_1: Ah.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_1: Which is
SPK_1: to take the highest status position
SPK_1: in society. And maybe even
SPK_1: at the highest level, like a Napoleon,
SPK_1: to take a position which
SPK_1: is proximal to actually
SPK_1: participating in reality.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: And that's place. And that's
SPK_0: just to summarize, like, not
SPK_0: summarize, just to bring
SPK_0: it finally close to the home and
SPK_0: we do it all the time. The moment
SPK_0: I say, my goal is to make
SPK_0: a world a better place,
SPK_0: I'm already playing this game.
SPK_0: Yeah. The moment my
SPK_0: goal is to make this better,
SPK_0: like,
SPK_0: already has a danger in it.
SPK_0: Let's say, not always.
SPK_0: You can, but it already
SPK_0: has a danger in it. Because
SPK_0: truth be told, it shouldn't be your
SPK_0: motivation. Like, not shouldn't be, like,
SPK_0: that's another tricky part, and that's
SPK_0: where I will leave it as it is, but the only real,
SPK_0: real trick to avoid falling into this
SPK_0: trap is
SPK_0: not ever
SPK_0: setting up a goal to make a world
SPK_0: a better place. You might make it
SPK_0: a better place as an accident, but
SPK_0: not as a goal.
SPK_1: Yeah. Yeah.
SPK_1: And just to say, there's,
SPK_1: again, a number of different pieces.
SPK_1: One is this notion of the world.
SPK_1: Don't make the world a better
SPK_1: place.
SPK_1: You can make your house a better place.
SPK_1: Right? You can make your sandwich a better
SPK_1: sandwich. Feel free.
SPK_1: Run. As soon as you try to step
SPK_1: into making the world a better place,
SPK_1: you've stepped into something.
SPK_0: You've stepped into something.
SPK_1: It's as big and
SPK_1: confusing, so you better watch out.
SPK_1: Get out quick.
SPK_0: Kind of get out quick. Yeah.
SPK_1: And then, as you do that, you'll begin
SPK_1: to notice that
SPK_1: you're also then avoiding,
SPK_1: ah, that's so, you're avoiding repentance
SPK_1: and replacing
SPK_1: it with rationalization and
SPK_1: therapy.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: We will talk about later why you have to, but
SPK_0: I think it's a good place to make a stop.
SPK_1: Okay.