SPK_1: Okay, so we are in the middle, chronologically speaking, because it's the fourth episode.
SPK_1: Seven episodes, fourth is in the middle.
SPK_1: However, here is a good way to show the lack of chronology, if you want, or insufficiency
SPK_1: of chronology, because the beauty of truth is you can walk it in any order, almost.
SPK_1: So let's take our episodes.
SPK_1: Our previous episode was knowledge is power, and we arrived to it through starting with
SPK_1: the world is broken, reason is salvation, the knowledge is power.
SPK_1: So there is a logical change, if you didn't see, come and see.
SPK_1: But right now I just want to show that you can do these three lines in exact opposite
SPK_1: order, them remaining true, not just objectively, but causally as well.
SPK_1: If we start with that.
SPK_1: Knowledge is power, then gaining more knowledge makes you more and more and more powerful.
SPK_1: Then what, how we gain knowledge through reason, like naturally there's no other way to gain
SPK_1: knowledge, at least that's what we think at this point, we gain it through reason.
SPK_1: But if I'm getting through reason more and more and more power, it's very easy for me to start
SPK_1: feeling like I'm a chosen one.
SPK_1: If I'm a chosen one, I am a saved one.
SPK_1: So that's how reason becomes salvation.
SPK_1: So by acclimating and increasing.
SPK_1: By the quantity of my reason or the fruits of my reason, I'm becoming more and more saved.
SPK_1: But if I'm saved, isn't it my duty to become a savior and to become a savior of the world, which for
SPK_1: this to have to be broken.
SPK_1: So for me to be a savior of the world, it has to be broken naturally and necessary.
SPK_1: So reversing this whole line, but still the beauty of causality flows both directions from past to
SPK_1: present, from present since the past.
SPK_1: And in itself, it is a paradox.
SPK_1: So yes, I wanted to start the fourth episode with a paradox because we're going to spend a lot of time
SPK_1: on paradoxes in it.
SPK_1: The paradox, the title is deal as trust, or deal is trust.
SPK_1: And to start it, I actually want to go back into the desert because my, let's say, spirit from which
SPK_1: I'm starting this story is...
SPK_1: The second temptation of Christ in the desert, it is a temptation, which I remember, for those who
SPK_1: don't remember, so the devil puts Christ on top of the roof building, on a temple building and suggests
SPK_1: him go jump down and the angels, like aren't you the son of effectively God, the angels will take you
SPK_1: and you won't be harmed.
SPK_1: What does it mean?
SPK_1: It means power over miracle.
SPK_1: And that's the streaky hidden part.
SPK_1: Because we've been so much on rationalism and knowledge.
SPK_1: But there is a tricky part I want to immediately throw into the picture.
SPK_1: It's the fact that the founders of the scientific worldview, if you go through their library, you will find
SPK_1: that the majority of their books was not on science and physics, but was on occult and alchemy.
SPK_1: And there is this hidden relationship between, for some reason, science, reason, light and occult.
SPK_1: And effectively, it all comes to the deal.
SPK_1: And that's my argument.
SPK_1: That's what I offer you.
SPK_1: I offer you this observation that what the second temptation is, or what is the hidden
SPK_1: agnostic temptation is, because on the surface, it's about reason, but in its heart, there
SPK_1: is a deeper truth.
SPK_1: It is about a deal, ultimate deal.
SPK_1: And deal is a modus of avaperandi.
SPK_1: What's the difference between, let's say, faith in invisible and deal with an invisible?
SPK_1: Well, you can control the second.
SPK_1: At least you believe you're controlling the second.
SPK_1: You don't need to have faith.
SPK_1: You need to have knowledge.
SPK_1: It can be knowledge in visible.
SPK_1: It can be knowledge in invisible.
SPK_1: But it is knowledge, and knowledge creates an opportunity for a deal, for a very particular
SPK_1: kind of relationship.
SPK_1: That's the thing.
SPK_1: We can call about individualism.
SPK_1: We can speak about rationality.
SPK_1: But very quickly, we...
SPK_1: In our experience, I'm not completely alone, and if I'm even scientifically honest enough,
SPK_1: visible is not everything.
SPK_1: There is a lot of uncontrollables in my life.
SPK_1: How do I react with them?
SPK_1: How do I relate with them without challenging my fundamental assumption?
SPK_1: And that's a very low-hanging, but very addictive fruit through deals.
SPK_1: I can make a deal with them.
SPK_1: I can make a deal with the unknowable.
SPK_1: I can make a deal with the invisible.
SPK_1: I can box them.
SPK_1: And why it is comfortable for me?
SPK_1: Because then I don't need to trust.
SPK_0: Okay, so I'm going to come from a different direction.
SPK_1: That's what I'm here for.
SPK_0: What I want to do is I want to cast some light on this question, because as you say,
SPK_0: we're now in a very...
SPK_1: Murky water.
SPK_0: Murky water.
SPK_0: Exactly.
SPK_0: So let's talk about Hobbes.
SPK_0: Hobbes.
SPK_0: I think we may have talked about Hobbes already.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_0: We'll talk about Hobbes again.
SPK_0: Because we have in the context...
SPK_0: He's important.
SPK_0: In the context of the Thirty Years' War, we have the actual breakdown of trust.
SPK_0: In fact, we have a double breakdown of trust.
SPK_1: Both vertical and horizontal.
SPK_0: Right.
SPK_0: We have a practical breakdown of trust between, and we have a demoralization of trust vertically.
SPK_0: Or to put it very simply, this thing ain't going to work.
SPK_0: This church thing, this God thing, it can't seem to resolve the trouble.
SPK_1: It might be somewhere here, but it doesn't.
SPK_0: Practically speaking, everybody's dying.
SPK_0: And everybody seems to think they've got God on their side.
SPK_0: That seems to be the center of the problem.
SPK_0: They seem to think they've got God on their side.
SPK_0: So clearly having God is not going to solve the problem.
SPK_0: We got to go somewhere else.
SPK_0: Which is to say, we will find a way to make deals with each other.
SPK_0: We will shift.
SPK_0: We will not be in communion with each other.
SPK_0: That seems to be insolvable.
SPK_0: By the way, still seems to be the case.
SPK_0: And we'll try to resolve...
SPK_1: But we won't even try.
SPK_1: And that's an important shift.
SPK_0: Yeah, well, we're going to give up on it.
SPK_0: We're going to punt.
SPK_0: Punt on that whole problem.
SPK_0: Sorry, punt is an American...
SPK_0: You get it?
SPK_0: Okay.
SPK_0: And we'll resolve to deals.
SPK_0: And the deals will work this way.
SPK_0: We have a good word for it.
SPK_0: Win-win.
SPK_0: Hey, let's stop fighting.
SPK_0: Let's put down our arms.
SPK_0: If you stop fighting and I stop fighting,
SPK_0: then we can actually both win.
SPK_0: For example, you'll be able to grow food,
SPK_0: and you won't be starving to death.
SPK_0: Me too.
SPK_0: I like that.
SPK_0: How about you?
SPK_0: Now we're negotiating.
SPK_0: So we're being able to stitch something together
SPK_0: on the basis of deals.
SPK_1: And guess how you're doing it.
SPK_1: On the basis of what?
SPK_1: Reason.
SPK_1: Reasonable people don't solve problems through violence.
SPK_0: That's right.
SPK_0: Can we reason together?
SPK_1: Can we just be civilized?
SPK_0: Right.
SPK_0: Can we be civilized?
SPK_0: Yes, that's right.
SPK_0: And there's a way for us to find an answer.
SPK_0: If we just sit down and we talk it through,
SPK_0: we'll find a reasonable solution.
SPK_1: Notice we don't have to trust each other.
SPK_1: Let's talk it.
SPK_0: It's not reasonable to ask for that.
SPK_0: I mean, come on.
SPK_0: He's a fucking German.
SPK_0: You can't trust a German.
SPK_0: You can't trust a Han.
SPK_0: But here's what you can trust.
SPK_0: You can trust he has self-interest.
SPK_0: And his self-interest,
SPK_0: if I can make sure that he has his self-interest in mind,
SPK_0: I got my self-interest in mind,
SPK_0: we can find a deal on the basis of that.
SPK_0: That I can trust.
SPK_1: It's as I tell myself I can trust.
SPK_1: Well, of course.
SPK_0: You can hear the tone of my voice.
SPK_1: Yeah, I can hear the tone.
SPK_0: That was a convincing tone.
SPK_1: You're very convincing.
SPK_0: That was a conspiratorial and a con man tone.
SPK_0: There's something about that.
SPK_0: The rationalization and therapy is still very deeply there.
SPK_0: What I know is that I've actually made a one-way trip out of reality.
SPK_0: I'm no longer actually living in communion.
SPK_0: I'm no longer actually living in the real world.
SPK_0: I'm living in something which is...
SPK_1: Simulacrum.
SPK_0: Simulacrum.
SPK_0: Right.
SPK_0: I've exchanged survival,
SPK_0: I've exchanged life for mere survival.
SPK_1: Yes.
SPK_0: But four or five generations hence,
SPK_0: my great-grandchildren have forgotten that life was ever a thing.
SPK_1: And yet they didn't.
SPK_1: And yet every generation they didn't.
SPK_1: That's why you need an every generation creating,
SPK_1: create an extra layer of simulacrum to keep this energy tamed.
SPK_0: Yes, very good.
SPK_0: Keep going.
SPK_0: Tell me more.
SPK_1: Well, that's very easy.
SPK_1: Like that's like historical example just showcases this.
SPK_1: Like, so again,
SPK_1: we start with 30 years war with cops,
SPK_1: which honestly one day I will do a series with you on it,
SPK_1: on him.
SPK_1: But in a nutshell,
SPK_1: rational order,
SPK_1: like we can all agree,
SPK_1: like survival is good.
SPK_1: So to stop this war against all of against all,
SPK_1: we create a modern simulacrum of God.
SPK_1: We will call him state.
SPK_1: I mean, not icon of God,
SPK_1: but simulacrum of God.
SPK_1: Very important.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_1: Mechanical God.
SPK_1: Artificial God.
SPK_1: Like something we will pretend to believe in.
SPK_1: We don't even have truly believe in,
SPK_1: but we need to act.
SPK_1: As if we believe in it.
SPK_1: And for those who don't,
SPK_1: we will do propaganda or violence,
SPK_1: like lie or violence,
SPK_1: classical state apparatus,
SPK_1: like very efficient.
SPK_1: Like here comes many more than university idea.
SPK_1: A lot like who prepare homes and guys who will actually go and do the
SPK_1: censorship,
SPK_1: like to keep this order,
SPK_1: like,
SPK_1: not like it haven't been happening on its own before hops or before
SPK_1: modernity,
SPK_1: but it's never been happening on such a purpose in itself,
SPK_1: like purpose in itself.
SPK_1: That's important difference.
SPK_1: Okay.
SPK_1: And then we will have a civilized century.
SPK_1: Yes,
SPK_1: we will have barbarians.
SPK_1: We're going to fight with,
SPK_1: but they are barbarians.
SPK_1: It's fine.
SPK_1: Like between us,
SPK_1: we will be civilized.
SPK_1: And we actually were civilized for a while.
SPK_1: Let's,
SPK_1: there is this very famous example of this rational utopia.
SPK_1: Effectively,
SPK_1: we are even violence for civilized.
SPK_1: It's this battle battle of Fontainebleau.
SPK_1: Like it's middle of the 18th century.
SPK_1: And let's say French versus English men are starting like this line order.
SPK_1: They're coming closest to a firing direction.
SPK_1: And officers are getting out of the line and like,
SPK_1: noble gentlemen,
SPK_1: we give you the right of a first shot.
SPK_1: And say,
SPK_1: oh,
SPK_1: no,
SPK_1: no.
SPK_1: It's our honor to give it to us.
SPK_1: And basically there is this very famous scene,
SPK_1: like very tamed,
SPK_1: like looks like this reason will last forever.
SPK_1: Like in 40 years,
SPK_1: revolution in France happens.
SPK_1: And that's what I mean.
SPK_1: There is some in this story.
SPK_1: There is some big lies that it can tame.
SPK_1: What it cannot tame.
SPK_1: And this untamed keeps surfacing.
SPK_1: Like more importantly,
SPK_1: like here is a tricky part because knowledge is power.
SPK_1: You can get some knowledge,
SPK_1: some deals,
SPK_1: maybe through deals,
SPK_1: maybe this is how to use this untamed to destroy your enemy.
SPK_1: Let's say if I know how to organize a revolution in any given community.
SPK_1: Ooh.
SPK_1: So it gives me a lot of power,
SPK_1: really a lot of power.
SPK_1: And notice how subtle and invisible this power is.
SPK_1: I don't even need to kill people.
SPK_1: I will just give some idea here,
SPK_1: some money here,
SPK_1: and you will destroy yourself on your own.
SPK_1: My hands are clean.
SPK_1: This is the temptation.
SPK_1: Ultimately,
SPK_1: and that's what,
SPK_1: again,
SPK_1: who is coming to play for this rational utopia to exist.
SPK_1: We actually needed to value survival above all,
SPK_1: but we don't.
SPK_1: We value power.
SPK_1: I value my survival overall,
SPK_1: but not your survival.
SPK_0: Right.
SPK_0: Well,
SPK_0: the image is,
SPK_0: as I said,
SPK_0: I value my survival.
SPK_0: You value your survival.
SPK_0: And we're going to create a story that that will work.
SPK_0: And there's some equilibrium that we can establish between the two of us.
SPK_0: But of course,
SPK_0: knowledge is power.
SPK_0: We are both pursuing disequilibrium.
SPK_0: I'm always looking for asymmetry.
SPK_0: And as soon as I achieve asymmetry,
SPK_0: there's no other way around it.
SPK_0: There's no possibility other than I will now begin to encroach upon your interests.
SPK_0: By sheer necessity.
SPK_0: The equilibrium can't contain that.
SPK_1: Because knowledge is power.
SPK_1: You can't have a knowledge and not use it.
SPK_1: Come on.
SPK_0: Yeah,
SPK_0: exactly.
SPK_0: And knowledge,
SPK_0: by the way,
SPK_0: has this really interesting characteristic that it also is impossible to keep.
SPK_1: Yes.
SPK_0: So it will disseminate.
SPK_1: It will trickle.
SPK_1: Especially being,
SPK_1: I mean,
SPK_1: classic example on this story is the mess armies.
SPK_1: Like,
SPK_1: basically,
SPK_1: how the story develops.
SPK_1: So you have French,
SPK_1: like,
SPK_1: why the French army was so successful.
SPK_1: And then you have,
SPK_1: for example,
SPK_1: in revolutionary war.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: Many people don't know it.
SPK_1: It's not because they had,
SPK_1: okay,
SPK_1: they had a genius of Napoleon,
SPK_1: but it was not just the story.
SPK_1: Part of the story of the genius behind Napoleon,
SPK_1: that was,
SPK_1: he was simply capable of mobilize masses of people.
SPK_1: No comparative army to French army could simply mobilize people into the army.
SPK_1: Because they didn't have a story to do it.
SPK_1: Because French created the story of a nation.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: So,
SPK_1: and if you're a part of a nation,
SPK_1: please go and die for your nation.
SPK_1: Before,
SPK_1: like,
SPK_1: even this thought for us is self-evident.
SPK_1: Point aside,
SPK_1: no,
SPK_1: not at all.
SPK_1: For most part of the history,
SPK_1: there are those who fight and those who don't.
SPK_1: It's not my job.
SPK_1: Okay,
SPK_1: a king has a problem with another king.
SPK_1: If it's,
SPK_1: there are issues when it becomes my story.
SPK_1: When it's a matter of faith,
SPK_1: there is a truly a matter of survival of everyone.
SPK_1: Maybe.
SPK_1: But most of the time,
SPK_1: it's him dealing with this guy.
SPK_1: Like,
SPK_1: he uses his guys whom he pays,
SPK_1: whom I serve for this purpose.
SPK_1: But I am part of my services to being protected.
SPK_1: But the idea that everyone needs to go and die in a war,
SPK_1: it's a radical modern idea.
SPK_1: And it's only possible on the simulacrum of a nation.
SPK_1: And simulacrum of a nation is a technology,
SPK_1: which is a very efficient technology.
SPK_1: You can create a nation out of anybody.
SPK_1: We can create a nation out of,
SPK_1: I don't know,
SPK_1: the people living in Greenville.
SPK_1: Sorry.
SPK_1: Spoilers.
SPK_1: But it's a matter of technology,
SPK_1: time,
SPK_1: money,
SPK_1: but ultimately it's not hard.
SPK_1: Like,
SPK_1: in an agnostic world,
SPK_1: it's a matter of capacity.
SPK_1: Nice.
SPK_0: Yeah,
SPK_0: simulation of a nation.
SPK_0: Very good.
SPK_0: Yeah,
SPK_0: like,
SPK_1: no problem at all.
SPK_1: Like,
SPK_1: a thought here
SPK_1: and a little bit of material interest there.
SPK_1: Like,
SPK_1: honestly,
SPK_1: there are lots of actual studies and papers on,
SPK_1: like,
SPK_1: modern nationalisms were created.
SPK_1: Like,
SPK_1: they didn't emerge.
SPK_1: They all were created
SPK_1: and we know names of people who created them.
SPK_1: That's the nicest part about it.
SPK_1: But,
SPK_1: where I'm going,
SPK_1: back to France.
SPK_1: So,
SPK_1: they created this model
SPK_1: and it was a shock for Europe,
SPK_1: especially for one European country,
SPK_1: particularly Russia.
SPK_1: Because they really didn't like being humiliated militarily.
SPK_1: It happened to be that military was a part of the whole of their identity.
SPK_0: And that's my thing.
SPK_1: And it's my thing.
SPK_1: And after this whole Napoleonic war story,
SPK_1: like,
SPK_1: yes,
SPK_1: Napoleon gets defeated,
SPK_1: like,
SPK_1: with many different steps in the story,
SPK_1: but he gets defeated.
SPK_1: But the principle of nationalist army remains.
SPK_1: The gin is out of the bottle.
SPK_1: That's clearly,
SPK_1: if you can mobilize this many people,
SPK_1: it gives you power,
SPK_1: advantage,
SPK_1: power,
SPK_1: rage.
SPK_1: The problem is how to make these people capable of fighting,
SPK_1: how to make these good soldiers.
SPK_1: Like,
SPK_1: how to make such masses of people good soldiers
SPK_1: before you needed to train them for life.
SPK_1: Well,
SPK_1: nowadays you cannot train them for life.
SPK_1: And truth be told,
SPK_1: you don't really need to train them for life
SPK_1: because,
SPK_1: you know,
SPK_1: guns and bullets and like,
SPK_1: it's much easier,
SPK_1: much quicker.
SPK_1: But something is missing.
SPK_1: Mass evasion is missing.
SPK_1: How to make them willing to die and mass for something.
SPK_1: They have this power within them.
SPK_1: They're still looking for some meaning.
SPK_1: We'll give them meaning.
SPK_1: And that's the famous Fichte speeches to German nation,
SPK_1: which led to the creation of modern education system.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: And that's in 50 years,
SPK_1: we have this famous writing
SPK_1: that it was a Prussian teacher
SPK_1: who destroyed an Austrian army.
SPK_1: But then everybody else started copying it.
SPK_1: Welcome World War One.
SPK_0: So we have two,
SPK_0: two principles.
SPK_0: This is get down to like really,
SPK_0: really deep principles.
SPK_0: So one principle is arms race.
SPK_0: Okay.
SPK_0: So one is that in the context of knowledge is power.
SPK_0: And in the context of,
SPK_0: of the equilibrium necessary for deals to work,
SPK_0: lest there be a renegotiation,
SPK_0: you have an arms race.
SPK_0: And,
SPK_0: and everybody is on the run.
SPK_0: And by the way,
SPK_0: we're at the tail,
SPK_0: we're,
SPK_0: we're the recipient of now several hundred,
SPK_0: maybe thousands of years of arms race.
SPK_0: And the arms race,
SPK_0: we should be very clear,
SPK_0: is across every possible front.
SPK_1: Yes.
SPK_1: The technical arms race is the surface level.
SPK_1: The real arms race,
SPK_1: the real one is cognitive.
SPK_1: Just to be clear,
SPK_1: it's about the real technologies are about not just giving people guns.
SPK_1: It's making enough number of willing people to go with this gun in French.
SPK_0: Right.
SPK_0: Okay.
SPK_0: So that's one.
SPK_0: Um,
SPK_0: and then the second direction has to do with this notion of super salience.
SPK_0: All right.
SPK_0: So if,
SPK_0: if you're,
SPK_0: if you're orienting people towards a deal,
SPK_0: right,
SPK_0: or survival rather than life,
SPK_0: what I have to do is I have to give you a really strong hit of a part of the whole.
SPK_0: And the example that I've used for a long time is the jolly rancher or cotton candy.
SPK_0: Okay.
SPK_0: So a jolly rancher tastes superficially like an apple in the dimension of sweetness.
SPK_0: It tastes a lot more like an apple is much sweeter than an apple in the dimension of say anything vaguely good for you.
SPK_0: It's zero.
SPK_0: And this is,
SPK_0: this is the essence of the super salient.
SPK_0: But the problem is that the fabric of the deal is based upon the logic of the super salient.
SPK_0: And the problem with the super salient is you get,
SPK_0: it's an addiction cycle.
SPK_0: You have to keep taking a bigger and bigger hit because you're getting further and further away.
SPK_0: There's a reciprocal closure of you,
SPK_0: yourself,
SPK_0: every step you take in the direction of the super salient,
SPK_0: reduce blind spots,
SPK_0: produces blind spots in your larger wholeness.
SPK_1: That's how we end up with people.
SPK_1: Sorry,
SPK_1: recent conversation.
SPK_1: Why Indians are not afraid of our tariffs.
SPK_1: I'm sorry.
SPK_1: It's just,
SPK_1: it should be.
SPK_1: Why is there not like the super salience actually becomes bigger and bigger.
SPK_1: That's a problem.
SPK_1: And that's the problem.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_0: And the dynamic loop between the,
SPK_0: the kind of society that you're living in,
SPK_0: or let's just say the word society and the addictive cycle of super salience and the decline of discernment or the ability to make choices in the basis of a subtle,
SPK_0: a whole has a trajectory to it.
SPK_0: And this trajectory has an inescapable direction towards death.
SPK_0: I don't know who coined the term death works.
SPK_0: It may come from actually the Protestant tradition,
SPK_0: but this is a death work.
SPK_0: These are things that are intrinsically moving you towards death.
SPK_0: But each step is very difficult not to take because each step has that local hit that,
SPK_0: that separates your salience from your relevance.
SPK_0: And gives you something that you cannot.
SPK_1: And quantitatively it makes every with each step to go back is becoming exponentially harder.
SPK_0: Exponentially harder.
SPK_0: And the,
SPK_0: the easiest example of this is just cocaine addiction.
SPK_0: Because it hits you right in the dopamine.
SPK_0: It hits you right in the,
SPK_0: in the way of knowing whether or not you're winning.
SPK_0: If to use that term from the internet.
SPK_0: The problem with a cocaine addict is that taking a step back feels like losing.
SPK_0: It feels like a bad choice.
SPK_0: In a very comprehensive way.
SPK_0: Right?
SPK_0: It feels like being sick.
SPK_0: It feels like being dumb.
SPK_0: Right?
SPK_0: It feels like a bunch of things that are not good.
SPK_0: Rationalization kicks in.
SPK_0: Therapy kicks in and you're stuck.
SPK_0: And so the deal is ultimately an addiction cycle.
SPK_1: It is an addiction cycle,
SPK_1: but it's not just an addiction cycle.
SPK_1: The deal is also a lie from the very beginning.
SPK_1: And we said about it like on some levels,
SPK_1: like,
SPK_1: but you also mentioned one part of win-win,
SPK_1: but it's,
SPK_1: it's a very particular type of win-win.
SPK_1: And I will borrow it actually from my producer's father,
SPK_1: like,
SPK_1: and his street wisdom in Russian barracks in like mid-Soviet Union.
SPK_1: And this wisdom sounds like this.
SPK_1: In any deal,
SPK_1: there are two parties.
SPK_1: One is a moron and another is a crook.
SPK_1: If one were not moron and another were not the crook,
SPK_1: there would be no deal.
SPK_0: That's very fucking harsh indeed.
SPK_1: But it is true.
SPK_1: Like,
SPK_1: sorry,
SPK_1: I'm talking to a man who managed to buy,
SPK_1: from a nation who managed to buy an island for a necklace.
SPK_0: Quite right.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: So let's see.
SPK_0: Man.
SPK_0: So it's interesting.
SPK_0: I'm actually finding myself struggling with orthodox microeconomics.
SPK_1: It's a struggling point.
SPK_1: It is completely different.
SPK_1: We didn't figure it out theoretically yet ourselves.
SPK_1: Some are pathetic elements,
SPK_1: but it is,
SPK_1: it becomes so tricky.
SPK_1: We don't even want to think about it.
SPK_0: This is the key.
SPK_0: The key is actually is this conversation about salience.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: So if I foreground a need,
SPK_0: then a deal can be had at the cost of things that I am backgrounding into blind spots.
SPK_0: So what happens is I,
SPK_0: and we can see that again,
SPK_0: the local global problem,
SPK_0: the now future problem.
SPK_0: So how about you become a factory worker?
SPK_0: You can feed your family.
SPK_0: Okay.
SPK_0: You can do what you've been had,
SPK_0: but what's happening is you're now on a trajectory of increasingly dependent,
SPK_0: increasing dependence on society,
SPK_0: increasing necessity.
SPK_0: And it seemed like a free deal in the beginning,
SPK_0: but the point is,
SPK_1: Oh,
SPK_1: no,
SPK_1: everybody,
SPK_1: our liberal friend,
SPK_1: you signed this contract voluntarily.
SPK_1: Every time it's a free choice.
SPK_1: It's a free deal.
SPK_1: Every time,
SPK_1: not as long,
SPK_1: like they will say,
SPK_1: if it is a reason,
SPK_1: objective coercion,
SPK_1: then it is of course bad.
SPK_1: Like,
SPK_1: obviously if you're having a gun to your head,
SPK_1: it's not a real deal.
SPK_1: Well,
SPK_1: here is an ugly truth.
SPK_1: Any deal is with the gun to your head.
SPK_0: This is so intense.
SPK_0: So this is,
SPK_0: this is the place right here.
SPK_0: This line is the line where definitely America,
SPK_0: probably the entire West just like rejects.
SPK_0: So maybe we should spend time on it.
SPK_0: This is,
SPK_1: this is a very simple level.
SPK_1: Like at least there is one thing in the deal.
SPK_1: Why it's more than a crook.
SPK_1: And on a very practical level,
SPK_1: there is always an asymmetry of information.
SPK_0: Well,
SPK_0: let me make simple.
SPK_0: My daughter wants to make a lemonade stand.
SPK_0: She wants to make lemonade and sell it to people who want lemonade.
SPK_0: Where's the crook?
SPK_0: Where's the moron?
SPK_0: She goes out,
SPK_0: somebody thirsty and hot.
SPK_1: Ironically in this story,
SPK_1: I just wouldn't call it a deal.
SPK_1: Okay.
SPK_0: Keep going.
SPK_1: you can say,
SPK_1: let's say if your daughter,
SPK_1: that's a good point,
SPK_1: actually point.
SPK_1: It's thirsty.
SPK_1: Like it's a thirst season.
SPK_1: I can charge three times more and exploit the current thirst of a people.
SPK_1: Then she's a crook.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: No question.
SPK_1: If it's just an expression of her art that we can run away from.
SPK_0: Very nice.
SPK_0: So what happened by doing that?
SPK_0: You actually played a really nice cause there's tension,
SPK_0: right?
SPK_0: Cause what happens is now I'm going to be hoisting.
SPK_0: My own petard is our slide.
SPK_0: So the liberal architecture is going to try to say,
SPK_0: well,
SPK_0: what about right here?
SPK_0: What about where it's a fair deal?
SPK_0: I'm going to get my corner term,
SPK_0: a fair,
SPK_1: but it's not here.
SPK_1: That's the thing.
SPK_1: It's a fair deal is underpinned by face and trust.
SPK_1: I trust your daughter not to exploit.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: This is the cut flower.
SPK_0: This is the degeneracy problem.
SPK_0: If it is an expression of her art.
SPK_0: Ah,
SPK_1: yeah.
SPK_0: Okay.
SPK_0: So hold on.
SPK_0: Let me back up.
SPK_0: I was in a conversation,
SPK_0: gosh,
SPK_0: 20 years ago with a gentleman who was 20 years,
SPK_0: my senior or something like that.
SPK_0: Both of us had been in entrepreneurs and we just ended up,
SPK_0: having this conversation about the moral decline of the business world.
SPK_0: And he said,
SPK_0: I remember a time when if something wasn't right,
SPK_0: you wouldn't do it.
SPK_0: Even if you would make more money doing it.
SPK_1: And he said,
SPK_1: you have no reason not to.
SPK_0: Well,
SPK_0: hold on.
SPK_0: He remembered that time when he was young,
SPK_0: that was how it worked.
SPK_1: Even back then he had face,
SPK_1: not reason.
SPK_1: Yeah,
SPK_0: exactly.
SPK_0: This is a point.
SPK_0: He said,
SPK_0: but he remembered in his life,
SPK_0: in his lifetime,
SPK_0: in his career,
SPK_0: a movement from that to me.
SPK_0: Think of it.
SPK_0: Remember what the architecture was?
SPK_0: Well,
SPK_0: it went through a series of steps,
SPK_0: but the end step was something as long as it wasn't,
SPK_0: as long as it was legal,
SPK_0: even if it was wrong,
SPK_0: that was irrelevant.
SPK_0: The question of wrong is irrelevant.
SPK_0: The question is,
SPK_0: does it make me profit?
SPK_0: Is it profit?
SPK_0: And is it legal?
SPK_1: Not,
SPK_1: should I do it?
SPK_1: Can I do it?
SPK_0: The next step.
SPK_1: Tell me,
SPK_1: can I do it?
SPK_0: So I pick up the narrative there and I say,
SPK_0: okay,
SPK_0: so I entered into the world roughly there.
SPK_0: And during my tenure,
SPK_0: it was as long as the cost of being caught is less than the benefit of running the risk.
SPK_0: Do it.
SPK_1: Yep.
SPK_0: All right.
SPK_0: That's the,
SPK_0: that's the degeneracy cycle.
SPK_1: Example.
SPK_1: If my profit is 500 millions and the city,
SPK_1: and the city fine is a hundred million,
SPK_1: do it.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: If the city fine is a billion,
SPK_0: but my chance of getting caught is one out of five,
SPK_0: do it.
SPK_0: Right.
SPK_0: So it's pure,
SPK_0: you know,
SPK_0: the pure,
SPK_0: as you say,
SPK_0: as soon as you are in the regime of the deal,
SPK_0: right?
SPK_0: We're talking about that now is not as an entire architecture where,
SPK_0: where the,
SPK_0: the governing logic is the governing logic of the rational.
SPK_0: As soon as you're in the regime of the deal,
SPK_0: you are on a downward slope.
SPK_0: This is CS Lewis,
SPK_0: right?
SPK_0: The,
SPK_0: the,
SPK_0: the cut flower.
SPK_0: You are sliding from a capital of a store of value that you did not earn and could not build.
SPK_0: And you were inevitably sliding into complete chaos and,
SPK_0: and everybody killing everybody else in the worst imaginable way.
SPK_0: I'm being hyperbolic to break,
SPK_0: make the point.
SPK_0: This is trust.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: And,
SPK_0: and we,
SPK_0: we're now,
SPK_0: I literally am part of a group that came to me with the name,
SPK_0: the trust apocalypse.
SPK_0: Hey,
SPK_0: we are out of trust.
SPK_0: Trust is no longer part of our world.
SPK_0: What happens?
SPK_0: Right?
SPK_0: And the answer is the apocalypse in,
SPK_0: in the sort of ordinary sense,
SPK_0: not in the revelation sense,
SPK_0: although perhaps that too,
SPK_0: we'll see.
SPK_1: You cut too many deals.
SPK_0: You cut too many deals.
SPK_0: That's right.
SPK_0: Then once you cut too many deals,
SPK_0: you cut too many deals.
SPK_0: There will be hell to pay.
SPK_1: That's a beautiful way of putting it.
SPK_1: But the reason why that's,
SPK_1: let me go back to the beginning.
SPK_1: Why do I even want them?
SPK_1: If it's such a scary picture,
SPK_1: why do I would want to go into this realm?
SPK_0: Right.
SPK_1: Well,
SPK_1: because it gives me power and liberates me from,
SPK_1: I think it liberates me if I have it because trust is a problem.
SPK_1: It's mysterious.
SPK_0: Okay.
SPK_1: The nature of trust is not rational.
SPK_1: Trust is irrational.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_1: Okay.
SPK_1: Some people say,
SPK_1: well,
SPK_1: I can show you studies that say that the more trust is a society,
SPK_1: is it like,
SPK_1: so it's a rational choice.
SPK_1: Okay.
SPK_1: I can't even tell you it's a rational choice,
SPK_1: but trust itself is irrational.
SPK_0: Right,
SPK_0: right,
SPK_0: right.
SPK_1: Like.
SPK_0: It is very reasonable to trust.
SPK_0: Trust is not rational.
SPK_1: Yes.
SPK_1: So that's a problem.
SPK_1: So.
SPK_0: Oh,
SPK_0: just to be clear,
SPK_0: it's more fundamental than reason.
SPK_0: This is the key thing.
SPK_0: This is a thing people lose.
SPK_0: Reason,
SPK_0: as we've talked about,
SPK_0: is not the bottom of the stack of reality.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: Here,
SPK_0: trust is closest to the bottom.
SPK_0: Not quite,
SPK_0: but close.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: And the problem,
SPK_1: you need to learn to trust,
SPK_1: trust.
SPK_1: Like,
SPK_1: it's all this concept like faith,
SPK_1: belief,
SPK_1: vulnerability,
SPK_1: because,
SPK_1: for example,
SPK_1: spouses.
SPK_1: You ideally trust your spouse.
SPK_1: You don't cut a deal with your spouse.
SPK_1: If you start cutting deals with your spouse,
SPK_1: there is no communion between two.
SPK_1: And then there is,
SPK_1: there is no communions,
SPK_1: and it becomes a very partnership,
SPK_1: business partnership.
SPK_1: When,
SPK_1: when,
SPK_1: inevitably,
SPK_1: the power,
SPK_1: symmetry,
SPK_1: gap,
SPK_1: line,
SPK_1: like,
SPK_1: how can exploitation here,
SPK_1: can I get more of this?
SPK_1: Can I get off this?
SPK_1: And it's,
SPK_1: it's inevitably starts unfolding into this category.
SPK_1: Like,
SPK_1: your incentives,
SPK_1: like,
SPK_1: rational speaking,
SPK_1: your very incentive structure changes.
SPK_1: If we move from trust to deal,
SPK_1: the incentive of a deal,
SPK_1: you,
SPK_1: you can choose not to do it.
SPK_1: And that's the story you've been talking about,
SPK_1: of the old businessman.
SPK_1: But the truth is,
SPK_1: he never had a reason not to do it.
SPK_0: Okay.
SPK_0: So to,
SPK_0: to recapitulate some of the concepts that we've developed so far,
SPK_0: deal lives in the category of a part replacing the whole.
SPK_0: The trust is larger than deal.
SPK_0: Trust contains a very large territory,
SPK_0: and it situates,
SPK_0: it allows deals to occur.
SPK_0: Deals can occur.
SPK_1: I wouldn't even call it a deal.
SPK_1: It's called transactions.
SPK_1: Interactions.
SPK_1: Very good.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: I wouldn't call my experience.
SPK_1: Yes.
SPK_1: I don't,
SPK_1: I wouldn't call my experience with your daughter selling,
SPK_1: with me,
SPK_1: a lemon at a deal.
SPK_1: Okay.
SPK_0: It's a,
SPK_1: it's a sale.
SPK_1: It's transaction.
SPK_0: It's a transaction.
SPK_0: But it,
SPK_0: it only works in the sense of fair.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: In the sense of good.
SPK_0: In the sense of wholesome.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: In a context where trust is already.
SPK_1: Because I know she's a good girl.
SPK_0: Saturated.
SPK_0: Yes,
SPK_0: absolutely.
SPK_0: She is,
SPK_0: by the way.
SPK_0: And this is,
SPK_0: interestingly enough,
SPK_0: when she came up with this idea,
SPK_0: the conversation we had was,
SPK_0: well,
SPK_0: first,
SPK_0: let us begin the process of figuring out what it means to make,
SPK_0: truly,
SPK_0: good,
SPK_0: lemonade.
SPK_0: I'm not going to go to the store and buy a box of powder with sugar and bullshit in it,
SPK_0: and put it in a cup,
SPK_1: mix it with water.
SPK_1: You,
SPK_1: but you can.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: On a hot day,
SPK_1: if your goal is to just exploit.
SPK_1: Right,
SPK_0: right.
SPK_0: This is a,
SPK_0: this is the moral lesson,
SPK_0: like art.
SPK_0: This will be art,
SPK_0: not technique.
SPK_0: That's.
SPK_0: So we spent quite a time researching really great recipes.
SPK_0: By the way,
SPK_0: mint,
SPK_0: lavender,
SPK_0: lemonade.
SPK_0: Very good.
SPK_0: Delicious.
SPK_0: You can also do a little bit of blackberry,
SPK_0: which is fantastic.
SPK_1: Preaching to the choir.
SPK_0: So,
SPK_0: but this is the point,
SPK_0: right?
SPK_0: There's an architecture here.
SPK_0: There's a,
SPK_0: there's a,
SPK_0: there's a pattern language.
SPK_0: If you orient towards the art of lemonade in a context of being trustworthy,
SPK_0: then you're living in the kingdom.
SPK_0: Right?
SPK_0: When you move towards the technique.
SPK_1: And remember this weird phrase,
SPK_1: just remember this phrase,
SPK_1: which we kind of lost.
SPK_1: We use it when it blinds us with,
SPK_1: but in this conversation,
SPK_1: it feels necessary.
SPK_1: Pay me a fair price.
SPK_1: Yes,
SPK_0: that's right.
SPK_0: By the way,
SPK_0: without even thinking about it,
SPK_0: this is where we settled.
SPK_0: What is the price?
SPK_0: Pay me a fair price.
SPK_0: Make,
SPK_0: pay what you think is proper.
SPK_0: Isn't that interesting?
SPK_0: These fit together.
SPK_0: These,
SPK_0: these may actually be part of a natural construct,
SPK_0: which of course throws the market out of its mind.
SPK_0: But we can say this,
SPK_0: this has been talked about before.
SPK_0: There's a false dichotomy back to the binary logic of market and state.
SPK_0: If you think you live in a world where you have a choice between market and state,
SPK_0: one,
SPK_0: you're wrong.
SPK_0: And two,
SPK_0: you're trapped.
SPK_0: Okay.
SPK_0: We live in a Trinitarian world.
SPK_0: There's a third.
SPK_0: I've called it the commons to bring economists towards it.
SPK_0: But I've also said,
SPK_0: look,
SPK_0: when I say the commons,
SPK_0: what I mean is the sacred.
SPK_0: The sacred is clearly.
SPK_1: I would call it ethics in this context,
SPK_1: but on a.
SPK_1: Okay.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_0: Ethics or,
SPK_0: or the church,
SPK_0: by the way,
SPK_0: which will irritate a lot of people.
SPK_0: And that's fine.
SPK_0: And it's more fundamental.
SPK_0: It's like trust.
SPK_0: It's a bigger thing.
SPK_0: When your market is embedded in this space,
SPK_0: your market can actually be effective and good.
SPK_0: You can do things.
SPK_0: Well,
SPK_0: there's real logic to the people who talk about markets.
SPK_0: And that's,
SPK_0: by the way,
SPK_0: your state is very small,
SPK_0: but it can do things that things it needs to do.
SPK_0: Okay.
SPK_0: Same thing.
SPK_0: So we keep talking about this notion.
SPK_0: Now we have a new concept to make sure we flesh out this notion of the three.
SPK_0: When you get stuck in the two,
SPK_0: where's that three?
SPK_0: And that three is probably more fundamental.
SPK_0: And by the way,
SPK_0: three also will definitely point towards the sacred and we're going to end up on Christ.
SPK_0: But even if you,
SPK_0: even if that's not your world,
SPK_0: the sacred is going to have to be part of what you're doing.
SPK_1: But you will just run into the question.
SPK_1: What is ethics based upon?
SPK_1: But you will need something.
SPK_1: I'm denying all of it.
SPK_0: Right.
SPK_0: And by the way,
SPK_0: you're now expanding beyond the rational.
SPK_1: And that's the worst part.
SPK_1: You are going beyond the rational.
SPK_0: Which does not mean the irrational.
SPK_1: I would rather prefer it called super rational.
SPK_1: Sure.
SPK_1: Like some,
SPK_1: but,
SPK_0: but not post rational.
SPK_1: And not,
SPK_1: not,
SPK_1: not even post.
SPK_1: No,
SPK_1: it is.
SPK_1: it's rational.
SPK_0: It's just situated properly within a context where it is meaningful.
SPK_0: That's all.
SPK_1: Meaningful.
SPK_1: Meaningful is even better.
SPK_1: But just saying back to the contracts and deal,
SPK_1: you see how I started with
SPK_1: the relationship between
SPK_1: material and immaterial.
SPK_1: Like,
SPK_1: like how to,
SPK_1: so if the,
SPK_1: if the knowledge is what Gnostic way of interacting with material,
SPK_1: then the deal is the way to interacting with immaterial.
SPK_1: And guess what?
SPK_1: Trust,
SPK_1: faith,
SPK_1: they are immaterial.
SPK_1: They are very real,
SPK_1: but they are very immaterial.
SPK_0: Okay.
SPK_0: Keep pulling on that.
SPK_0: I feel like there's something,
SPK_0: I'm actually feeling like that feeling a little bit of fear,
SPK_0: which is good.
SPK_1: No,
SPK_1: but,
SPK_1: but that's the thing.
SPK_1: So,
SPK_1: our experience of life is both material and immaterial
SPK_1: in a most profound way.
SPK_1: Like,
SPK_1: love,
SPK_1: joy.
SPK_1: They're not just chemical reactions.
SPK_1: At least your experience of them is not just of chemical reactions.
SPK_1: There is some,
SPK_1: like,
SPK_1: if you've ever been joyful about anything,
SPK_1: you know,
SPK_1: it's not just about matter.
SPK_1: There is a difference between cocaine,
SPK_1: John was hitting the right dopamine effects and real joy.
SPK_1: We all know it from experience.
SPK_1: Like,
SPK_1: so in some profound,
SPK_1: profound way,
SPK_1: but even like on a principle level.
SPK_1: So there is some always invisible,
SPK_1: um,
SPK_1: principle called context in anything.
SPK_1: So there is always something context because you cannot express the whole context of anything.
SPK_1: Like,
SPK_1: and on a material level,
SPK_1: on a material level,
SPK_1: it corresponds.
SPK_1: Like,
SPK_1: if you ask me to look at this table and to give a perfect account of this table,
SPK_1: I cannot do it in a perfectly scientific ways.
SPK_1: There is an infinite number of atomic relationship within this space.
SPK_1: And like,
SPK_1: it's an sub,
SPK_1: sub,
SPK_1: and I'm not even going to subatomic.
SPK_1: And it said,
SPK_1: but there was,
SPK_1: there was a table.
SPK_1: So in the same akin to it in a material context acts as the table in any relation.
SPK_1: So in any relationship to happen,
SPK_1: there must be something which lets it happen.
SPK_1: And this is the context.
SPK_1: This is a material in case of a lemonade example.
SPK_1: I trust your girl.
SPK_1: Like,
SPK_1: I trust your girls that she's not screwing me or like in any good deal.
SPK_1: I trust you that we've been doing business together.
SPK_1: I trust you.
SPK_1: Then when I hit a hard time,
SPK_1: you won't step me in the back.
SPK_1: You don't have any reason to do it,
SPK_1: but I trust you not to do it.
SPK_1: But,
SPK_1: and in fact,
SPK_1: this expectation of foreknowledge or anything,
SPK_1: that's what makes my current transaction with you possible.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: It's in the future,
SPK_1: but it actually is the reason of my current transaction with you.
SPK_1: I wouldn't want to make a deal with a person who I know will backstab me.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: So my mind is shifting right now to this notion of sorcery,
SPK_0: right?
SPK_0: You specifically highlighted it.
SPK_0: And so let's focus on that for a moment.
SPK_1: Well,
SPK_1: in fact,
SPK_1: what sorcery like takes it says,
SPK_1: yeah,
SPK_1: but all of this context,
SPK_1: isn't it too scary for you?
SPK_1: You can't control it,
SPK_1: but you are dependent upon it.
SPK_1: What if you could make it predictable through your particular knowledge,
SPK_1: power,
SPK_1: will,
SPK_1: and this all starts playing into here again.
SPK_1: So I will give you a knowledge.
SPK_1: So draw this circle,
SPK_1: put this spell,
SPK_1: you can control it.
SPK_1: And this holy materials,
SPK_1: and that's the idea of a deal.
SPK_1: And then,
SPK_1: and we'll sign a deal.
SPK_1: But,
SPK_1: and in this act of control,
SPK_1: it will be quote unquote fair,
SPK_1: but very different fair.
SPK_1: It'd be favorable in the sense that it will become,
SPK_1: we will sell you the idea that it's you controlling us.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_0: The sucker side of the equation at a meta level.
SPK_0: Yeah,
SPK_1: it is.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: So I will reserve to myself the ability to be aware of the potency and necessity of
SPK_0: context.
SPK_0: And I will sell to you a different kind of good,
SPK_0: which is you can just have content without context.
SPK_1: Yes.
SPK_1: That's it.
SPK_1: I'm giving you a necklace for your island.
SPK_1: I'm not telling you how much your island is really worse.
SPK_1: What does it even mean?
SPK_1: How big,
SPK_1: what does your island mean in the scale of this whole world?
SPK_1: I'm not lying to you.
SPK_1: I'm just not telling you what it really means.
SPK_0: Right.
SPK_1: But in fact,
SPK_1: you can say,
SPK_1: there's always just evil moral people,
SPK_1: but sorry,
SPK_1: that's the whole stock market is based upon.
SPK_1: I know something you don't know.
SPK_1: I'm using this knowledge to gain my capital.
SPK_1: I'm sorry,
SPK_1: but that's all deals are structured.
SPK_1: I mean,
SPK_0: I think if you were to ask the question in that fashion,
SPK_0: everybody in both economics and finance would agree with you.
SPK_0: So there's no,
SPK_0: it's not even not a bash.
SPK_0: As you say,
SPK_0: it's a virtue of information.
SPK_0: Asymmetry is the essence of the market of the stock market,
SPK_0: let's say.
SPK_1: Yes.
SPK_1: So it is the foundation,
SPK_1: but I'm just showing that because it is a symmetry,
SPK_1: as imagery,
SPK_1: where we started,
SPK_1: there can be no trust.
SPK_1: And if there can be no trust and don't,
SPK_1: let's say,
SPK_1: basically,
SPK_1: then I have this incentive structure to cheat,
SPK_1: exploit and maximize my power at all costs.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: But let me,
SPK_0: I'm going to hammer down because what I also notice is what I want you to do.
SPK_0: Moron is I want you to believe macro microeconomics.
SPK_0: I want you to,
SPK_0: I want you to begin the process of separating yourself,
SPK_0: from an awareness of context.
SPK_0: I want you to really back to reason.
SPK_0: I want you to really believe that reason can do the job that I'm selling you.
SPK_0: Reason can do.
SPK_0: I want you to enter into transactions with me on the basis of a absolute falsehood.
SPK_0: The key thing,
SPK_0: of course,
SPK_0: is that I'm not going to tell you that the most important information asymmetry is that I'm going to say there are no information asymmetries,
SPK_0: or everybody's always playing information asymmetry and you're not the sucker.
SPK_1: If you don't know who's a fish behind the net,
SPK_1: behind the poker table,
SPK_1: you are the fish.
SPK_0: So this also ties to the notion that as we reach the end of these stages,
SPK_0: conspiracies begin to kick up into high gear.
SPK_1: Weird trickster part because yeah,
SPK_1: it's kind of this trickster element,
SPK_1: this conspiracy trickster role.
SPK_0: Because at the most basic level,
SPK_0: every conspiracy theorist is absolutely correct.
SPK_0: We live in a non-trustworthy society.
SPK_0: I'm being redundant because of the way I define society.
SPK_1: And we call it a virtue.
SPK_1: Just remember that the theory of modern state,
SPK_1: American state,
SPK_1: is based on an idea of social contract,
SPK_1: social deal.
SPK_1: We are not the icon of something.
SPK_1: We are not the mystery of something.
SPK_1: We are those who signed the deal.
SPK_1: Literally.
SPK_1: Constitution.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: We have a constitution,
SPK_0: not a covenant.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_1: We pretend that constitution can be a covenant.
SPK_1: Like technically,
SPK_1: it's trickier because we pretend that constitution is.
SPK_1: We pretend that nation is a covenant.
SPK_1: We pretend that class is a covenant.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_0: This is important because spiritually.
SPK_1: We have to pretend it.
SPK_1: Yes.
SPK_1: That's why you get this most bizarre on its surface statement
SPK_1: like our sacred democracy.
SPK_0: Right.
SPK_0: Even the most autistic rationalist is not ultimately severed
SPK_0: from the ability to perceive that there is a reality beyond that.
SPK_0: And so you have to provide them with something
SPK_0: that allows that lie to continue to hold.
SPK_1: Yep.
SPK_1: The trick part is like,
SPK_1: not even to them,
SPK_1: but to us.
SPK_1: The trick part,
SPK_1: what do we believe in?
SPK_1: Like that is because it is always a fractal.
SPK_1: Like one argument would be like,
SPK_1: they're morons.
SPK_1: We crooks.
SPK_1: Let's agree between us crooks
SPK_1: and just let's exploit this freaking morons.
SPK_1: Yes,
SPK_1: there is.
SPK_0: I'm telling you.
SPK_1: No,
SPK_1: I love it.
SPK_1: I just like the logic.
SPK_1: how most people see it.
SPK_0: As a crook.
SPK_0: Great idea.
SPK_0: Let's cut a deal.
SPK_1: Let's cut a deal.
SPK_1: Wait a minute.
SPK_1: That's one of the good news out of it.
SPK_1: That's why no project of world peace was built.
SPK_1: No project of world peace will ever come into play
SPK_1: because the pattern works on every level of hierarchy.
SPK_1: Now,
SPK_1: within the crooks,
SPK_1: you need to find morons.
SPK_0: Right.
SPK_1: Immediately.
SPK_0: This is the,
SPK_0: you've read that hideous strength.
SPK_1: Yes.
SPK_1: That's exactly.
SPK_1: That's it.
SPK_1: That's exactly it.
SPK_1: It's exactly it.
SPK_1: You necessary.
SPK_1: It happens because the cornerstone is the lack of trust.
SPK_1: So why do you believe if you don't have trust here,
SPK_1: you can have trust here.
SPK_0: Right.
SPK_1: You can argue the same reasons.
SPK_1: Well,
SPK_1: because otherwise it's rational or we will kill each other.
SPK_1: But if you find a way to survive while killing each other,
SPK_1: you can do the same thing.
SPK_1: Well,
SPK_1: then yeah,
SPK_1: I guess.
SPK_1: Of course.
SPK_0: Exactly.
SPK_0: So,
SPK_0: so it's very nice.
SPK_0: Hold on.
SPK_0: Let's,
SPK_0: let's get to,
SPK_0: to get to the essence of that,
SPK_0: because this is very,
SPK_0: this is very salient.
SPK_0: So we begin with the vision of the liberal nation.
SPK_0: And we begin with the vision of let's cut a deal.
SPK_0: Win,
SPK_0: win.
SPK_0: Okay.
SPK_0: Then we begin to realize I have to be careful because if,
SPK_0: if we get to asymmetry,
SPK_0: things might break down.
SPK_0: So we have to put some things in place,
SPK_0: trust,
SPK_0: but verify.
SPK_1: What is the law?
SPK_1: Okay.
SPK_0: But here's where it ends up.
SPK_0: The end point.
SPK_0: The end point is we must achieve something like mutually assured destruction at the individual level.
SPK_1: Libertarian,
SPK_1: sorry,
SPK_1: it's funny,
SPK_1: but there is actually a libertarian position.
SPK_1: Give everybody a nuke.
SPK_0: no,
SPK_0: I'm being very concrete.
SPK_0: Okay.
SPK_0: The crooks aware of the problem must achieve something like symmetric capacity to destroy
SPK_0: each other to produce a conspiracy that is effectively able to simulate trustworthiness.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: Any group that can achieve that has asymmetric advantage over any group that can't achieve
SPK_0: that in the froth of the deal,
SPK_0: the land of the deal.
SPK_0: So they will tend to move up in the hierarchy because they can produce a simulacrum of trust,
SPK_0: which is much more powerful,
SPK_0: but only on the basis.
SPK_1: Yeah,
SPK_1: powerful,
SPK_0: intense,
SPK_0: but only on the basis of the increasing intensity of the power they wield against each other
SPK_0: as a threat.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: You get what I'm saying?
SPK_0: I think I've just described how our reality works.
SPK_0: The world we live in right now.
SPK_0: That's the world we live in.
SPK_1: Yes.
SPK_1: That's the world we live in.
SPK_1: And we have no other choice to live in if we accept the basic assumption that the deal
SPK_1: is trust.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_1: That the law is important.
SPK_1: Like,
SPK_1: sorry,
SPK_1: you have to not get rid of the law,
SPK_1: but you need to put the law in its proper place as well.
SPK_1: That law is not at the highest.
SPK_1: No.
SPK_1: That there is a higher thing than the law.
SPK_0: Absolutely.
SPK_0: I mean,
SPK_0: as Paul said,
SPK_0: but we can be very clear.
SPK_0: Um,
SPK_0: if you have to have laws in your family,
SPK_0: then your family does not work.
SPK_0: You need to have justice in your family,
SPK_0: but justice is a lived present experience.
SPK_0: If you have to have laws,
SPK_0: then you're in real trouble.
SPK_1: Again,
SPK_1: we will talk about it like history and the wages of sin in our following conversation.
SPK_1: But,
SPK_1: what you're saying is an ideal,
SPK_1: but it's not a minimum threshold.
SPK_1: As a minimum threshold,
SPK_1: at least you need to be conscious and willing to be humble and surrender yourself.
SPK_1: That law is not on the top.
SPK_1: That the contract is not on the top.
SPK_1: That the deal is not on the top.
SPK_1: For sure.
SPK_1: It can all happen.
SPK_1: Like laws are not bad.
SPK_1: Oh,
SPK_1: sorry.
SPK_0: Well,
SPK_0: I'm saying it this way.
SPK_0: Let me bring it to the foreground.
SPK_0: I've made this point recently and not particularly clearly.
SPK_0: This goes back to this notion of the,
SPK_0: you start with trust that you did not earn and you're depleting it over time.
SPK_1: Yes.
SPK_0: The source and origin of trust is ultimately at the end of the day,
SPK_0: the mother and the child,
SPK_0: right?
SPK_0: Among humans.
SPK_0: Okay.
SPK_0: And by the way,
SPK_0: you see what happens when that is broken.
SPK_0: In the family,
SPK_0: the father,
SPK_0: the mother,
SPK_0: the children,
SPK_0: you know,
SPK_0: this is where we generate the ability as human beings to actually feel the presence of the reality of a field of actual trust.
SPK_0: Um,
SPK_0: society,
SPK_0: the regime of the deal principally predates on that.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: It's primary source of,
SPK_0: of,
SPK_0: of resource is that,
SPK_0: but,
SPK_0: but as it does that,
SPK_0: it depletes that it breaks it.
SPK_0: It's not that there was,
SPK_1: it doesn't give it,
SPK_1: you can say it doesn't honor it.
SPK_1: It doesn't give it justice.
SPK_0: That's right.
SPK_0: It doesn't give it justice.
SPK_0: Very good.
SPK_0: And so this thing that let's say political conservatives have talked about for a couple of generations,
SPK_0: of kind of the war on the family,
SPK_0: it's more like the inevitable consequence of a parasitic organism on the family.
SPK_0: Um,
SPK_0: and so again,
SPK_0: you end up at something that is not able to continue to be alive because it's ultimately not actually alive.
SPK_0: It is a parasite.
SPK_0: It is an undead creature that lives on the life of something else.
SPK_1: Absolutely.
SPK_1: That's the parasite is the story of like,
SPK_1: it is a short story of the last 300 years in the sense let's like,
SPK_1: because one of this position very famously hold by in America,
SPK_1: like in particularly was,
SPK_1: okay,
SPK_1: let's effectively set up a set of rules for godly people,
SPK_1: but saying nothing about the need to be godly in this set of rules.
SPK_1: Ultimately,
SPK_1: the problem is what,
SPK_1: what's in the set of rules,
SPK_1: not in the,
SPK_1: but you already depleted me of a context.
SPK_1: Sorry.
SPK_1: You already said that's only the constitution.
SPK_1: There is no,
SPK_1: you,
SPK_1: you say that there is a four corner.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: There is a context,
SPK_1: but where?
SPK_1: Well,
SPK_1: it's somewhere.
SPK_0: We find this truth to be self-evident.
SPK_1: Yeah,
SPK_1: that's where I'm hitting like,
SPK_1: sorry,
SPK_1: self-evident to whom?
SPK_1: It's important.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_0: And more.
SPK_1: And the key question was that you're self-evident to us.
SPK_1: You didn't written it down.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: You didn't even write it's self-evident for us.
SPK_1: Well,
SPK_1: then because then you would need to define us and then you would need to come into the whole niches,
SPK_1: identities,
SPK_1: hierarchies,
SPK_1: logo,
SPK_1: like where us are coming from,
SPK_1: where is the name is coming from.
SPK_1: It really limits your freedom immediately if you put it.
SPK_1: So we would just self,
SPK_1: just self-evident.
SPK_1: And then the goal,
SPK_1: like,
SPK_1: and pursuit of happiness.
SPK_1: Well,
SPK_1: sorry,
SPK_1: if all is life,
SPK_1: liberty and pursuit of happiness,
SPK_1: who says that your way of pursuing liberty is better than mine or happening?
SPK_1: It's just my way of pursuing happiness.
SPK_1: No,
SPK_1: you can say,
SPK_1: but I implied that there is a particular better way of pursuing happiness.
SPK_1: Well,
SPK_1: good for you that you implied it,
SPK_1: but there is nothing in your code.
SPK_1: And there is a reason you can't put it in your code because then you will,
SPK_1: you will,
SPK_1: you will have to submit to it.
SPK_1: And ultimately yourself don't want to submit to it.
SPK_0: Well,
SPK_0: actually,
SPK_0: I'm going to say it differently.
SPK_0: I think we're going to end up converging,
SPK_0: but it's,
SPK_0: if you say you,
SPK_1: one,
SPK_0: we are,
SPK_0: sorry,
SPK_0: who,
SPK_0: who in order to form a,
SPK_1: who I'm the one with the power that is Kate.
SPK_0: No,
SPK_0: no.
SPK_0: In order to form a,
SPK_0: who that is capable of resisting another,
SPK_0: who I'm going to compromise on things.
SPK_0: And then I'm not founded on something that has integrity.
SPK_0: I'm not sure if this is a principle or,
SPK_0: or,
SPK_0: or just a historical event,
SPK_0: but this happens all the time.
SPK_0: This is the notion of compromise.
SPK_0: If I want to,
SPK_0: if,
SPK_0: if there's two of us and there's one of him,
SPK_0: and we're trying to figure out who's going to be on the two,
SPK_0: and who's going to be on the one,
SPK_0: we're going to find a way to make a deal.
SPK_0: And whoever makes the deal quickest gets to be on the side of two.
SPK_0: So this is the idea.
SPK_0: There's,
SPK_0: there's a lack of integrity to that in both senses of the term,
SPK_0: but there's a orientation towards strategic exigency.
SPK_0: So we keep getting,
SPK_0: this shows up consistently as well,
SPK_0: right?
SPK_0: We have our prince,
SPK_0: our queen,
SPK_0: and the quarantine,
SPK_0: right?
SPK_0: We have the prince and the arms race.
SPK_0: We also now have this notion of the strategic exigency of the war of all against all.
SPK_0: And whoever is able to get to the local optimum of minimum viable,
SPK_0: who to achieve critical mass in self-defense is able to achieve local victory,
SPK_0: but they're on the process,
SPK_0: but they're now committed to something that has no integrity,
SPK_1: no integrity.
SPK_1: Like it starts from a bottom.
SPK_1: Like,
SPK_1: that's the thing.
SPK_1: And theologically it would work more like the way the choice would be something of this
SPK_1: following.
SPK_1: Basically,
SPK_1: you know,
SPK_1: the basic,
SPK_1: the basic political logical distinction is between us and enemy,
SPK_1: like we,
SPK_1: and them,
SPK_1: we,
SPK_1: and enemy.
SPK_1: And it is true.
SPK_1: Just in case it is a very true distinction.
SPK_1: That's how basically any distinction truly functions in its steps.
SPK_1: And we will go into it and into that later.
SPK_1: But what the trick happens in this story,
SPK_1: we either forget or completely rewrite.
SPK_1: So,
SPK_1: that unity precedes enemy.
SPK_1: Ontologically,
SPK_1: unity precedes enemy.
SPK_1: identity precedes sin.
SPK_1: Like,
SPK_1: et cetera,
SPK_1: et cetera.
SPK_1: So,
SPK_1: and that makes very particular conclusions that unity is not a contract.
SPK_1: That is the third,
SPK_1: which has got out of the picture.
SPK_1: Like,
SPK_1: that's very interesting way.
SPK_1: It's said in America,
SPK_1: like it is endowed by the creator,
SPK_1: but it's not clear why creator,
SPK_1: who created this classical Lockean paradigm.
SPK_1: Whereas in truth,
SPK_1: like any unity is a manifestation of heavenly unity.
SPK_1: And then we can start building trust.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: We could say something like true unity versus,
SPK_0: I've used the word society,
SPK_0: but we could say,
SPK_0: what's the other one?
SPK_0: What is that which is tempted together?
SPK_0: Aggregate.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: So,
SPK_0: you have a unity and you have an aggregate.
SPK_0: we have this other principle we keep running into,
SPK_0: which is something like.
SPK_1: It looks like unity,
SPK_1: but it doesn't have the spirit of unity.
SPK_0: Right.
SPK_0: Exactly.
SPK_0: And it might be good enough for right now.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: Might be even better.
SPK_0: Might be even better for right now.
SPK_0: So,
SPK_0: we have this question of speed.
SPK_1: Yes.
SPK_1: Let's not use better.
SPK_1: It must be more efficient.
SPK_1: Yes.
SPK_1: Or speedier.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: And these are these.
SPK_0: So,
SPK_0: it's interesting this.
SPK_0: It's funny to say that these are all part of the Gnostic civilization problem.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: All these different principles.
SPK_0: So,
SPK_0: we're sort of pulling them out and noticing.
SPK_1: Because you notice how they underpin each other.
SPK_1: It's not,
SPK_1: like they are in any.
SPK_1: That's the thing.
SPK_1: They make a weird form of a punity,
SPK_1: but they all unify.
SPK_1: Because you can start from any pros.
SPK_1: Nice.
SPK_1: Again,
SPK_1: let's do this.
SPK_1: This is a trick I did in the beginning.
SPK_1: If deal is trust,
SPK_1: or code is law,
SPK_1: or deal,
SPK_1: like all these things.
SPK_1: If this is the truth,
SPK_1: then knowledge is power.
SPK_1: Knowledge how to make a good deal.
SPK_1: Knowledge how to trick somebody.
SPK_1: Knowledge how to be a crook and not a moron in a deal.
SPK_1: Goes back and forth.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: But biting in its tail.
SPK_1: And we will come to biting and like.
SPK_1: Can we do this?
SPK_0: Let's go from,
SPK_0: let's go from deal.
SPK_1: Okay.
SPK_0: To world is broken.
SPK_1: Let's go from,
SPK_1: deal from world is broken.
SPK_1: So,
SPK_1: here already we are starting seeing a circle appearing.
SPK_1: Not a spiral,
SPK_1: not a hierarchy,
SPK_1: but a circle.
SPK_0: A serpent eating its own tail,
SPK_0: perhaps.
SPK_0: Exactly.
SPK_1: Because,
SPK_1: so in this context,
SPK_1: how it becomes already at this stage self-contradictory.
SPK_1: And that's why it's,
SPK_1: when you keep them all together,
SPK_1: the contradiction shines.
SPK_1: So,
SPK_1: you start with,
SPK_1: the deal is trust.
SPK_1: So,
SPK_1: my knowledge about how to be a crook in the deal,
SPK_1: is my power.
SPK_1: To gain,
SPK_1: how I gain this knowledge?
SPK_1: Through,
SPK_1: through reason.
SPK_1: There is a whole sciences of good deals and managements.
SPK_1: And stuff,
SPK_1: disciplines,
SPK_1: university departments.
SPK_0: Sure.
SPK_0: Yeah,
SPK_0: yeah.
SPK_1: In this particular example.
SPK_1: So,
SPK_1: back to the reason.
SPK_1: But,
SPK_1: if I'm with the power to be always a crook,
SPK_1: which I achieved through my beautiful merit alone,
SPK_1: one way or another.
SPK_1: It can be even reasonable merit.
SPK_1: It can be a cult merit.
SPK_1: Doesn't matter,
SPK_1: but it's my.
SPK_1: Then,
SPK_1: that's,
SPK_1: the way I'm chosen.
SPK_1: That's the way I'm saved.
SPK_1: And if I'm saved,
SPK_1: well,
SPK_1: that means,
SPK_1: I'm in a position,
SPK_1: to do whatever I,
SPK_1: want.
SPK_1: Well,
SPK_1: and part of this,
SPK_1: to do what I want,
SPK_1: is to fix things around me.
SPK_1: Yeah,
SPK_1: I want to,
SPK_1: as you said,
SPK_1: the imperative.
SPK_1: If I'm so powerful and knowledgeable,
SPK_1: and always on top,
SPK_1: well,
SPK_1: they don't know how to do it.
SPK_1: I know how to do it.
SPK_1: Then,
SPK_1: they don't want to do it fittingly.
SPK_1: Well,
SPK_1: I will sign a deal with them,
SPK_1: how to do it.
SPK_1: And then,
SPK_1: we will fix this broken world,
SPK_1: which I'm still deep in my heart,
SPK_1: not happy with,
SPK_1: for some reason.
SPK_1: I don't know.
SPK_0: Nice.
SPK_0: So,
SPK_0: the movement,
SPK_0: the key movement here,
SPK_0: is this notion of the necessity,
SPK_0: of becoming something,
SPK_0: like the savior.
SPK_0: It's a beautiful little turn.
SPK_0: It's a beautiful turn.
SPK_1: But it cannot come,
SPK_1: because you're still a human.
SPK_0: I'm not a crook.
SPK_1: What do you mean,
SPK_0: I'm not a crook?
SPK_0: I'm a savior.
SPK_1: Perfect example.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_0: It's very,
SPK_0: very,
SPK_0: very powerful,
SPK_0: because,
SPK_0: hmm,
SPK_0: that's very powerful.
SPK_0: I'm not a crook.
SPK_0: I use the power that I have accrued,
SPK_0: for the benefit of those around me.
SPK_0: For the world.
SPK_0: For the whole world.
SPK_1: They don't even see the whole world.
SPK_1: They are too trapped in their everyday struggles.
SPK_1: But I can see the whole world.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_1: I have the knowledge.
SPK_0: Mm-hmm.
SPK_0: I feel convicted.
SPK_1: The deal is appealing.
SPK_1: What can one say?
SPK_1: It is appealing on a surface.
SPK_1: But there is one big lie,
SPK_1: and just like,
SPK_1: I will say it just for the spirit's sake.
SPK_1: The problem with any deal of this sort
SPK_1: is that you are the moron.
SPK_1: And the real crook
SPK_1: is the spirit behind the deal.
SPK_0: This is very important.
SPK_0: Okay.