SPK_1: what you start to realize is is this table is unique these 20 people are unique but also
SPK_1: not really yeah and that's what tradition is that's what it is you are unique but also
SPK_1: you should pay attention because these people have already done this super huge heresy for
SPK_0: a modern time you are not that special i didn't even think about it you're right
SPK_1: because you're not but you are that's the tricky part but why why do we emphasize that you are a
SPK_0: part um i want to go back to vulnerability like because what we did right now truth be told it's
SPK_0: pretty vulnerable if you think about it we toast it on camera like yeah no let's be honest uh it
SPK_0: already has this tricky why the table is universal why is wine or liquor is involved but traditionally
SPK_0: wine let's say wine is a symbolism of all good liquor around a good table because it does increase
SPK_0: vulnerability you become more vulnerable when you drink especially when you drink in public
SPK_0: uh why would why would one risk this interesting part good question good question many people would
SPK_0: say well don't risk it at all like just don't for sure and i can see in some context maybe
SPK_0: for some people it's good not to risk but if you're making the not risking
SPK_0: itself an idol like horror falls god then you end up in this pretty lonely
SPK_0: boring culture yeah loneliness and spirit it becomes puritanical becomes puritanical and
SPK_0: what is the tricky part we talked a lot you already brought vulnerability and let's build
SPK_0: upon it because vulnerability is one of the inescapable tragedies of human condition
SPK_0: we are vulnerable the problem is i don't know as a person and as a philosopher any good thing which
SPK_0: can flourish or simply exist without vulnerability yeah vulnerability is not just a byproduct
SPK_0: it's a necessary condition for any trust for any invisible link vulnerability is a necessary
SPK_0: condition for any unity with the spirit i'm sorry i will raise it up a little bit here that's nice
SPK_0: you brought your story about opening the restaurant and why why the table is universal but because any
SPK_0: anything you do anything any unity like any project any deed is actually build upon face
SPK_0: it and faces vulnerability it's about trusting that in the unpredictable
SPK_0: uh let's see space of the future like not truly predictable i will come we lie to ourselves a lot
SPK_0: here but in many ways uh in an unpredictable ocean of the future uh my relationship with
SPK_0: with something bigger than me and with other people
SPK_0: will produce something good, will let me be.
SPK_0: Table makes you face it.
SPK_1: Can I take this?
SPK_1: Please.
SPK_1: And tell a story?
SPK_0: Yeah, that's what I'm here for.
SPK_1: I'm gonna tell a story.
SPK_1: To understand the story fully, just,
SPK_1: we had a table, I was the Tamada,
SPK_1: and it was a group of women.
SPK_1: It was about 30 women, maybe 25 women.
SPK_1: They came in on fire and it was gonna be great.
SPK_1: And things were wonderful.
SPK_1: And they made the restaurant,
SPK_1: they beautified the restaurant
SPK_1: with their young, beautiful selves, all dressed up.
SPK_1: And they sat down and I was ready to do Supra
SPK_1: and I started trying to explain.
SPK_1: And three of the women came up to me on the side
SPK_1: and they said, oh, John, I was here.
SPK_1: Tamada, thank you for doing this.
SPK_1: We're so excited.
SPK_1: It's my friend's birthday, whatever her name.
SPK_1: I don't remember, Stacy, let's say.
SPK_1: And two of us were at this before
SPK_1: and we know how Supras go.
SPK_1: So this is gonna be the best thing
SPK_1: we're gonna do this night ever.
SPK_1: But we really need you to not do that one toast
SPK_1: where you toast to those dead people.
SPK_1: And I was like, well, okay, but it's a Supra.
SPK_1: And I can get into the history
SPK_1: because that toast is actually essential.
SPK_1: It's essential.
SPK_1: It's essential because that's how
SPK_1: the Supra started in Georgia.
SPK_1: So I said, well, you gotta trust me on this.
SPK_1: And they said, no, you don't understand.
SPK_1: Our friend whose birthday it is,
SPK_1: you see, it's very practical.
SPK_1: She is suffering this week
SPK_1: because her father died only a week ago.
SPK_1: And we just had to bury him and we didn't wanna cancel it.
SPK_1: And it's her birthday.
SPK_1: Please don't make her think of this.
SPK_1: And I said, no, no, you have to trust me.
SPK_1: This is why we need to do the toast.
SPK_1: And then another girl said, you don't understand.
SPK_1: We paid for this.
SPK_1: She went to like the most practical.
SPK_1: And she made me the most, she's trying to voice like,
SPK_1: a deep, like Western vulnerability on me,
SPK_1: like dough, money, I'm gonna risk money.
SPK_1: And I just looked at her
SPK_1: and I had this really important choice to make.
SPK_1: And it was early on in our existence as a restaurant.
SPK_1: And I don't, I just remember thinking,
SPK_1: and I told her, look, girl, I can't do that.
SPK_1: I didn't even have words anymore
SPK_1: to try to explain what was gonna happen.
SPK_1: You just gotta trust me.
SPK_1: She had to be vulnerable.
SPK_1: She wasn't, she was pissed off.
SPK_1: And she walked away with her friends and sat down
SPK_1: and we started to do the super
SPK_1: and then you know what happened.
SPK_1: I know.
SPK_1: Because you're a human being.
SPK_1: And also maybe I even told you this story.
SPK_0: I've been to many super species.
SPK_1: You can get what happened.
SPK_1: And everybody on the camera watching right now,
SPK_1: when I give you the answer,
SPK_1: if you don't know what happened, you do know what happened.
SPK_1: You're not thinking clearly,
SPK_1: or you're not allowing your being to surpass your thinking.
SPK_1: What happened was, is we toasted to her dead father.
SPK_1: Which was the best thing that I ever had.
SPK_1: What could be better than that?
SPK_1: Ignoring her dead father?
SPK_1: Like, just think about it on a scale of one to 10.
SPK_1: Which one's cool?
SPK_1: Of course you have to toast to the father that just died.
SPK_1: And you know what?
SPK_1: That's universal.
SPK_1: It is universal.
SPK_1: And when we did it.
SPK_0: The super began.
SPK_1: Oh, you got it.
SPK_1: It began.
SPK_1: Each, her friends started to tell stories about her father.
SPK_1: I'm about to get emotional now.
SPK_1: And then you know what happened?
SPK_1: They came up after me and said this was the best night ever.
SPK_1: And they hugged me and then we all took pictures.
SPK_1: And you know what I wanted to do?
SPK_1: I wanted to go, why are you trying to put that on me like that?
SPK_1: With dollars, why are you trying to do that thing?
SPK_1: Why are you trying to do that?
SPK_0: Because that's what we're trying to do.
SPK_1: Why, why?
SPK_1: Well, I mean, I got answers, but what's your answer?
SPK_1: Why'd she do that?
SPK_0: Because we're trying to do that.
SPK_0: The only way to deal with the unpredictability of the future.
SPK_0: Right.
SPK_0: Is to make a deal. Chaos.
SPK_0: No, is to make a deal.
SPK_0: And that's why we build institutions.
SPK_0: And to an extent, we all do it.
SPK_0: Because that's the tricky part.
SPK_0: Like we have institutions, we have a law, like Christians here, law, like all the talks
SPK_0: about law.
SPK_0: But the very idea why we have law is precisely because this, to face this black ocean of
SPK_0: something which you can predict because you know what will happen, but you are not certain
SPK_1: of what will happen.
SPK_1: That's good.
SPK_0: But it is important.
SPK_0: I will stand here because what we want to do, it's not just knowing, it's certainty.
SPK_0: And knowing with certainty is replacement of faith because faith is built on trust and
SPK_0: trust built on vulnerability and vulnerability necessarily presupposes, as a boring word,
SPK_0: logical opportunities, the possibility of things go wrong.
SPK_0: You can understand it as the story of the fall.
SPK_0: Why God gave us a capacity to sin?
SPK_0: Because to keep the freedom.
SPK_0: Like it's a capacity to sin.
SPK_0: But to be able to do good, you must have a capacity to sin.
SPK_0: It doesn't mean you will use it, but you must have a capacity.
SPK_0: I see.
SPK_1: And so there has to be a capacity, a potential for the thing you're certain about to not
SPK_1: actually come true.
SPK_1: You need that uncertainty in order to live a proper life.
SPK_0: Yeah, but it's actually scary.
SPK_0: Like imagine like you're actually giving, like was there, let's say a possibility that
SPK_0: giving this toast for the dead in front of this girl will lead to her, I don't know, emotional
SPK_0: collapse.
SPK_0: Breakdown, awkward silence, Supra falling apart.
SPK_0: Again, you from your experience, and because you trust the spirit of Supra, which is in
SPK_0: my opinion, connected to Holy Spirit, you know it's not, but technically it exists,
SPK_0: but they don't know.
SPK_0: And here is this trust builds over time.
SPK_0: That's why any good relationship, like we know, we just know around this, we sit at
SPK_0: this table right now because we know each other for two years.
SPK_0: It took many tables for us virtually to be at this table, truly to be at this table.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: It's like instant podcasting, but even feeling it right now, very different.
SPK_0: It is.
SPK_1: And we're going to do Supra tonight.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: And we're going to do Supra tonight.
SPK_0: But it takes time.
SPK_0: Time creates trust.
SPK_0: And faith is the only antidote against.
SPK_1: Can I speak about that for a second?
SPK_1: So I've done.
SPK_0: But anyway, that's my hypothesis.
SPK_1: By the way, that's beautiful.
SPK_1: And it's also true.
SPK_1: And that uncertainty to me, I don't know, I was given a gift by my parents or through
SPK_1: experience.
SPK_1: I like it.
SPK_1: I think it's an entertainer's gift that I don't know what's going to happen.
SPK_1: It's a stage and it could go crazy and it could go wrong.
SPK_1: There's something exciting about that for me.
SPK_1: I get it.
SPK_1: And I think that's one reason that Tamadas are Tamadas is because they're like, well,
SPK_1: let's see what happens.
SPK_1: I think.
SPK_0: I think.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: But also like to an extent, obviously, there are errors in your life where you don't know.
SPK_0: You don't want this at all.
SPK_0: Of course.
SPK_0: I can bet.
SPK_0: So like and for some people, this area is the table.
SPK_0: But that's why a table is universal.
SPK_0: It actually builds up your stamina.
SPK_0: It builds you up.
SPK_0: You can face maybe the truth, which as a person about you thinks is a compliment and you always
SPK_0: hate it in yourself.
SPK_0: You might be able you might need to face it.
SPK_0: But if you go through it, it will bring up trust.
SPK_0: It will bring up more of you.
SPK_0: And that's in truth is the only way forward.
SPK_0: Problem is we don't do it.
SPK_0: And as a practice, as a social institution, as the whole world around us is built on precisely
SPK_0: opposite principle.
SPK_0: It's built on protocol.
SPK_1: That's what I was going to say is so I've done a lot of these tables, tables with strangers
SPK_1: who sit together and tables with friends from for years that sit together.
SPK_1: And it's really interesting.
SPK_1: Everyone thinks, oh, when all the friends are together, they can they speak freely with
SPK_1: each other.
SPK_1: It's not really true.
SPK_1: Because what the Tamada is doing.
SPK_1: There's a canon of meaning.
SPK_1: It's not a canon of toasts.
SPK_1: In other words, you're not it's you're not repeating toasts that you did.
SPK_1: It's not like every super has the same toasts.
SPK_1: This is weird.
SPK_1: The Tamada actually shouldn't repeat himself on any given like tonight.
SPK_1: You you should hear themes.
SPK_1: Maybe tonight you'll hear toast the children or.
SPK_1: Yeah, of course.
SPK_0: No, you know, the teams.
SPK_1: But the idea is, is if you hear my same toast again, I've probably gotten lazy as a Tamada.
SPK_1: I've.
SPK_1: I'm trying to skirt the poem.
SPK_1: You know, the poetry.
SPK_0: Well, come on.
SPK_0: Well, let's be honest.
SPK_0: Everybody has their favorite toast.
SPK_0: But I do.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: But obviously, the idea is it's not a stage performance because I mean, the faces of
SPK_0: truth.
SPK_0: And that's a good part.
SPK_0: Like on a special level, it would be a mistake.
SPK_0: Oh, sorry.
SPK_0: It's a little bit off top.
SPK_0: But if you let me.
SPK_0: Sure.
SPK_1: I'll get back to this.
SPK_0: I just want to do a quick dig into potential conservative audience because I want to hear
SPK_1: this.
SPK_1: I like this.
SPK_0: Because it's.
SPK_0: Your example on toast is a perfect representation because, like, for example, the reason I don't
SPK_0: call myself conservative is because conservatism necessary is about keeping the form in case
SPK_0: of table.
SPK_0: It would be like you have a list of toast and you have a list of exact 14 COVID toasts
SPK_0: and every super you do this toast.
SPK_0: And what is truly the very first time you do it?
SPK_0: It might have been the most best, amazing supra.
SPK_0: Problem is, if you only do it.
SPK_0: And if you start worshiping.
SPK_0: This exact phrases, this exact words, it will end up being hollow.
SPK_0: You will lose the meaning.
SPK_0: And why?
SPK_0: Because table change.
SPK_0: That's one of the problem with the vulnerability.
SPK_0: Vulnerability is our reaction to the change.
SPK_0: And any change has a potentiality of danger.
SPK_0: Legitimately.
SPK_0: Sure.
SPK_0: Ultimately, change results in death.
SPK_0: Like I'm just saying, like, all change leads to death.
SPK_1: I feel when I wake up these days, I'm like, death is happening.
SPK_1: I feel great.
SPK_1: I feel I don't feel well.
SPK_1: I'm older.
SPK_1: I'm getting older.
SPK_0: So, and in that sense, conservatism is understandable, but also a little bit childish desire.
SPK_0: If I just keep the form right, it will save me from facing the change.
SPK_0: Well, the good Tamada is actually to help people face the change and table is for Tamada,
SPK_0: his personal way of facing the change.
SPK_0: And that's why it's universal.
SPK_0: We all face these problems.
SPK_0: We all face the change.
SPK_0: Well, you have two potential members.
SPK_0: The conservative mistake is to sacralize the form, sacralize the order of toast, make
SPK_0: a toast holy, like effectively.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_0: Liberal answer would be let's basically just get rid of Tamada.
SPK_0: Let's not.
SPK_1: Let's do it.
SPK_1: Let me express it the way I want to express it.
SPK_0: Let me express it the way I want to express it.
SPK_0: Just the way.
SPK_0: This is my table.
SPK_0: This is mine.
SPK_0: I paid.
SPK_0: I paid for it.
SPK_0: That's right.
SPK_1: Now I'm going to.
SPK_1: I'll do my toasts.
SPK_1: Any Tamada knows.
SPK_1: No, no, no, no, no.
SPK_1: I'm doing their toasts.
SPK_1: I'm doing the toasts for this table.
SPK_1: And what comes to be true, and this is what's so cool about the tradition.
SPK_1: And that's why.
SPK_0: That's tradition.
SPK_1: It's just why we're trying to give it to Americans.
SPK_1: The coolest, the most beautiful thing about the tradition is what you start to realize
SPK_1: is this table is unique.
SPK_1: These 20 people are unique, but also not really.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_0: And that's what tradition is.
SPK_1: That's what it is.
SPK_0: You are unique.
SPK_0: But not really.
SPK_1: Also, you should pay attention because these people have already done this.
SPK_1: And you're not that different.
SPK_0: Do you understand that you just said basically a super huge heresy for a modern time?
SPK_0: You are not that special.
SPK_0: What?
SPK_1: I didn't even think about it.
SPK_1: You're right.
SPK_1: Because you're not.
SPK_0: But you are.
SPK_0: But that's the tricky part.
SPK_1: But why do we emphasize that you are a part?
SPK_1: I guess it's just an imbalance through history, right?
SPK_1: It's a type of adoption of a certain type of being, a certain type of God.
SPK_1: And we followed this, the I am my own God.
SPK_1: By the way, it's okay.
SPK_1: Because you are unique.
SPK_0: That's what I'm saying.
SPK_1: This is the weird part, right?
SPK_0: I would say the weird part is you are way less unique than you think you are.
SPK_0: And that's the job of Tamada a little bit, that you are way more unique than you ever
SPK_0: thought you are.
SPK_1: You're infinitely unique.
SPK_0: You're infinitely unique than you thought you are.
SPK_0: The problem is we put emphasis traditionally on different parts because I'm still coming
SPK_0: back to vulnerabilities.
SPK_0: There's a desire not to be.
SPK_0: There's a desire not to feel vulnerable.
SPK_0: If you remember-
SPK_1: So let me tell you about these tables.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: Back to the table.
SPK_1: So often we get, and by the way, I want everybody who's listening to call me.
SPK_1: Because if people are trying to unite, let's call it diverse groups, there's nothing better
SPK_1: than Supra.
SPK_1: Oh yeah.
SPK_1: The problem is it makes people uncomfortable, which is great.
SPK_1: Business Supras are difficult.
SPK_1: You know what I mean?
SPK_1: Of course.
SPK_1: Oh, I really love this idea.
SPK_1: Someone comes in and they go, this is fantastic.
SPK_1: And I work at this insurance company and every year we do something, it's so dumb, a trust
SPK_1: fall.
SPK_1: I don't really think everyone should come here and do Supra.
SPK_1: And I always go like this.
SPK_1: They should.
SPK_1: Absolutely.
SPK_1: Not just because I want them to come because it's amazing, but man, watching the American
SPK_1: ethos about business that don't tell people your personal, like don't share the personal
SPK_1: details of your life.
SPK_1: Don't share your vulnerabilities with your coworkers.
SPK_1: And the reason all the leaders want their businesses like Michelin to come to Supra is
SPK_1: because at the office, no one's sharing their vulnerabilities, which leads to a type of slow
SPK_1: death.
SPK_1: I think.
SPK_0: It does.
SPK_0: I can give you later insight.
SPK_1: But those tables are hard, Pasha.
SPK_0: Of course they are hard.
SPK_0: They're difficult.
SPK_0: Because you're doing the heresy.
SPK_0: You're doing the heresy.
SPK_0: Another heresy.
SPK_1: I like that.
SPK_0: You're doing the heresy.
SPK_0: I mean, no, I'm sorry.
SPK_0: Because if you think about...
SPK_0: Sorry.
SPK_0: Now do you get capital?
SPK_0: No.
SPK_0: Capitalism as a religion is based upon certain dogmas.
SPK_0: And one of the ultimate dogmas of capitalism is exactly there is no human, there is a service.
SPK_0: What is a dough?
SPK_0: Like dough is a material version of the service.
SPK_0: I don't care who.
SPK_0: There is no who.
SPK_0: And you can say, well, no, but really, no, ultimately, sorry.
SPK_0: If you look historically, structurally, the whole system is moving towards a number.
SPK_0: Because it's the most efficient.
SPK_0: Wow.
SPK_1: That's right.
SPK_0: I mean, it's the most efficient.
SPK_1: That's dark, but people think this way.
SPK_0: Here is the tricky part.
SPK_0: In the short run, and here is our problem of incapable of thinking long term, let's
SPK_0: say all the modern capitalist practices, this franchising, contract employment, like
SPK_0: basically trying to, let's say, I only need 10 minutes of your time a day, so let me pay
SPK_0: only for 10 minutes of your day and not...
SPK_0: So reduce yourself not even to the function, but to the function in a very particular time
SPK_0: function.
SPK_0: So I'm only paying you for the time of your function or something of the sort.
SPK_0: So it's all going this way.
SPK_0: So what it means, it's completely a movement of who.
SPK_0: So ideally, let algorithm and AI do all of it.
SPK_0: Sorry.
SPK_0: That's the dream of all businessmen.
SPK_0: Can I just not pay for any labor?
SPK_0: Right.
SPK_1: That's what's happening.
SPK_0: I would say for any dumb businessmen, here we come to the slow desk part later.
SPK_0: But it is right now.
SPK_0: So when you are bringing it, and you suddenly, okay, functions.
SPK_0: You're actually not functioning.
SPK_0: Functions, you are people.
SPK_0: Let's talk about who we actually...
SPK_0: Let's not even talk.
SPK_0: Talking would be one thing, because talking has a little bit this performative element
SPK_0: and elevator pitch.
SPK_0: We have our cheats for it.
SPK_0: Let's show ourselves who we are.
SPK_0: So this whole unit of-
SPK_1: Show is a great word.
SPK_1: It's the right verb.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_0: You might not even say anything, but people will see.
SPK_0: You can't hide it around the table.
SPK_0: But guess what?
SPK_0: You can't hide it in your life.
SPK_0: You think you can hide it behind your paycheck or-
SPK_0: Exactly.
SPK_0: Excel sheet.
SPK_0: But you actually can't.
SPK_0: No.
SPK_0: That's the true part.
SPK_0: And the more you try, the more lonely you are, the sadder you are, ultimately, the
SPK_0: more suicidal.
SPK_0: So it's a slow desk trip.
SPK_1: It's what you're describing.
SPK_1: It's also what, if you go look at our restaurant comments, it's what people say.
SPK_1: They say something like, I really needed that.
SPK_1: It's therapeutic.
SPK_0: Can attest to this.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: And there's something like, what was that?
SPK_1: That happens a lot.
SPK_1: Right?
SPK_1: Like, what was that?
SPK_1: Like, what happened right there?
SPK_1: And you're like, no, we just did dinner.
SPK_1: And then I try to like not go, I try not to, I don't like to ruin Shvidoba, the piece
SPK_1: of the table with a very mechanical explanation of what's happening.
SPK_1: But there is a mechanical explanation that is, that's undergirded by a spiritual reality.
SPK_1: And maybe we can talk about that.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: Let's talk.
SPK_0: Okay.
SPK_1: So I'll give you one that's super fascinating, right?
SPK_1: Is the Tamada.
SPK_1: So for people that don't know, the Tamada sits at the end of the table, sometimes in
SPK_1: the middle, depending on how big the table is.
SPK_1: I sat in the middle recently for a big 40 seater and I'm mediating.
SPK_1: And so the Tamada is a mediator between heaven and earth and earth is symbolized in the food
SPK_1: and heaven is symbolized in the wine, but be careful, not in the wine itself.
SPK_1: It's in the words that are offered for the wine.
SPK_1: Again, this is all Orthodox liturgy on some level, it's the image of all this.
SPK_1: But here's what's really, really, really cool is in the Georgian tradition, if you go up
SPK_1: in the mountains, they don't do this so much anymore.
SPK_1: You and I have a drink, we'll do it the old fashioned way.
SPK_1: You and I have a drink and you'll see the spiritual unity with the material in a second.
SPK_1: You and I have a drink and there's food everywhere.
SPK_1: And the Tamada is now going through the process.
SPK_1: We have to offer the toast and the toast is offered, I'll do it, I'll do one, to innocence
SPK_1: and to the innocence that resides within us because we were all children once and it's
SPK_1: good to be innocent and may we remember from time to time.
SPK_1: I could go on and we make the toast and in the tradition, the old school, we would both
SPK_1: finish this.
SPK_1: We don't have to, it's a little strong.
SPK_1: It's also not great, but we would finish it.
SPK_1: If you put it down empty and if you held yours right there in the tradition, if you
SPK_1: held it.
SPK_0: You won't continue, right?
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: No, I'll continue.
SPK_1: I'll say to children and to the innocence and I would give something poetic and then
SPK_1: I would drink.
SPK_1: You would just hold it.
SPK_1: Let's practice it.
SPK_1: So I'm drinking, but you're just, you're just like this.
SPK_1: Then I put it down empty and I say, oh, please, Pasha, please, I know you want my toast because
SPK_1: you held it.
SPK_1: And then you would add words.
SPK_1: To my toast to innocence or children, maybe talk about your children and then you would
SPK_1: drink to the end.
SPK_1: Now if there's 30 or 40 of us sitting here or 20 or 10, you see that everybody's glass
SPK_1: is empty.
SPK_1: Well, yeah, maybe three other people held, maybe he held and she held.
SPK_1: Then we're finished.
SPK_1: And if people are still following what's happening is the whole table has emptied their glass
SPK_1: and now you never pour your own wine.
SPK_1: Someone will, the Marikipe will pour for you or your neighbor will pour and they fill
SPK_1: it again.
SPK_1: And guess what happens?
SPK_1: You should not drink wine again until, until I, the Tamada.
SPK_1: And when the Tamada speaks, and this is what's really cool about the unity of heaven and
SPK_1: earth.
SPK_1: When the Tamada speaks, he's giving you access to earth by blessing it with the logos, the
SPK_1: invisible meaning or the spirit of heaven.
SPK_1: And so I'm saying to you, now you can participate in earth because I've given the blessing of
SPK_1: heaven.
SPK_1: And of course, this is how it works with Lord have mercy, Lord have mercy, right?
SPK_1: The litany is followed by the amen and the amen is the evidence of the people, right?
SPK_1: The altar is the evidence of heaven and the people are evidence of earth and they're united
SPK_1: in Christ.
SPK_1: This is happening at the table.
SPK_0: Okay.
SPK_0: Two comments.
SPK_0: So like one comment, low and then go back a little bit higher.
SPK_0: First thing first, speaking in other words, what's happening around the Supra wall?
SPK_0: Like what does it, what does it do to people around it?
SPK_0: It reminds us about the truth, which we kind of, even in a religion's tradition, mostly
SPK_0: forgotten.
SPK_0: What I mean is the following.
SPK_0: We kind of tend to think about religious life and religion.
SPK_0: Spiritual.
SPK_0: Spiritual reality as something where very confined.
SPK_0: So there is a special place for it.
SPK_0: It's called the church.
SPK_0: You do that.
SPK_0: You go there for one hour, maybe two, maybe two and a half if it's like super, you know,
SPK_0: long, whatever.
SPK_1: You're rushing guys.
SPK_1: Maybe you go a little longer.
SPK_0: You maybe do it a little bit longer, but you know, sometimes it's whatever, but basically
SPK_0: it's a special place.
SPK_0: So we think of spiritual as something which is alienated.
SPK_0: There is a place for sport.
SPK_0: There is a place for work.
SPK_0: There is a place for eating.
SPK_0: There is a place for marriage.
SPK_0: There is a place for religion.
SPK_0: Like these places have clear borders and they are all function based and I know what to
SPK_0: do.
SPK_0: Well, what is happening around the Supra, you're actually bringing people to realizations
SPK_0: that it works in the opposite.
SPK_0: There is a spiritual reality and then there are different phases of the spiritual reality.
SPK_0: You can't confine it.
SPK_0: Like that's the thing.
SPK_0: So even when you go to sports, you worship your sports clothes.
SPK_0: When you go to work, you worship your work clothes.
SPK_0: When you go to church, you may be the one time of the day you worship something right.
SPK_0: Maybe if you're like around the table, it reminds that we are called to worship correctly,
SPK_0: rightly every moment of our life, even around something which is not in your face because
SPK_0: of our misconceptions, religious.
SPK_0: And that's what I think is very important happening around the Supra.
SPK_1: So on that note, another story.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: So I've toasted many times with, this is in Georgia.
SPK_1: I've toasted many times with men in Georgia.
SPK_1: So it works like this.
SPK_1: Me and you see each other, I don't know, Andrew here, our lovely editor sees us and
SPK_1: he sits down and then, oh, there's two guys, hey, look, it's Steve and Jim and they come
SPK_1: sit down and then we go, let's get a bottle, don't worry, we get a bottle and then we get
SPK_1: maybe cha-cha comes from wine because the idea is you drink around wine.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: And then we put it down, we pour and then here's the coolest part and this is right
SPK_1: to your point is you may have just been talking about a cocaine deal you're about to make
SPK_1: or all of us are talking about, man, that girl and it doesn't matter what we're talking,
SPK_1: we're guys and I don't know, I've seen 18 year old kids do this, whatever they're talking
SPK_1: about.
SPK_1: And one of the guys who sort of agreed to be Talmud, I will say, don't worry, one minute,
SPK_1: one second, I want to hear about this girl, but first, maybe a little toast to our parents,
SPK_1: let's not forget our parents.
SPK_1: And then you toast to your parents and then he goes back to whatever he was bad about
SPK_1: to say and he's like, one second, don't forget, we have to thank God to our elders, to all
SPK_1: of the ancients.
SPK_1: And then you'll be like, how are they going to keep going back to that cocaine deal?
SPK_1: And what happens is, is it mediates not only heaven and earth.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: It reminds us of the highest things.
SPK_0: Present.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: Like I think present.
SPK_1: Present.
SPK_1: Exactly.
SPK_1: And when you do that, I'm not trying to say that it saves you from yourself, but it reminds
SPK_1: you of the other self, the self you can become.
SPK_1: And I found it amazing, I was a young guy, I was single and I was toasting with young
SPK_1: guys and it wasn't always the best stuff, but boy, I was saved many times, but I was
SPK_1: also called to honor.
SPK_1: And when I left Georgia, that's what happened.
SPK_1: I came home and I was like, there's something honorable in that, I started doing it at home.
SPK_1: And basically it turned into this restaurant.
SPK_0: Well, yeah.
SPK_0: And the reason is like, again, it provides the context, like the other thing, like you
SPK_0: are you, but you are you not on your own.
SPK_0: I think that's what I would put it this way.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: And back to like heaven and earth, like a little bit what I wanted to say, like why
SPK_0: Supra works and what we can learn about, like from it.
SPK_0: In every moment of our life, on my level as a self, on a family level, on a corporate
SPK_0: level, et cetera, et cetera, coming back to trust, connect.
SPK_0: Any trust or any relationship between two can only be in the face at the face of a
SPK_0: third.
SPK_0: So it's against the face of somebody.
SPK_0: I see.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_0: So it's me, you, but it's not just me and you.
SPK_0: It's not horizontal.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: It's me and you.
SPK_1: That's what that toast is doing.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: I'm a little bit trying to show it.
SPK_1: I know.
SPK_1: I jump in like a crazy person.
SPK_0: No.
SPK_0: Sorry.
SPK_0: So it's just exactly what is happening.
SPK_0: So no table would work like on a practical level.
SPK_0: And I saw it when it's just me and you.
SPK_0: If it's just me and you, it's not a table.
SPK_0: You can't do it.
SPK_0: It's negotiation at best.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: That's right.
SPK_0: It's a fight, rivalry.
SPK_0: But truth be told, in my experience, the reason tables work, in my opinion, it's impossible
SPK_1: to have a table without a third.
SPK_0: There will be some spirit around the table.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: It might not be the best spirit, but there will be some spirit.
SPK_0: That's so true.
SPK_0: But there will be some spirit.
SPK_0: But all reality is based on it.
SPK_0: Literally, take anything.
SPK_0: Take corporations.
SPK_0: The only reason people come to work is because there is a spirit.
SPK_0: There is something higher than them that unites them.
SPK_0: It might not be good.
SPK_0: That's right.
SPK_0: It might be the dough, as we're talking about, or the fear.
SPK_0: Like fear is a spirit of fear.
SPK_0: Unfortunately, people use it as a substitute for a good spirit, but it's still a spirit.
SPK_0: That's right.
SPK_0: And supra reminds you about spiritual reality, and from it, you can start being more open,
SPK_0: seeing it around yourself.
SPK_0: Because I teach, so that's what I do mostly.
SPK_0: And it's good talking about the concept, so share me sharing a story.
SPK_0: So sometimes I do like group lectures, like let's say, so people come, we talk about
SPK_0: some interesting topic, like I do presents.
SPK_0: But then I thought like how to make it truly special.
SPK_0: Because people go a long ways, they spend a lot of money, like you want it to be meaningful.
SPK_0: And let's be honest, interesting part, we live at the age, some teaching inside, where
SPK_0: all the information is available.
SPK_0: That's the tricky part.
SPK_0: Like people don't really look for information.
SPK_0: And even when they are watching our videos, those who are, I know you are not looking
SPK_0: for information.
SPK_0: You don't really want to know the mechanics of the supra or anything.
SPK_0: You're looking for something else.
SPK_0: And that's coming back to your elevator pitch.
SPK_0: So what you're looking for is the space, which we call the table.
SPK_0: So the piece or the Shvedoba around the table.
SPK_0: And the certain freedom and vulnerability of people communing with certain spirit, experiencing,
SPK_0: seeing it.
SPK_0: That's what it is, yeah.
SPK_0: So long story short, we started doing supras at the end of the seminar.
SPK_0: You did?
SPK_0: Yeah, I did.
SPK_0: Like that's what I do now all the time.
SPK_0: And that's what seals it.
SPK_1: How are they going?
SPK_0: Going great.
SPK_0: Like they're going wonderful.
SPK_0: And it is very humbling because yes, I know, like I can tell interesting stories.
SPK_0: Like I teach interesting stuff.
SPK_0: But to them truly change someone's heart, one needs to, not needs to, it's much deeper
SPK_0: meaning when then a personal relationship against the face of the spiritual reality
SPK_0: comes into play.
SPK_1: So can I just say, this is what we're trying to do.
SPK_1: So like there's the do part.
SPK_1: Now let's just talk about do first.
SPK_1: Okay.
SPK_0: Let's talk about the right do.
SPK_0: Can I do?
SPK_1: I'm going to do right do.
SPK_1: Do do.
SPK_1: I got to do this.
SPK_1: I want to talk about this.
SPK_1: What's happened is the thing that we started doing, which is aid work, in the world called
SPK_1: America aid work or international aid is giving to poor people in poor countries what they
SPK_1: need.
SPK_1: That's not what we do.
SPK_1: Mm-hmm .
SPK_1: It started as supra elongated and turned into two years of offering yourself in the
SPK_1: poorest neighborhoods by living simply right alongside at a table.
SPK_1: It's simply mud huts, no car, living the life of those where we were invited to work.
SPK_1: And that meant eating with them.
SPK_1: And so out of this experience of doing projects around the world, the project is the person
SPK_1: who goes by the way.
SPK_1: Mm-hmm .
SPK_1: The poor person.
SPK_1: That's not the project.
SPK_1: We go because we're trying to heal.
SPK_1: We sit and commune.
SPK_1: And then out of the communion comes projects.
SPK_1: This is a very Orthodox Christian way to do missionary work.
SPK_1: So what I'm telling you is that's what First Things is.
SPK_1: That's what we do.
SPK_1: But what happened was it was successful.
SPK_1: I don't know if it's super successful.
SPK_1: I know it's beautiful.
SPK_1: Mm-hmm .
SPK_1: Beauty's a kind of ...
SPK_0: How do you measure success?
SPK_1: It's a pretty good metric.
SPK_1: I'll take that.
SPK_1: The stories are magnificent and the people are transformed.
SPK_1: But this restaurant came about when we tried to say, this is who we are, let's have offices.
SPK_1: That didn't work.
SPK_1: We opened a restaurant.
SPK_1: Now, guess what we're doing?
SPK_1: And I didn't know it until really in the last year.
SPK_1: We're sharing what happens over there in Mozambique and Sierra Leone and Guatemala, which is they
SPK_1: come and they take a piece of the material reality that we can offer.
SPK_1: We help them with resources.
SPK_1: Mm-hmm .
SPK_1: And we've learned about the spiritual reality that that kind of tight-knit community offers.
SPK_1: And what we realize is we don't need money here.
SPK_1: We need communion.
SPK_1: Mm-hmm .
SPK_1: And then people are like, well, I'm a Baptist.
SPK_1: I'm not going to commune with an Orthodox.
SPK_1: That's the first thing.
SPK_1: And they're like, whoa, whoa.
SPK_1: I don't ... You go to your church, I go to mine.
SPK_1: But the table has proven, and this is a gift from the Georgians.
SPK_1: Mm-hmm .
SPK_1: We'll always say this.
SPK_1: This has nothing to do with America whatsoever.
SPK_1: It's a gift from the Georgian.
SPK_1: Mm-hmm .
SPK_1: From the depths of the Georgian liturgy.
SPK_1: From behind the iconostasis where Vakhtang was buried, deep in mystical Georgia, somehow
SPK_1: we've been given a task of sharing the universal table with every human we can.
SPK_1: So we have PDFs, we do courses.
SPK_1: We're trying to create tamadas.
SPK_0: You're doing a successful job.
SPK_0: And we're trying.
SPK_1: This is it.
SPK_0: But the reason it's working, I think, as you said, it's ... Okay, you brought the word.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: Which was in my head, the gift part.
SPK_0: The interesting part, it's the gift from Georgia, like in your story.
SPK_0: But the reason it works, because it was given to them.
SPK_1: Well, this is good.
SPK_1: Thank you for that.
SPK_0: And ...
SPK_1: Don't tell you that.
SPK_1: Uh-huh .
SPK_1: No.
SPK_0: But that's the true nature of anything, everything.
SPK_0: Like you brought before, it's like the good tamada, the bad tamada.
SPK_0: Here, the gift part, surprisingly, is a great bridge to mention another universal element.
SPK_0: The universal element in any table, which we completely, in my opinion, misunderstand.
SPK_0: The nature of power, because obviously tamada is a certain figure of power, right?
SPK_0: You have ...
SPK_0: Big time.
SPK_0: For sure.
SPK_0: You stand.
SPK_0: You raise the glass.
SPK_0: You drink.
SPK_0: Everybody drinks when you say.
SPK_0: Ultimately.
SPK_0: And not when they want to drink in Georgian tradition.
SPK_0: So you would imagine it.
SPK_0: You would imagine it pretty high.
SPK_0: Like it makes you feel pretty mighty, one would think.
SPK_1: It can.
SPK_1: For sure.
SPK_0: A hundred percent.
SPK_0: It can.
SPK_0: Well, the trick is if you start feeling this way, the table will start falling apart.
SPK_1: I've seen it.
SPK_1: It's my own eyes.
SPK_0: But why?
SPK_0: Well, it's the same reason, let's say, if you have a beautiful tradition, like some
SPK_0: super tradition, cause a table tradition, it's a particular way of doing table.
SPK_0: It's only beautiful because it's a snippet of something.
SPK_0: It's something bigger than you have it.
SPK_0: And so the power of tamada is way bigger than any tamada.
SPK_0: The moment you start thinking that you can keep this power for yourself, that the moment
SPK_0: you can think that you can control this power to yourself, it starts falling apart.
SPK_0: So what I mean, everything is a gift.
SPK_0: And it is a philosophical category.
SPK_0: So any property of yours, characteristic, mind, eyes, ears, age, health, wisdom, knowledge,
SPK_0: tradition, was given to you.
SPK_0: I'm sorry for the culture of self-accomplishment, I know it sounds horrible, but even your capacity
SPK_0: to read a book is a gift.
SPK_0: All is a gift.
SPK_0: But if everything is a gift, then power is a gift as well.
SPK_0: So there is such a thing as a gift of power.
SPK_0: We don't think about it.
SPK_0: We think about power as a contract.
SPK_0: In one case, I saw power as like a product of my will.
SPK_0: I have this power because I willed it.
SPK_0: Sorry, I need a chance.
SPK_0: No.
SPK_0: But they do think it.
SPK_0: But I will say, it's a very common tradition and we can see very dark places it goes.
SPK_0: We recently had a pretty big story, exactly, like if you know why the really dark islands
SPK_0: exist, well, that's because of it.
SPK_0: Because we think about-
SPK_1: I've heard about that.
SPK_1: Yes, but that's right.
SPK_0: It's because we think that power is out of myself.
SPK_0: I myself create the power.
SPK_0: And then you can even start beneficial, but you will inevitably end up on that island.
SPK_1: You'll end up on the island and you'll do things you can't imagine because you've become
SPK_1: your own god.
SPK_0: You'll become your own god.
SPK_0: But alternatively, like let's say, well, we don't need any power.
SPK_0: Well, in a way, on some level, maybe no, but only if you submit to the absolute highest
SPK_0: power.
SPK_0: So no, you still need power because stable needs some structure.
SPK_0: Even if it's like invisible structure, it's still a structure.
SPK_0: You know, in Orthodox tradition, even heavens have their hierarchy.
SPK_1: Well, this is the idea that when we kiss the priest's hand, you're kissing the priest's
SPK_1: hand because the priest is handling communion.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_1: And it has nothing to do with the priest.
SPK_1: His power is not, his power is actually, it goes through him.
SPK_0: Exactly.
SPK_0: And it would be horrible for a priest to start thinking that you're kissing his hand.
SPK_0: Good priests are-
SPK_0: But it's a temptation.
SPK_0: It is a temptation.
SPK_0: Temptation.
SPK_0: It is a temptation, which is real, but the way to deal with it, like at least that's
SPK_0: what I read.
SPK_0: Like in Holy Fathers, effectively, it's exactly passing it forward.
SPK_0: And that's going back to the gift.
SPK_0: So the reason this tradition of yours works, so there is something universal.
SPK_0: And that's the truth.
SPK_0: There is truly something universal.
SPK_0: And Orthodox people have a name for it, Christ.
SPK_0: Christ is universal.
SPK_0: So it's not just something, it's someone.
SPK_0: And then everything good, effectively, is of him.
SPK_0: But it comes through different people, through different cultures, through different traditions,
SPK_0: through different faces.
SPK_0: The faces of it can be passed forward.
SPK_0: So these energies can be passed forward.
SPK_0: And if any, basically, long story short, if any powerful person, if any powerful leader,
SPK_0: in my opinion, not even powerful, any person of power, and here is a trick, we are all
SPK_0: people of power, either on a level of myself or a level of my family, a level of my business.
SPK_0: Maybe somebody is a level of a country.
SPK_0: I don't know who's going to listen to this.
SPK_0: You want to do it honorably, try to be a good tamada with people who owe nothing to
SPK_0: you.
SPK_1: There's a man who taught me how to do this.
SPK_1: One of them.
SPK_1: There were many.
SPK_1: It was Mamuka.
SPK_1: He had leprosy.
SPK_1: His nose was falling off.
SPK_1: And he would do this thing at the end.
SPK_1: I don't know that every tamada does this.
SPK_1: I do it now.
SPK_1: We do it in the restaurant.
SPK_1: So it's mostly men.
SPK_1: This is in 94, 95.
SPK_1: It's mostly dark.
SPK_1: There's no electricity.
SPK_1: And toiling away are usually women in the kitchen.
SPK_1: This is in the countryside.
SPK_1: It's not really Tbilisi anymore.
SPK_1: You can find women tamada.
SPK_1: But during all my time, there was never a woman tamada.
SPK_1: But what would happen, it was really beautiful, is this was a powerful tamada.
SPK_1: He spoke like he meant it.
SPK_1: And people liked him.
SPK_1: Like a true king.
SPK_1: Really.
SPK_1: And at that time, he was like...
SPK_1: It was almost like a gangster.
SPK_1: A gangster boss.
SPK_1: It was like, this is for...
SPK_1: And so...
SPK_1: But he would always, toward the end, he would say, please, to the women, he would bring
SPK_1: them out.
SPK_1: It was really nice.
SPK_1: And he would say, this table, this table, so much has been given to us.
SPK_1: I don't even know who made this.
SPK_1: Where did the wood...
SPK_1: Who grew the wood?
SPK_1: Who cut the wood?
SPK_1: But today we have her.
SPK_1: This is my aunt or my mother or my...
SPK_1: This is Kakaladze's friend.
SPK_1: And then he would go and...
SPK_1: He would kiss the hand of the chef, of the women.
SPK_1: Not all of them, maybe, but he would go and honor them by kissing their hand.
SPK_1: And this is resplendent.
SPK_1: And it's also in the image of the priest, who's bowing as an act of ownership of his
SPK_1: power.
SPK_1: He bows before the others and then kisses the true hand.
SPK_1: Or in other words, he demonstrates where the real power lies.
SPK_1: And it's so beautiful.
SPK_0: And that's what we forgot.
SPK_0: Because notice what happened right now.
SPK_0: We talked about concept of power without ever mentioning oppression or subjugation.
SPK_0: Right.
SPK_0: And notice that that's literally the only language we think.
SPK_0: The whole debate about power is structured this way.
SPK_1: Always.
SPK_0: Always.
SPK_0: The problem is the whole debate is false.
SPK_0: I often have it as a problem, like, many people, what do you think about this matter
SPK_0: and this matter?
SPK_0: And many tables fall, like, you know, like how political subjects are usually the reason
SPK_0: we like falling.
SPK_0: Like, it's like all falls apart usually.
SPK_0: But in my opinion, it's because the very language of it is unfortunately not right.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_1: We have it upside down.
SPK_0: We have it upside down.
SPK_0: Because we don't accept the third.
SPK_0: That's what I'm talking about.
SPK_0: We don't accept the third.
SPK_1: That's correct.
SPK_1: We've forgotten the third.
SPK_1: Yes.
SPK_1: It's really interesting.
SPK_1: Another tradition is a table.
SPK_1: Again, this isn't every single table and every single tamina.
SPK_1: Mm-hmm.
SPK_1: But it's very rare for the tamina to just pick you out and just toast to you.
SPK_1: Most, the tamina's will do this.
SPK_1: They'll toast, they'll say, please, I would like to toast to you.
SPK_1: Mm-hmm.
SPK_1: But mostly I want to toast to your mother.
SPK_1: I've known her.
SPK_1: And they're always triangulating.
SPK_0: It's always triangulating.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_1: They don't let it rest on one person.
SPK_1: And it's very uncomfortable when they do that.
SPK_1: Now, what they'll do is they'll triangulate.
SPK_1: Mm-hmm.
SPK_1: And they'll give a toast to families, and then someone else at the table will then toast
SPK_1: to you.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: And he or she will aim it at you.
SPK_1: But the tamina didn't do that.
SPK_1: Yes.
SPK_1: The tamina's not meant to locate all the power in one place, or all the honor in one
SPK_1: place.
SPK_1: They're always trying to, they call it like a Trinitarian triangle.
SPK_1: To me, it always makes sense.
SPK_1: So often we'll do, it's the third thing you're talking about.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: So often you and I would drink from the horns, but we're not drinking to you or I, we're
SPK_1: drinking to Vakhtang, the saint.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: There is a saint.
SPK_0: We're drinking.
SPK_1: The horns represent honor because they were probably acquired through some-
SPK_1: Battle.
SPK_1: You have to wrestle an animal or a battle or something.
SPK_1: And so you and I toast, you're the best, I'm the best, but this toast itself is for
SPK_1: Vakhtang.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: I like that.
SPK_0: I think it's the way of, it is the only way to not fall into the pit we began our conversation,
SPK_0: not into the pit of loneliness.
SPK_0: Because the moment you take the third out, like that's a tragedy, you will necessarily
SPK_0: end up in the mayhem we are in.
SPK_1: I feel like war is what you, at some point-
SPK_0: I mean, not just, yeah, ultimately war.
SPK_1: It is kind of you versus me in that moment.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: Even if I love you, that's the tragedy.
SPK_0: That's what I mean.
SPK_0: Even if I say I love you and we have a great relationship, like let's say we
SPK_0: are long term friends, et cetera.
SPK_0: But the moment it's just the two of us and no true other context, like no spirit between,
SPK_0: no like high cert thing.
SPK_0: Well, we are, that's the tragedy, we are not the same.
SPK_0: We are different.
SPK_0: Do you notice it?
SPK_1: Well, we don't have immediate, we don't have-
SPK_0: And we don't have, so imagine, take this.
SPK_0: You are different from me.
SPK_0: I'm different from you.
SPK_0: you, there is no mediator between us. Immediately. Indeed, the only way for me to become more
SPK_0: of me is to take some of you. And for you to become more of you is to take some of me.
SPK_0: So then we inevitably end into this Marxist, et cetera, oppression reality.
SPK_1: This is also the pattern of modern secular marriage.
SPK_1: Yes.
SPK_1: Inevitably, the man and the woman start to fight if the marriage isn't meant for the
SPK_1: third thing.
SPK_1: And then they make an idol of their children. The child is born as the mediator.
SPK_1: This is like destructive to the child. It's so destructive. I'm the mediator. I'm the third.
SPK_1: And you're, no, no, I'm meant to follow you. I'm not meant to lead you. And so without God
SPK_1: in the marriage, it's very risky. I'm not saying people don't love each other.
SPK_0: Come on. He doesn't meant to be a scapegoat.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: But it's an alternative.
SPK_0: So thanks for bringing it up. There's only other
SPK_0: alternative for us not to kill.
SPK_0: Ourselves because they're liking us. Let's kill somebody.
SPK_1: It's going to happen. It's what's going to happen.