SPK_0: I actually know a Georgian guy that died at a supra because the soldiers came to kill him
SPK_0: Yeah, and he threw the supra first and says first before we fight. Let's have supra
SPK_0: He had supra and they killed him
SPK_0: It was during the Abkhaz Civil War Civil War.
SPK_1: Isn't that nuts? That's nuts
SPK_0: And his family to this day is without him obviously, but they honor him
SPK_0: He did the thing.
SPK_0: There's a tradition in Georgia to say wait before we fight. Mmm. That's it. We have supra we feast
SPK_0: Afterwards if we still want to fight
SPK_0: Then we can fight
SPK_0: They were attempting to
SPK_0: To unify the greatest minds in order to answer questions around the table. That's what they were doing
SPK_1: Okay, I mentioned a good time and I can even turn this into a good table
SPK_1: I guess what what I meant was like imagine the time I die himself being as being as a in a position of a source and
SPK_1: Leader trying to do it rationally not just giving rational topics
SPK_1: But everything about him is about the calculation
SPK_1: rationality or risk management formulas, etc table would not work
SPK_1: Well, if you're using the time, it is a pattern of a sorority which again hierarchy sorority
SPK_1: That's a tragedy like for those people who say why would you need to talk about?
SPK_1: This in a way that this quote-unquote smart grace will and I said well
SPK_1: Like it or not in a way
SPK_1: we leave
SPK_1: Those people who are called to be and the fact that I call to be that is simply the fact that they are here is a sad
SPK_1: philosophical truth
SPK_1: you know who deserves power? Those who
SPK_1: have it. That's a tragedy.
SPK_1: If you think that somebody undeservingly
SPK_1: is having the power, you're lying to yourself.
SPK_1: There is something in that unity
SPK_1: that that's the only power it can produce.
SPK_0: This is deep and dark.
SPK_1: It's dark.
SPK_0: And it's happening right now.
SPK_1: You can't run away from this general
SPK_1: structure, general pattern. All you
SPK_1: can do is hope that there will be better Tamadas.
SPK_1: On every level of reality,
SPK_1: and that's why this universal particular
SPK_1: dance is so important, you can start being
SPK_1: better Tamada in your life.
SPK_1: What you are doing right now, it's a very
SPK_1: practical advice. Do a supra.
SPK_1: Be a better Tamada on your level
SPK_1: of reality. Maybe it will be
SPK_1: just the level of yourself. Maybe it will
SPK_1: be the level of your group of friends. Maybe it will
SPK_1: be the level of your family. But
SPK_1: basically throwing the table together,
SPK_1: creating the community, taking the
SPK_1: cross of authority, that's
SPK_1: the only way you do it. And then you can hope that in some
SPK_1: way this will
SPK_1: change the spirit
SPK_1: of a body. And then out
SPK_1: of this body, maybe some better
SPK_1: leader or bigger Tamada
SPK_1: will appear.
SPK_0: If you go to our website
SPK_0: and First Things Foundation, and then
SPK_0: you see that our tagline
SPK_0: is creation begins with sacrifice.
SPK_0: And it's
SPK_0: sort of like pedestrian
SPK_0: and cheesy. Just
SPK_0: the way to solve everyone's problems
SPK_0: is to throw a table. If people
SPK_0: were like, okay, have you ever noticed that
SPK_0: these guys all get together and then their
SPK_0: solution to all the problems
SPK_0: is to do the thing that they love.
SPK_0: It's kind of gross, except for once.
SPK_0: It works.
SPK_0: Because I want to say why it works.
SPK_0: It's because, guys,
SPK_0: throw a table, sit together,
SPK_0: drink wine, and toast.
SPK_0: Do you know what the sacrifice is?
SPK_0: I'm being really serious.
SPK_0: So let's do that tonight.
SPK_0: The sacrifice is of time.
SPK_0: It's time that you want to
SPK_0: spend on your own watching
SPK_0: Netflix.
SPK_1: Or just with this device.
SPK_0: Right.
SPK_0: Or with your phone.
SPK_0: Just with the person you like.
SPK_0: You see?
SPK_0: Because if it's too...
SPK_1: Sanitize.
SPK_0: I can sanitize and control.
SPK_0: With one, I can sanitize and control.
SPK_0: With two, I can sanitize and control.
SPK_0: With five, I'm starting
SPK_0: to get beyond this point.
SPK_0: Now, that guy always
SPK_0: talks about this. I don't want to deal
SPK_0: with that. But the sacrifice
SPK_0: is so profound in your
SPK_0: life. If you do three in a week,
SPK_0: the sacrifice is so profound. But I'm just
SPK_0: telling you, the
SPK_0: creation or what is born of
SPK_0: the sacrifice, which is how we
SPK_0: know life is designed that
SPK_0: way. We know this from our God.
SPK_0: Like, I love people who go,
SPK_0: you sure? Sacrifice?
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_1: It's just, it's the actual
SPK_0: image of Christ.
SPK_1: Do you want a hotter topic?
SPK_1: Like a hotter version of this?
SPK_1: Yeah, bring a hotter topic.
SPK_1: Eros. Eros, because of the sacrifice.
SPK_0: That's right. Eros is the thing.
SPK_1: Because the meaning of creation you're using
SPK_1: can... Basically, you're talking about
SPK_1: Eros.
SPK_0: And so you have to do it.
SPK_0: And when you do it,
SPK_0: your wife also, or whoever cooks,
SPK_0: there's about 50 sacrifices.
SPK_0: And what happens is, is when that's
SPK_0: that sacrifice to create, create
SPK_0: this dinner for others becomes the
SPK_0: pattern, you live, you live,
SPK_0: you live. But you'll know what else
SPK_0: you do. You get poorer.
SPK_0: What I mean by that, you're going to
SPK_0: make less money because you spent it
SPK_0: on the dinners and you spent all your
SPK_0: time sitting with other people.
SPK_0: So think about that.
SPK_0: What we're really asking when we say
SPK_0: do a supra.
SPK_0: If everybody does supra, I'm telling
SPK_0: you, we're asking you to participate
SPK_0: in 1310 Medieval Village because
SPK_0: you will have less and like it.
SPK_0: I like, what's his name?
SPK_1: World, oh my goodness, he will own us
SPK_1: and he will be happy.
SPK_0: You will own and have less wealth,
SPK_0: but I mean it, you will like it.
SPK_0: I'm telling you, that's the place you
SPK_0: have to go. But this is just Christianity.
SPK_0: It's just St. John Chrysostom talks
SPK_0: about, you got a lot of cargo in your ship,
SPK_0: but guess what? It's going to flip over
SPK_0: into the ocean and you're going to sink
SPK_0: down into the ocean with the cargo.
SPK_0: It's just the way it works.
SPK_0: Too much cargo is a sign of illness.
SPK_1: Okay.
SPK_1: And it's just, no, and you know what?
SPK_1: You can't even escape it.
SPK_1: Like as another, I can, I can make it
SPK_1: slightly darker, not slightly, very much
SPK_1: darker, which I love to do.
SPK_1: This part about sacrifice, like how
SPK_1: basically it's only out of sacrifice.
SPK_1: Let's say a power comes, like power
SPK_1: comes only out of sacrifice.
SPK_1: Guess what?
SPK_1: You're still doing it.
SPK_1: And people are still literally it's
SPK_1: happening everywhere.
SPK_1: Like you can't escape this pattern.
SPK_1: Think about it.
SPK_1: You go for a walk, you go for a gym to get
SPK_1: the power of your body.
SPK_1: You're repeating exactly the same.
SPK_0: Creation begins with sacrifice.
SPK_0: And so that which is begins with sacrifice.
SPK_0: We know this because that's how the world
SPK_0: was created.
SPK_0: God knew that this would happen in order
SPK_0: for us to exist.
SPK_1: And there would not, it can go in a very
SPK_1: dark way, but that's what we also need to
SPK_1: be aware of.
SPK_1: Especially.
SPK_1: In 2026, I mean, coming back to a certain
SPK_1: island, you think you can run away from this
SPK_1: pattern?
SPK_1: Well, you can't.
SPK_1: If you are not willing to sacrifice anything,
SPK_1: there will be people who are, and they will
SPK_1: know this law because there is a power
SPK_1: element in creation.
SPK_1: And I want just to highlight this.
SPK_1: So creation says power element and sacrifice.
SPK_1: The only choice is what do you sacrifice?
SPK_1: You can sacrifice.
SPK_1: All like Tamada sacrifices himself to the table.
SPK_0: This is the answer Epstein and these characters,
SPK_0: by the way, people might not like this, this
SPK_0: language, but I really want to take this back
SPK_0: through history, Epstein, Zionism, American manifest
SPK_0: destiny, English colonialism, all the various European
SPK_0: colonialism's, uh, the, the, the conquest of the South
SPK_0: America.
SPK_0: Through the Spaniards, they go back to the Romans.
SPK_0: You can pick, there's a whole series, Monsa Musa in West Africa.
SPK_0: And, and, uh, the, the, the capture of basically the gold trade in West
SPK_0: Africa, through Monsa Musa, various Mohammedan movements.
SPK_0: They're all of the same species.
SPK_1: Ultimately, there is only one choice of power.
SPK_1: Who do you sacrifice?
SPK_0: But those people are sacrificing others on behalf of their, but, but it's the same process.
SPK_1: And you will get power.
SPK_1: Like that's a tricky part.
SPK_1: You will get power.
SPK_0: Like that's, that's a, well, it's, it's evident you'll get power.
SPK_0: And so these characters, Epstein are studying the saints of the worldly control mechanism, which is
SPK_0: Satan, no offense.
SPK_0: They're studying the works of Satan in order to understand how to get that, which comes next.
SPK_0: It's like, this is, should it not be for a Christian?
SPK_0: This shouldn't be like complicated.
SPK_0: Okay.
SPK_0: So wherever you see that pattern, a Christian should recognize it.
SPK_0: And what happens?
SPK_0: Well, we know what happens.
SPK_0: Martyrdom happens.
SPK_0: This is, this is how the, if we've had a Christian state and that's probably arguable, it's because there were martyrs who were willing to say the creation of something like a beautiful thing in the world will be created by my blood, not by yours.
SPK_0: I will not take yours.
SPK_0: I will let you take mine.
SPK_0: And here's why I wanted to bring this up.
SPK_0: When the crazy loud liberal progressive is screaming about colonialism.
SPK_0: This is what I don't like about politics these days, and especially about Orthodox, many Orthodox converts.
SPK_0: We need to be in alliance with them.
SPK_0: They are recognizing the proper, their anger is properly disposed toward an evil.
SPK_1: The problem is that their solution is.
SPK_0: Now you got it.
SPK_0: The problem is, is their, their antos, the thing that they're being, the thing they want me to be is dead.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: But their anger is, it has, it's properly directed.
SPK_0: And what I'm trying to say, there's such an opportunity for unity right now in the world, because.
SPK_1: That's a silver lining against the background of all of this.
SPK_1: And that's the tricky part.
SPK_1: I think that's why throwing the table is so, so important.
SPK_0: You beat me to it.
SPK_1: What is the story of this sacrifice of the others?
SPK_1: Like ultimately, it has one ultimate weakness.
SPK_1: It doesn't really work in a long.
SPK_1: Long term when everyone, two conditions, when everyone is aware of it.
SPK_1: So when you can't lie to yourself that that's not what is happening.
SPK_1: People are for some reason, quote unquote, uncomfortable when it is happening in your face.
SPK_1: That's why we want to.
SPK_0: When what is happening?
SPK_1: When you have that the power is derived from a sacrifice of the other.
SPK_1: I got you.
SPK_0: Classic, classic worldly politics.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_1: We need, we need to frame it in a, we really need to frame it.
SPK_1: Right.
SPK_1: Like otherwise something in us rebels.
SPK_1: The tragedy, that's a tragic element.
SPK_1: The tragedy.
SPK_1: Of modern time.
SPK_1: Being uncomfortable itself is not enough.
SPK_1: And I think that's why there is a scary part of this whole story that it's suddenly starting
SPK_1: happening in your face.
SPK_1: And there is a challenge to everyone.
SPK_1: What are you going to do?
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_1: I'm like this.
SPK_1: So what are you going to do?
SPK_1: And currently on our level, on a level of worldly powers, basically we hear crickets.
SPK_1: Like they kind of, I don't know.
SPK_1: I don't like exactly this, but I'm kind of on the same ladder, but just like a little
SPK_1: bit down the road.
SPK_0: They're using the same construct.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_1: Just okay.
SPK_1: Maybe I'm not ready to do this, but effectively I am still in the same game.
SPK_1: So what are you going to do?
SPK_1: Well, your answer is pretty straightforward.
SPK_1: Throw a table.
SPK_0: Throw a table.
SPK_0: Acquire humility.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: Die to yourself.
SPK_0: I know people don't want to hear this, but this is how it works.
SPK_0: Die to yourself and be generous and open your house for other people.
SPK_0: Like this is the actual act of fighting the machine.
SPK_0: You know what's not?
SPK_0: Christian nationalism.
SPK_0: Wait.
SPK_0: So you're going to embrace the entirety of the worldview that you supposedly are against
SPK_0: in order to acquire the thing called Christian nationalism?
SPK_0: I mean, who does this?
SPK_0: Well, you know who does it?
SPK_0: A lot of people do it.
SPK_0: White nationalism.
SPK_0: What is this?
SPK_0: What are you guys doing?
SPK_0: What are you doing?
SPK_0: It's an embrace.
SPK_0: You have not yet emerged from the narrative that is killing you.
SPK_0: You have to emerge all the way out of that narrative.
SPK_1: You need a different language.
SPK_0: You need a different language.
SPK_0: Exactly.
SPK_0: You need the language of the Supra, the liturgy.
SPK_0: Liturgy.
SPK_0: The liturgy is the right answer.
SPK_0: And my whole point in this is it's so radical.
SPK_1: That's the thing.
SPK_1: The simple idea about-
SPK_0: It's so radical.
SPK_1: Even on a smaller level, and I'm not saying it's easy, just to be absolutely clear, just
SPK_1: start dining together at your home, even as a family.
SPK_1: Even if you start eating again together as a family, in a modern way, it is already a
SPK_1: sacrifice in actual fighting.
SPK_0: You know, you can eat this way together too.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: It's really easy.
SPK_0: It's not-
SPK_1: It is easy, but it's not-
SPK_0: No.
SPK_0: Hold on.
SPK_0: Let me say it differently.
SPK_0: The mechanics are easy.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: The mechanics are.
SPK_0: You don't have to have wine every time.
SPK_0: You just simply toast.
SPK_0: But guess what?
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_1: All the health starts getting worse.
SPK_0: All the vulnerability comes out, and then your kid's looking at you all weird.
SPK_0: Your 15-year-old's like, Papa, do we have to toast to the dead again?
SPK_0: Do it every time, please.
SPK_0: Yeah, we should.
SPK_0: We should probably not have a day where we don't remember our dead.
SPK_0: Why would we?
SPK_0: Maybe a couple days.
SPK_0: Okay, fine.
SPK_0: But why aren't we remembering?
SPK_0: By the way, when people hear this, it's not like hours of sitting at a table and remembering.
SPK_0: It's just like to our parents or to our grandparents, and I remember them well, to their name.
SPK_0: It's not like-
SPK_1: To your great-aunt today, like something.
SPK_0: It's not complicated stuff.
SPK_0: It's important.
SPK_0: But it's deep.
SPK_0: It's deep.
SPK_1: But it's super deep.
SPK_1: Super deep.
SPK_1: That's a battlefield.
SPK_1: That's a battlefield, because you can't expect essentially different outcomes of the same
SPK_1: hearts.
SPK_0: It's better put than a language.
SPK_0: Well, it's a language.
SPK_1: It's a heart.
SPK_1: Language is the consequences of this.
SPK_1: Yes.
SPK_1: Exactly.
SPK_1: But guess what I'm saying?
SPK_1: That's why it's so much usually easier to be in a critic position, and obviously I understand,
SPK_1: but you need to be aware of what exactly you are criticizing.
SPK_1: Are you criticizing the game or your place in the game?
SPK_0: This is great.
SPK_0: But this is coming to an end now in America.
SPK_0: I can't speak for Russia.
SPK_1: No, I mean, it's coming way quicker down there.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: The red and the blue, anytime you catch yourself in that now, as someone trying to move toward
SPK_0: crucifixion and resurrection, if you get into the red and the blue, it's almost like
SPK_0: porn.
SPK_0: It's just passions at that point.
SPK_0: The red is not fixing, the blue is not fixing.
SPK_0: It's a brand new narrative.
SPK_0: And I think that's why orthodoxy is so appealing.
SPK_0: It's because it feels like a new narrative, but it's old.
SPK_0: It's not new.
SPK_0: It's Christian.
SPK_0: I don't have to jettison all my Christianity?
SPK_0: No.
SPK_0: You don't have to become a Hindu.
SPK_0: It's a whole different bag.
SPK_0: And so again, I don't have all the answers, but I've gotten a world-class education by
SPK_0: doing this table and starting this nonprofit.
SPK_0: So I'm just trying to share the blessing.
SPK_0: It's weird, because I don't even...
SPK_0: You're crazy.
SPK_0: You came over here, then you're looking at me in the face, like a brother, which we are.
SPK_0: But I can feel like you've totally imbibed the mojo.
SPK_0: And then I'm looking at you, and I'm like, I start to realize we got blessed by this.
SPK_0: Something happened.
SPK_1: I would say a relationship.
SPK_0: I know, but it's like what it's doing to me.
SPK_0: It's like it's a walking experience.
SPK_0: It's an experience of Christianity that somehow I got responsible for, and not that I'm in
SPK_0: any way sharing Christianity, I'm trying, but I'm sharing a super which constantly educates
SPK_0: me on my own sins, my riffraffness, but also on the potential of like beauty and joy.
SPK_0: It's kind of nuts.
SPK_0: Okay.
SPK_0: And it's the liturgy, but it's not the liturgy, but it's the liturgy.
SPK_1: Can you explain that?
SPK_1: It's the liturgy.
SPK_1: I mean, as we discussed, it's liturgical, but it's not liturgy.
SPK_1: And ultimately, it's of the same pattern, just on a lower level of reality.
SPK_1: And because it's on a lower level of reality, it's legitimately more open.
SPK_1: Like for example, we are not healthy, and we can't avoid it.
SPK_1: But for example, you have a family with different denominations, or just Atheist and Christian,
SPK_1: or like, I don't know, Muslim and Christian would be harder than one family, but actually
SPK_1: you can have it in like in Russia, it happens.
SPK_1: You can go to the liturgy together.
SPK_1: You can't.
SPK_1: Like you can, but it will be weird.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: Like it won't work, you know, like it's...
SPK_0: It'll die at some point.
SPK_1: It will die at some point, but you can still throw a table together.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_1: And it will not be the same.
SPK_1: It won't do the true, true miracle through mystery, but it will do many mysteries and
SPK_1: miracles.
SPK_1: That's what I mean.
SPK_1: Like when it's liturgical, but it's of the same tree, but it's a lower branch, and that's
SPK_1: why it's so beautiful.
SPK_1: And that's why now it's important.
SPK_1: But I want to kind of bring it up.
SPK_1: It's one big topic we didn't talk yet, and it actually fits perfectly.
SPK_1: It's about leftovers, and it's about abundance, and it's about this whole idea of sacrifice,
SPK_1: resilience, and relationship.
SPK_1: What I mean is the tragedy of modern condition or any political condition, yeah, is that
SPK_1: it's necessarily against somebody.
SPK_1: There is no politics for common good.
SPK_1: I'm sorry, guys.
SPK_1: There is none.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: I think social treaties and social contract treaties don't work.
SPK_1: I'm sorry.
SPK_1: For Americans, Locke was wrong.
SPK_1: It doesn't work.
SPK_0: He just literally undermined the entirety of the American project.
SPK_0: Like, go ahead.
SPK_0: It's good.
SPK_0: It's fine.
SPK_1: It's not a new statement.
SPK_1: If you limit your world to politics, you will necessarily end up being against someone.
SPK_1: There is nothing else in politics.
SPK_1: That's the tragedy of human condition.
SPK_1: But you can also...
SPK_1: That's a mistake.
SPK_1: You can't put it aside.
SPK_1: What I mean by putting it aside, close your eyes on it.
SPK_1: Pretend that there is no against, because there is.
SPK_1: So what can we do?
SPK_1: Well, we can do a step above it.
SPK_1: You cannot basically be against it, but you can move above it.
SPK_1: And that's what the table does.
SPK_1: So the tragedy is like, whatever choices people are offered nowadays, generally speaking,
SPK_1: we are offered choices to be against always.
SPK_1: And there are things we need to be against, but not for the sake of being against.
SPK_1: That's what is lost in the process.
SPK_1: What is the good?
SPK_1: What is what we are for?
SPK_1: And ultimately, the table, it is exactly the answer.
SPK_1: So the table is for the relationship.
SPK_1: Don't build relationship against somebody, just build relationship.
SPK_1: That's kind of the starting point, I think, nowadays.
SPK_1: But how?
SPK_1: Throw a table.
SPK_1: Nowadays, I think it's one of the few, let's say, truly open paths to remember how to be
SPK_1: in a relationship.
SPK_0: There's a quick story on that.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: When we started the restaurant, I had been throwing soup on and off with friends for
SPK_0: a lot of years since I returned from Georgia.
SPK_0: These are often secular friends.
SPK_0: And we had great time, often down in Naples, Florida, to those people who are listening.
SPK_0: But I hadn't thought of it as anything other than something that brought people together
SPK_0: and all of this stuff I knew.
SPK_0: But anyway, and then the restaurant came.
SPK_0: And so then the arena is a public place certified by the city of Greenville.
SPK_0: And the arena has high stakes, because people are giving you money to do this.
SPK_0: Before, we just threw it all the time, because it was fun, it was our thing.
SPK_0: And what I got feedback constantly from people was, if you put a bunch of people who don't
SPK_0: know each other in the same room, they're going to fight.
SPK_0: It was like a constant feedback from the restaurant people.
SPK_0: And I was like, I don't...
SPK_0: When they would explain, I would be like, that seems true.
SPK_1: No, it seems reasonable.
SPK_1: It seems reasonable.
SPK_0: Like, someone's going to make a toast to Trump, and then someone's going to be pissed and
SPK_0: want to make a toast to Biden.
SPK_0: And then it's going to go like, ding, ding, ding, ding, ding, and it's going to be that
SPK_0: thing.
SPK_0: It's going to be Thanksgiving for most people.
SPK_1: Well, that's why you have a tamada.
SPK_0: Well, what they didn't understand is what you said, is we haven't had that problem.
SPK_0: It's because the game is being played above the level of politics.
SPK_0: Now we'll have someone dip into...
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: ...that layer of reality.
SPK_0: So I'll make a toast.
SPK_0: Sometimes I make a toast to the saints or to our stars, to our leaders, to people we
SPK_0: look up to.
SPK_0: And someone has taken that as, I just want to toast all the things Trump's trying to
SPK_0: do to fix this country.
SPK_0: That happens.
SPK_0: But there's something about the table.
SPK_0: There's some weird elixir.
SPK_1: Because at this moment, it's about this person.
SPK_1: And you can see his pain, his vulnerability, why he's saying these words.
SPK_0: By the way, that's what happens.
SPK_0: Because it's not...
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: It's not said with the same vitriol as online, for sure.
SPK_0: It's also said in person, and it's also said almost like he's trying to honor something.
SPK_0: And you don't want to just shit all over his honor.
SPK_0: There's something you don't...
SPK_0: Now, it flips both ways.
SPK_0: It flips both ways.
SPK_0: I've had LGBTQ people toast to marriage, and toast to their marriage, and their lesbian
SPK_0: girlfriends right there.
SPK_0: And there's evangelicals at the table.
SPK_0: That didn't happen last night, but they're sitting right there.
SPK_0: They don't really like that version.
SPK_0: They don't like that version of marriage.
SPK_0: They don't think it's real.
SPK_0: But somehow...
SPK_0: And for some rigorous, they see this as sellout.
SPK_0: But somehow, the automata puts it back together and re-elevates it, and then it just doesn't
SPK_0: go off the rails.
SPK_0: Now, sometimes...
SPK_0: By the way, this has to do with the automata.
SPK_1: During your whole story, it's a huge cross of automata.
SPK_0: It's the cross of the automata to not just weigh in on the LGBTQ person's marriage.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: You don't get to weigh in on it.
SPK_0: No, you can weigh in on it, but you gotta be artistic.
SPK_0: You gotta invite people back to the higher idea of love between humans, men, and women.
SPK_1: Higher idea of love.
SPK_1: And you can bring sacrifice, or something.
SPK_0: By the way, that's what you do.
SPK_0: If you're in it to try to convince those people at the table of your excellent stand on marriage
SPK_0: as a automata, I'm telling you, yeah, you're gonna go way off the rails.
SPK_0: You're gonna create division.
SPK_0: You're gonna not acquire stridoba.
SPK_0: You're gonna wonder why.
SPK_0: They're doing this.
SPK_0: And then you're only gonna invite the people you like to your table.
SPK_0: And that's what's gonna happen.
SPK_0: And then you're just creating a red table somewhere, or a blue table somewhere.
SPK_0: And then you...
SPK_0: You could still sit in that spot, but you haven't really healed.
SPK_1: It all comes back to the cigar conversation.
SPK_1: Again...
SPK_0: I know, I know, I know.
SPK_1: Because this is current tragedy.
SPK_1: That's the current state of even pain.
SPK_1: As an orthodox, I would say that's the current state of pain, of brokenness.
SPK_1: We see around.
SPK_1: Well, it is there.
SPK_1: Can I share another story from the Supra you said yesterday?
SPK_1: Please, please.
SPK_1: It's about the right way of doing it.
SPK_1: And sometimes it's easier to explain by example.
SPK_1: As you said, we are in the South, an American South.
SPK_1: And you're in this neighborhood and you share the story how, like, just recently, you had
SPK_1: a group of people from a Baptist church coming to your place, and a lady there, at one moment,
SPK_1: burst into tears.
SPK_1: And you felt like some deep-severed links were reconnected.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_0: But she was...
SPK_0: This was a...
SPK_0: African-Americans from this side of the tracks, in the Southern segregation history.
SPK_0: They were from the part of Greenville that was segregated.
SPK_0: And they came to eat at our restaurant.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_1: So what happened?
SPK_1: What happened, very unique, which you can't do in a New World culture, because it makes
SPK_1: no sense.
SPK_1: You didn't make an idol of their story.
SPK_1: You didn't make an idol of their...
SPK_1: Pain.
SPK_1: But you saw them, and they were seen.
SPK_1: And this rebuilds connection.
SPK_1: You understand why it's impossible in the New World?
SPK_1: Because we just don't understand the choice.
SPK_1: If I'm seeing it, then I immediately put it in the context of idolization.
SPK_1: That's right.
SPK_0: That's right.
SPK_1: Like, I need to make an idol out of your pain.
SPK_1: Even on a person...
SPK_0: This is the white liberal temptation.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: It's like, oh my gosh, you guys, we have to help you because of all the pain you went
SPK_0: through, and all the guilt that I'm feeling, I have to fix your pain.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: This is...
SPK_0: It's not what we tried to do at that Supra.
SPK_1: Well, another stupid little thing is to pretend the pain is not there.
SPK_1: And that's the biggest problem why all of these conversations, and why talking can...
SPK_1: Why we need more tamadas on all level of reality, because that's the job of tamada.
SPK_1: The job of a tamada is to see the pain, to honor the pain, to honor the person, but
SPK_1: don't make an idol neither of the person and not of the pain.
SPK_0: So good.
SPK_1: You see what I mean?
SPK_1: That's right.
SPK_1: Like, so you honoring, and that's the language of honor.
SPK_1: You're returning the honor, because the actual pain is the lost honor.
SPK_1: People lost their honor, and they are in pain.
SPK_1: And sometimes lost honor is like, I was betrayed by my friend.
SPK_1: Do you think it's not lost honor?
SPK_1: It is lost honor.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: I dated this girl, and then he took away from me.
SPK_1: It's a lost honor.
SPK_1: And it's because of this pain, which stays for me forever.
SPK_1: Okay.
SPK_1: I think it stays with me forever.
SPK_1: Forever, let's say you are like making the choices later, and you see it this way, or
SPK_1: again, on a societal level, a lot of pain of a lot of people over a lot of the time.
SPK_1: What do you do with it?
SPK_1: You can still honor the person.
SPK_1: You can still-
SPK_1: You have to.
SPK_1: You need to restore the honor, but to restore the honor is not to make an idol, because
SPK_1: we end up always in the false alternatives.
SPK_1: Like the worst thing you can do is not see the pain.
SPK_1: And again, just on a political level, you didn't see, let's say, the pain of a Rust
SPK_1: Bell for 20 years.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: It's called Trump.
SPK_1: Sorry, liberals.
SPK_1: That's the way.
SPK_1: Oh, I see.
SPK_1: You didn't see the pain of people from global.
SPK_1: You can disagree with their reaction, but you need to acknowledge the pain first.
SPK_1: You need to restore the honor if you don't want an outcome of destruction.
SPK_1: That's very straightforward.
SPK_1: That's very simple.
SPK_1: On a bigger scale, basically, like it or not, I will connect it with a different, another
SPK_1: hot topic, controversial.
SPK_1: Believe it or not, after the collapse of the Soviet Union, Russians didn't see it as
SPK_1: a lost and a cold war.
SPK_1: For them, it was a sign of peace.
SPK_1: We legitimately went through the solution of this process with an open heart, sacrificed
SPK_1: a lot.
SPK_1: It cost us a lot, right?
SPK_1: A better future for everyone to put as a legitimate attempt to put conflict aside.
SPK_1: What did you do?
SPK_1: You expanded your military structures towards us.
SPK_1: The pain is real.
SPK_1: The broken honor is real.
SPK_0: This story makes total sense to me, because people forget is it was 20 years of literally
SPK_0: tearing down your own system in order to be free of what the Russian became aware of as
SPK_0: evil.
SPK_0: And then the West doubles down and goes...
SPK_1: No matter what the system, we'll still be enemies.
SPK_1: That's the message.
SPK_1: You can disagree, but that's the message heard and why it happened.
SPK_1: I'm not saying you need to support everything you do, but you need to at least see the pain.
SPK_0: You have to honor.
SPK_1: You need to honor.
SPK_0: You have to honor what's good in someone, even though you don't like them.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_1: That's beautiful.
SPK_0: That's Christianity.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: Good.
SPK_1: Real.
SPK_1: True.
SPK_1: Pain.
SPK_1: And that's the thing.
SPK_1: Pain is true.
SPK_1: Even if you disagree with the source of the pain and you think it's a dumb way to do it,
SPK_1: you can still honor the pain, because it's real.
SPK_0: But Mamuka, the one who told me how to do supra, and then also Nino Garmashili, who's
SPK_0: a historian in Georgia who we talked to, they both said that the currency of the supra is
SPK_0: honor.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: It's what is valued above all else at the supra, is I'm going to honor you.
SPK_0: You're going to honor me.
SPK_0: So I know your family to have been ... Your grandfather killed my grandfather.
SPK_0: But you sit before me and I'm going to honor you, not for the killing, but for your very
SPK_0: being.
SPK_0: You have children.
SPK_0: And as a father, I honor you as a father.
SPK_0: Why can't I tell you that?
SPK_0: If you just think about your worst enemy, they still have participated in good.
SPK_0: Your very worst enemy.
SPK_1: And guess what?
SPK_1: The only way to really transcend the state of enemy, because that will make him vulnerable,
SPK_1: truly vulnerable.
SPK_1: That's right.
SPK_1: You know what makes an enemy truly vulnerable?
SPK_1: If you are in a place ... You need a place to do it.
SPK_1: You can't do it on a battlefield.
SPK_1: You can't do it in an election.
SPK_1: That's not places.
SPK_1: But you can do it at the table.
SPK_1: You can do it at the liturgy.
SPK_1: Sorry, that's the whole point.
SPK_1: That's the whole point.
SPK_1: We come together and then confess, and then we come ...
SPK_0: We can do it.
SPK_0: We have to do it.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: So that's the story.
SPK_1: And it is an antidote.
SPK_1: That's what I mean.
SPK_1: And it is universal.
SPK_1: But back to what it requires.
SPK_1: It does require sacrifice.
SPK_1: It starts with a sacrifice.
SPK_1: And the first sacrifice is ... Use the sacrifice as a tamada who is invited to such a table.
SPK_1: Do you think it's easy to run a table between Monteki and Capuleti from the literature?
SPK_1: Imagine these two families around one table, and you have to run it.
SPK_1: There are times when ...
SPK_0: I tell you, the hardest ones are big business.
SPK_1: Well, because it is constant snake business.
SPK_1: There's something there.
SPK_0: They don't trust each other.
SPK_1: Of course they don't.
SPK_1: I know.
SPK_1: Because they're all relationship and based on backstabbing.
SPK_1: It's wild.
SPK_1: It's the foundation.
SPK_0: And they want super.
SPK_0: So that's their humanity coming out.
SPK_1: Good.
SPK_1: There is still something human.
SPK_1: Well, as we know.
SPK_1: We do know.
SPK_1: There is human in everyone until the very end.
SPK_1: After the death, then complicated.
SPK_1: But why I brought it back to abundance?
SPK_1: Because that's another thing.
SPK_1: To honor somebody, you need to create a very particular thing.
SPK_1: A particular space.
SPK_1: You create a place of abundance.
SPK_1: For some reason, when you are in a place of abundance, you can honor people more.
SPK_1: I just noticed it happen.
SPK_0: Totally connected.
SPK_0: 100%.
SPK_0: Generosity is the beginning of the Supra.
SPK_0: In the Georgian tradition, they put all the food they're going to serve on the table
SPK_0: before you sit down.
SPK_0: Did you see that?
SPK_1: Yeah, I know.
SPK_1: It's so weird for me.
SPK_0: It's insane, right?
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: It's always a beautiful dish.
SPK_0: It's just stacked upon each other.
SPK_0: And you're like ...
SPK_0: There's no way everybody's going to eat all this.
SPK_0: And the women who are cooking, they're like, I know that already.
SPK_0: Why do you keep telling me?
SPK_0: When the Americans come to go, we're not going to be able to eat all this.
SPK_0: The Georgians are like, that's what you noticed?
SPK_0: Wait a minute.
SPK_0: They're like, hold on a second.
SPK_0: So I spent the entire two days doing this.
SPK_0: And you notice that there's too much?
SPK_0: They see that as something wrong with you.
SPK_0: A dishonor.
SPK_0: It's a dishonor.
SPK_0: Well, of course there's too much.
SPK_0: You're my guest.
SPK_0: Don't worry.
SPK_0: It's going to be eaten.
SPK_0: What do you think?
SPK_0: I'm going to take out all this and just dump it in the ground?
SPK_1: What are you doing?
SPK_0: You're focusing on the wrong thing.
SPK_1: Because there is an openness to the possibilities of more connections than you are.
SPK_0: Well, that's why they do it.
SPK_0: That's why they do it.
SPK_0: Because it's an image and it's a symbol of all the potentiality.
SPK_0: It's all here right now.
SPK_0: And so the other reason they do it at the beginning, you're like, well, now the cheesebread
SPK_0: is going to be cold.
SPK_0: They're like, yeah, we do a little cold cheese bread.
SPK_0: But now all the food is here for the rest of the evening for all the words, for all
SPK_0: the logos, for the meaning.
SPK_0: You don't have to worry about that.
SPK_1: Among those meanings, there might be some which miraculously will heal somebody.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_1: I think it is a way of invitation.
SPK_1: This abundance is a way of invitation.
SPK_1: And it's exactly invitation or invocation or a good, quote unquote, incantation of
SPK_1: good spirits which lead to the healing of people.
SPK_1: Pain.
SPK_1: Pain can be only solved through abundance.
SPK_1: You can't solve the pain from minimalization.
SPK_0: By the way, that's Petitsas.
SPK_0: He's like, why are we going to return to the deficit in order to understand the healing?
SPK_0: Just point the person toward the beauty, toward the abundance.
SPK_0: Let it overflow.
SPK_0: And when it overflows, that's the healing opportunity.
SPK_0: The Freudian way is to constantly revisit the deficit, the pain.
SPK_0: But no, go to the abundance.
SPK_0: Yeah, this is a natural way to become healed.
SPK_0: I don't know why people don't understand that.
SPK_0: Personally, it's kind of weird.
SPK_0: You could also say it's dark.
SPK_0: It's dark.
SPK_0: You could argue it's purposeful.
SPK_0: It's a way to keep people in their suffering.
SPK_1: Even without ill intention, but that's the only way.
SPK_1: We can keep people in their suffering and mitigate the risks and just keep some safety
SPK_1: checks so it doesn't explode completely.
SPK_1: That's the choices we are offered.
SPK_1: Well, it doesn't work because pain builds up.
SPK_1: That's another thing, like back to the point.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_1: Outside of abundance, pain builds up.
SPK_1: And then it erupts.
SPK_1: And it's ugly.
SPK_0: There's another problem, which is really interesting.
SPK_0: And this is the coolest part.
SPK_0: The coolest problem with that construction, which is basically a nihilist construction
SPK_0: of how life works.
SPK_0: By the way, the two biggest, I want to go back to what I was going to say.
SPK_0: I just want everybody to know.
SPK_0: I could be wrong.
SPK_0: And I don't know how long we're going to keep talking.
SPK_0: But the two biggest fights in American culture or Western culture right now, the two massive
SPK_0: battles that have to be waged still, the first one is evolution.
SPK_0: We cannot, at any level in society, continue to tell that story as our origin story.
SPK_1: It's a bad story.
SPK_0: The smartest person on any campus should be like, eh, it might not be true.
SPK_0: The least any college should be filled with is someone who's going, possibly not true.
SPK_0: Okay.
SPK_0: Jordan Peterson, stop using it as the template for all of your theories.
SPK_0: You have to stop.
SPK_0: If you don't stop, you'll continue to create atheistic, slimy mammal humans as the norm.
SPK_0: Let me try to explain what I mean.
SPK_1: Yeah, please.
SPK_0: The outcome of evolution is to teach me that survival of the fittest is my normal state
SPK_0: of being.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: Which is an exact opposite of Christianity.
SPK_0: Now, I just want to say this.
SPK_0: Evolution, as an educator, is buried and bound and weaved into every aspect of every
SPK_0: classroom from kindergarten until 12th grade.
SPK_0: There is no school that escapes ... I'm talking about Christian schools.
SPK_0: I'm talking about Christian schools.
SPK_0: They default to all kinds of weird conversations about bones.
SPK_1: Dinosaur.
SPK_0: I'm cool with bones.
SPK_0: The story you're telling about my bones cannot be the story of evolution.
SPK_0: You have to stop if you don't stop.
SPK_0: The second one is capitalism.
SPK_0: We have to stop telling the story of capitalism as salvific.
SPK_0: It's not.
SPK_0: It's just a choice.
SPK_0: It doesn't save anybody.
SPK_0: It doesn't make anybody better.
SPK_0: It's none of those things.
SPK_0: It doesn't do this on a spiritual level.
SPK_0: It is nothing but the flip side of communism.
SPK_0: It's just materialist economics at play.
SPK_0: We have to stop telling these two stories.
SPK_0: If we don't stop telling these two stories, we cannot exist as a society.
SPK_0: We have to.
SPK_1: Can I dig into capitalism, socialism a little bit?
SPK_1: Please.
SPK_0: By the way, I noticed I didn't argue for socialism.
SPK_0: Don't do that.
SPK_0: Oh, no, no.
SPK_0: I won't.
SPK_0: I didn't argue for socialism.
SPK_0: I'm just saying that capitalism is not salvific.
SPK_1: A red flag, Soviet meme moment.
SPK_1: Anyway.
SPK_1: So, just very easy explanation.
SPK_1: Why it's ... So, there is a presupposition which ...
SPK_1: Philosophically, which underpins the whole stupid economic debate.
SPK_1: That there is some objective economic laws.
SPK_1: Well, I'm sorry.
SPK_1: There are no objective economic laws.
SPK_1: Thank you.
SPK_1: Any economic laws is contingent and an outcome of an ethical choice.
SPK_1: What we consider to be the most important thing, generally speaking.
SPK_1: Just what we consider to be the most important thing.
SPK_1: And once you have these questions, then you build economic system to serve this purpose.
SPK_1: Right, right.
SPK_1: Basically, economic system always serves a purpose.
SPK_1: And this purpose is an act of choice.
SPK_1: In my opinion, there are only three big choices.
SPK_1: Well, one is a system which says that the center of everything is stuff, matter.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_1: And that's communism, actually.
SPK_1: And the second is that the center of everything is wealth as money.
SPK_1: That's capitalism.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_1: So, a little bit elaborate.
SPK_1: So, why communism is about stuff.
SPK_1: Just notice what communism is measured.
SPK_1: Tones of steel.
SPK_1: The number of planes.
SPK_1: I don't know, millions of shoes.
SPK_1: Thousands consumption of calories.
SPK_1: So, whenever basically you see a person describing the reality of material exchange in stuff,
SPK_1: it's effectively communist.
SPK_1: Yes, yes.
SPK_1: So, just that's an ethical system it serves.
SPK_1: And whenever you see like GDP as an abstract concept,
SPK_1: then it's a fact.
SPK_1: Oh, like the bank account or the shareholder value.
SPK_1: So, it's even more abstract.
SPK_1: Like you can say that capitalism just puts this matter but makes it abstract.
SPK_1: That's why it's kind of more.
SPK_0: Well, the words, the conversation is abstract.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: But a capitalist still thinks they're going to find their salvation.
SPK_1: Oh, yeah.
SPK_0: In the buying and selling of goods.
SPK_1: Yeah, the buying and selling of goods.
SPK_1: It's still there.
SPK_1: Problem is the third is the big third alternative.
SPK_1: The path which we kind of don't explore anymore.
SPK_1: Language, language is about human.
SPK_1: Like human being.
SPK_1: And I don't mean human as like, you know, in a humanistic way.
SPK_1: But the idea is like that the point of economic system like or just economy is to contribute
SPK_1: to certain changes in human heart, like it or not.
SPK_1: That would be an alternative.
SPK_1: Otherwise, the whole debate between whether like, I don't know, the tons of steel matter
SPK_1: or the number of zeros on bank account matter is a ridiculous argument.
SPK_1: Totally.
SPK_1: It's totally.
SPK_1: And it takes like, it's sad that people spend like really hours and decades on like as it's
SPK_1: the most important thing to debate.
SPK_1: Like, it's a false debate.
SPK_1: I'm sorry.
SPK_0: Yeah, I 100%.
SPK_0: They're the same system.
SPK_0: It's just built for different types of materialists.
SPK_0: Like, we're just different types of materialists.
SPK_1: Some people like stuff like I want bottles, like physically embodied bottles.
SPK_1: And some people have more joy of like the possibility of getting this bottle any moment,
SPK_1: which is would be like the power of money.
SPK_0: For me, I like America.
SPK_0: When I come home, when I participate in a capitalist society, whatever, I got no problems.
SPK_0: I'm all for it.
SPK_0: But the reason I can even be in it and still have hope is because of Christ and because
SPK_0: I have a brother that I'm willing to honor.
SPK_0: And you're telling me I should cut my brother so that I get a better price when I actually
SPK_0: go to sell in my house?
SPK_0: Are you crazy?
SPK_0: This is my brother.
SPK_0: This is my Christian brother.
SPK_1: Relationship.
SPK_0: I give him the number that he needs to move into my house.
SPK_0: Well, you're going to cut yourself off.
SPK_0: You're going to cut yourself off in the market.
SPK_0: What?
SPK_0: What are you talking about?
SPK_0: What kind of human being are you?
SPK_0: I know, but you paid this much and now you could get this much because it's your brother.
SPK_0: And it's objective.
SPK_0: Of course, because of my brother, I'm going to reduce the price.
SPK_0: What are you talking about?
SPK_0: You mean I'm not going to reduce the price?
SPK_0: It's my brother.
SPK_0: He's not really your brother.
SPK_0: You just go to church with him.
SPK_1: What?
SPK_0: What are you doing right now to me?
SPK_0: And you're calling yourself a Christian.
SPK_0: Back away from me.
SPK_0: You're a devil.
SPK_0: You're actually a devil.
SPK_0: What are you doing?
SPK_0: Of course, I'm going to give him the price he needs.
SPK_0: Of course, I'm going to give him that.
SPK_0: How are you even in this conversation with me right now as a Christian?
SPK_1: I mean-
SPK_0: How are you doing this?
SPK_0: And by the way, this happens.
SPK_0: No offense to evangelicals.
SPK_0: Watch to it.
SPK_0: Orthodox do it too.
SPK_0: Watch them sell each other a church, a building.
SPK_0: It's like an insanity.
SPK_0: It's like the first idea is first of all, how much money are we going to make toward
SPK_0: our $2 million endowment?
SPK_0: Shut up.
SPK_0: I can't even believe that that's a Christian conversation.
SPK_0: You know where I learned this?
SPK_0: Places like Georgia.
SPK_0: Georgia.
SPK_0: You know where I learned this?
SPK_0: Muslim Mali.
SPK_0: These guys aren't trying to like, what are you talking about?
SPK_0: It's a brotherly, it's a thing that tells me I'm united to you.
SPK_0: I'm not going to cut you.
SPK_0: And once you've gone into that realm with a human being, you're not allowed to put the
SPK_0: marketplace into that conversation.
SPK_0: Now someone's going, this sounds like nepotism to me.
SPK_0: Shut up.
SPK_1: Well, there is some good critique of what is called nepotism.
SPK_0: I don't mind critiquing nepotism.
SPK_1: I will explain what's the difference.
SPK_1: But in the language we talked about, it's like a dishonorable way of being related or
SPK_1: using the relationship or just manifesting the relationship.
SPK_1: But the solution is not cut the relationship out of the equation.
SPK_1: The solution is to do it in an honorable way.
SPK_0: Honorable way.
SPK_0: Exactly.
SPK_0: Of course, I have to consider my brother now whether he can work for me.
SPK_0: He didn't just get to work for me because he's my brother.
SPK_0: But of course, I have to consider my brother.
SPK_0: How am I not going to do this?
SPK_0: What kind of person am I?
SPK_0: And I just don't know what happened to us.
SPK_0: The marketplace became where we find our morality.
SPK_0: This is super dangerous.
SPK_0: Super dangerous.
SPK_1: Super dangerous.
SPK_1: And it is ultimately dehumanizing.
SPK_1: And again, when there is no heaven, there is no earth.
SPK_1: Thank you.
SPK_1: If you take the heaven out of equations against this horizontal we talked before, I need to
SPK_1: make an object out of you.
SPK_1: You need to make an object out of me.
SPK_1: And it's like two objects constantly fighting against each other.
SPK_1: It's a necessary outcome of a horizon.
SPK_1: And then we look for safety in objectivity.
SPK_1: But there is nothing objective in anything we do.
SPK_0: I love this.
SPK_0: This is a great conversation.
SPK_0: I don't know.
SPK_0: The only thing that's objective, right, is both.
SPK_0: That can see objectively and is an objective truth is God.
SPK_0: And so everything about you is subject to God.
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: That's it.
SPK_0: And so the only way I can know you is...
SPK_0: Yes.
SPK_0: Like C.S.
SPK_0: Lewis says, I can only see you because I see the sun.
SPK_0: Absolutely.
SPK_0: And so we can...
SPK_0: Why can't we start with these things?
SPK_0: And I just know the reason.
SPK_0: The reason is we don't spend time and we're not vulnerable.
SPK_0: We don't spend time being vulnerable.
SPK_0: And we're not...
SPK_1: Because we want safety.
SPK_1: We want...
SPK_1: We idolize our pain.
SPK_0: We retreat to our mammalian being.
SPK_0: And by the way, this isn't just America.
SPK_0: This isn't Western.
SPK_0: No.
SPK_0: I'm talking about this is the human condition.
SPK_1: Okay.
SPK_1: So just to be clear, like, yeah, so it's not Western.
SPK_1: Let's go as far as this possible.
SPK_1: Korea and Japan are in worst state right now.
SPK_1: I know.
SPK_1: We were in the worst state.
SPK_0: And by the way, I'm with you a hundred percent.
SPK_0: And by the way, the Georgians do this stuff all the time.
SPK_0: That's what war is.
SPK_0: I'm just saying at some point, the human condition can be addressed through Christ, the crucifixion,
SPK_0: the resurrection.
SPK_0: But the good news is, is all of that plays out in actual events in the world, like a
SPK_0: super table or like actually taking a lower price on a piece of land because it's for
SPK_0: your daughter.
SPK_0: There's a million things you can do on the regular.
SPK_1: Or John, to reverse.
SPK_1: If you're in a...
SPK_1: In a higher position or paying a bigger price for a person you love, even if it's not a
SPK_1: market price.
SPK_1: That's right.
SPK_0: A hundred percent.
SPK_0: That's it.
SPK_0: It's a hundred percent.
SPK_0: And Christ speaks about this clearly.
SPK_0: The entire Christian tradition speaks about this.
SPK_0: It's how we gain our humanity.
SPK_0: These aren't like hard concepts, but they've become so difficult.
SPK_1: And then what happens?
SPK_1: Like the whole, again, rationality behind it would be you're inviting the good possibilities
SPK_1: which you couldn't have predicted.
SPK_0: Oh, I love that.
SPK_0: We talked about that yesterday.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_1: So you're inviting them.
SPK_0: The risk invites the opportunity that leads to the saintliness.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: To lead...
SPK_0: Agia, to holiness.
SPK_0: It's so cool.
SPK_0: Again, I'm blessed to have...
SPK_0: If anything happened to me in life that I'm happy to share is that all these foreign cultures
SPK_0: have taught me this.
SPK_0: That's why I don't...
SPK_0: Ice.
SPK_0: Listen, whatever ice is, I get it.
SPK_0: You got to obey the laws.
SPK_0: But ice as an entity, the spirit of ice, the spirit of ice is just...
SPK_1: It's not the creation spirit.
SPK_0: It's just antithetical to what...
SPK_0: Again, I want people who are here illegal to move.
SPK_0: We need jobs for the people here.
SPK_0: I get all the economics.
SPK_0: But masked men with guns, this does not work.
SPK_0: This is not an answer to the question.
SPK_0: It will do something.
SPK_0: It's not an answer to the spiritual question that we have.
SPK_0: We can get every single one of these foreign people out of our country and win and we will
SPK_0: be bereft of the spirit.
SPK_0: We will be dead.
SPK_0: These aren't concepts that are hard.
SPK_0: I just get so upset.
SPK_1: Well, because ultimately the debate is framed falsely.
SPK_1: You have the same problem.
SPK_1: It's literally a flipped coin of the segregation debate we had, the segregation story we had.
SPK_1: Is really big change, unprecedented, really happening?
SPK_1: If you listen to people on the right, they will be pretty real.
SPK_1: Sorry, you've been telling me for 30 years there is no replacement and now you are celebrating
SPK_1: it openly.
SPK_1: My pain been suppressed for decades.
SPK_1: You want me now to be nice?
SPK_1: I don't want you to be nice.
SPK_1: That's important.
SPK_1: But I do want you to be kind and you can't expect it to happen on a political level.
SPK_1: That's another problem.
SPK_1: You can't expect happening on a political level.
SPK_0: That's a little sad though.
SPK_1: It's sad, but it's unavoidable until people throw a table, until we truly reconnect.
SPK_1: But it just can't.
SPK_1: But that's the same story.
SPK_1: You've been suppressing pain, but now you're making the literally same mistake.
SPK_1: You're making an idol out of the pain.
SPK_0: It's nuts.
SPK_1: Instead of honoring the pain.
SPK_1: People thought and people hope that there will be some honoring the pain.
SPK_1: And that would lead to change and change will be good and it will restore the server
SPK_1: to order.
SPK_1: And there are ways to do it actually.
SPK_0: This will date the recording.
SPK_0: I don't know how long we got to go.
SPK_0: I got a piece.
SPK_0: Andrew, how are we doing out there?
SPK_0: I just want to say the story I read when I got up this morning, sadly, well, before
SPK_0: I said my prayers, I should probably have read it after I said my prayers.
SPK_0: Elon Musk is now saying that within three to five years, we won't talk to each other.
SPK_0: We'll just know each other's thoughts.
SPK_0: By the way, it's because of his product that he's apparently...
SPK_0: Neuralink?
SPK_0: Neuralink.
SPK_0: And he was so happy.
SPK_1: Lord have mercy.
SPK_0: And what I said, he was like, it gets rid of the difficulty of trying to use words to
SPK_0: describe an idea.
SPK_0: And I was like, this dude just trying to kill poets.
SPK_0: He's like literally trying to kill poetry.
SPK_1: Not just poetry, humanity.
SPK_1: I'm sorry.
SPK_1: That's what I'm saying.
SPK_1: There is a point it's being difficult.
SPK_1: It's difficult because it's not about expressing just ideas.
SPK_1: It's about expressing me.
SPK_1: I am not the sum of my ideas.
SPK_1: You are not the sum of your ideas.
SPK_1: That's again, it's based on the assumptions that a person is the sum of his thoughts
SPK_1: or experiences.
SPK_1: But it's neither.
SPK_1: It's way more than this.
SPK_0: But it's also an autistic guy's way to not have to explain himself because now you can
SPK_0: just understand the beauty of his thoughts directly.
SPK_1: But you can't.
SPK_1: I can guarantee you can know of them.
SPK_1: You can kind of know the data, but you won't see the beauty.
SPK_0: Of course.
SPK_0: You just, but no offense to whatever autism is, that way of thinking, you don't get to
SPK_0: be in charge just because you think that way.
SPK_0: But the problem is we keep putting these people in charge because they're good at the reason.
SPK_0: They're good at the stuff.
SPK_0: Can we have a revolution against these guys?
SPK_1: Throw a table.
SPK_0: Can we do it?
SPK_0: Throw a table.
SPK_0: Good.
SPK_0: I don't have to use guns.
SPK_1: You don't have to.
SPK_1: Guns would not help.
SPK_0: Plus he's going to have the best guns.
SPK_1: But you will have the best table.
SPK_0: Let's die at a table.
SPK_0: I actually know a Georgian guy that died at a supra because the soldiers came to kill
SPK_0: him.
SPK_0: And he threw the supra first and says, first before we fight, let's have supra.
SPK_0: He had supra and they killed him.
SPK_0: It was during the Abkhaz Civil War.
SPK_1: Civil War.
SPK_0: Isn't that nuts?
SPK_0: That's nuts.
SPK_0: And his family to this day is without him.
SPK_0: Obviously, but they honor him.
SPK_0: He did the thing.
SPK_0: There's a tradition in Georgia to say, wait, before we fight, we have supra.
SPK_0: We feast.
SPK_0: Afterwards, if we still want to fight, then we can fight.
SPK_0: That's very classic Georgian.
SPK_0: They're giving up the tactical advantage of hiding in the mountains and shooting your
SPK_0: enemy.
SPK_0: And that's what this guy actually-
SPK_1: Well, that's only a place of hope.
SPK_0: I know.
SPK_0: It's like, let's do something human first and then we'll see what happens.
SPK_0: I'll tell you one last story.
SPK_0: This is my last story.
SPK_0: I've told this story on my podcast maybe once.
SPK_0: It's the best story about Georgia.
SPK_0: It's just a way to get the flavor.
SPK_0: I'm in a hotel.
SPK_0: It's two years ago, two and a half maybe.
SPK_0: I'm with a woman, we'll call her Mariam.
SPK_0: She's Mary.
SPK_0: And I love her.
SPK_0: And I always stay at her hotel.
SPK_0: You guys should all too.
SPK_0: And it's awesome.
SPK_0: And I'm sitting there and she's crying.
SPK_0: She's not crying yet, but she's like, John, how are you?
SPK_0: I'm so tired.
SPK_0: And I'm like, what's going on?
SPK_0: She goes, all these Russians.
SPK_0: No offense to you.
SPK_0: And she's like, all these Russians.
SPK_0: I don't know what to do.
SPK_0: And I'm like, your hotel's filled with Russians.
SPK_0: I did it like the American merchant mind.
SPK_0: I was like, but you must be making so much money.
SPK_0: She goes, I'm full every night.
SPK_0: It's not this.
SPK_0: It's not the problem.
SPK_0: I was like, well, what's the problem?
SPK_0: It was the time when Putin had upgraded the-
SPK_1: When there was a 2008 war.
SPK_0: Yeah, the-
SPK_1: State of South Ossetia.
SPK_0: Yeah.
SPK_0: Oh no.
SPK_0: No, and he was inviting all the young men into the Ukrainian war.
SPK_1: Ah, so 2022.
SPK_1: I see.
SPK_0: Yeah, 2022.
SPK_0: And so many young men fled and they were all coming to Georgia.
SPK_0: And she's like, all these Russians, they're coming because they won't want to fight and
SPK_0: they don't know what to do.
SPK_0: And I was like, what do you mean?
SPK_0: You're giving them rooms.
SPK_0: You're getting rich.
SPK_0: She's like, John, please.
SPK_0: It's because of my people.
SPK_0: We should close the border.
SPK_0: Why do we have the border open?
SPK_0: And then she went, but we can't close the border.
SPK_0: We can't.
SPK_0: Why would we close the border?
SPK_0: And she's like fighting with herself.
SPK_0: And I was like, well, why can't you close the border?
SPK_0: We're Georgians.
SPK_0: Why?
SPK_0: This is strangers.
SPK_0: We can't let them not come.
SPK_0: But I don't want them to come.
SPK_0: When they come, they ruin our culture.
SPK_0: And I was like, I know, but your hotel's full.
SPK_0: And she's like, what's this have to do with anything?
SPK_0: We lose ourselves.
SPK_0: And I was like, well, then close the border.
SPK_0: It was really hilarious.
SPK_0: I wish there was a camera.
SPK_0: So I would go back and say, well, John, how can we close the border?
SPK_0: We're Georgians.
SPK_0: We have to bring them.
SPK_0: These young men.
SPK_1: For the context, most of these young men, especially, to give, I would imagine would
SPK_1: be pretty new world, like as new world.
SPK_0: Hot, tight, skinny jeans, whatever, Nike t-shirts, they don't even look like Russians.
SPK_0: I don't even know why.
SPK_0: You would listen.
SPK_0: You would look at them.
SPK_0: You go, there's an American.
SPK_0: No, it's not an American.
SPK_0: He's a Russian guy.
SPK_0: And anyway, she was just bemoaning.
SPK_0: And then she just started crying.
SPK_0: She goes, we will never close.
SPK_0: This is not, we will, it's always Georgia.
SPK_0: And then she went, we will always be defeated.
SPK_0: And somehow we will be here, but it's no fun.
SPK_0: This is my favorite scene.
SPK_0: Their victory is in the sacrifice.
SPK_0: It's nuts.
SPK_0: Now, again, now Georgians are like this.
SPK_0: There's Georgians watching this in New York.
SPK_0: They're like, I don't like that.
SPK_0: I'm a gangster.
SPK_0: I get it, bro.
SPK_0: You're a Westerner.
SPK_0: I got it.
SPK_0: But the old school, the people I met up in the mountains in the 90s during the Civil
SPK_0: War who were holding on to whatever Georgia was after the Soviet Union, those cats are
SPK_0: the people I'm describing.
SPK_0: I'm telling you.
SPK_0: They are.
SPK_0: And they'll cut you.
SPK_0: Don't dishonor their daughter.
SPK_1: Don't dishonor.
SPK_1: Yeah.
SPK_0: You get cut.
SPK_1: So let's hope what we talked today somehow honored the beautiful thing you're
SPK_1: doing, the beautiful thing which is coming through you, and let's hope it will bring
SPK_1: good fruit.